Now let's move to Phase 8. Production Kubernetes deployment.
We'll deploy the entire stack on AWS EKS using Helm.
The Helm chart packages all Kubernetes manifests into a single versioned, configurable unit.
The key design principle is never hardcode anything.
Every value that differs between environments lives in values.yaml.
And is overridden per environment.
First, create infrastructure/helm/Chart.yaml.
This defines the chart metadata.
apiVersion is v2. name is financial-rag-agent.
type is application. version is 0.1.0. appVersion is 1.0.0.
We add keywords like rag, fintech, llm, pgvector, and fastapi.
And maintainers with name Cloudfrugal and email.
Our chart structure is ready.
Now let's create the helpers template.
#[## [SECTION: Step 2 — Helpers Template (Component #76)]]
We'll put it in infrastructure/helm/templates/_helpers.tpl
First, define the name helper.
It expands the name of the chart using the nameOverride value.
It truncates to 63 characters and trims any trailing dash.
This enforces Kubernetes' label value limit.
Next, the fullname helper.
If fullnameOverride is provided, use it.
Otherwise, use the chart name.
The chart helper returns the chart name and version.
With plus signs replaced by underscores.
Now the labels helper.
This defines common labels applied to every resource.
It includes helm.sh/chart, app.kubernetes.io/managed-by, and app.kubernetes.io/version.
The selectorLabels helper is critical.
This is used in matchLabels and must be stable, never change.
It includes only app.kubernetes.io/name and app.kubernetes.io/instance.
No chart version here. If chart version changes, the selector would mismatch.
This is a common Helm mistake.
matchLabels is immutable after creation. If you include the chart version, every upgrade fails.
The image helper constructs the full image reference.
It takes a global registry, an image repository, and a tag.
If registry is provided, it returns registry slash repository colon tag.
If not, it returns repository colon tag.
This allows the registry to be set globally while repository and tag vary per component.
The podAnnotations helper merges global podAnnotations with per-component overrides.
It uses Helm's merge function for deep merging.
Our helpers template is complete.
Now let's create the base values.
#[## [SECTION: Step 3 — Base Values (Component #75)]]
Now let's create the base values.yaml file.
This defines the configuration for all environments.
First, the global section.
image registry is empty, pullPolicy is IfNotPresent.
podAnnotations, podLabels, nodeSelector, tolerations, and affinity are empty by default.
These will be overridden per environment.
The namespace is set to financial-rag.
Now the API section.
enabled is true. image repository is financial-rag-agent/api. tag is latest.
replicaCount is 2. resources requests are 500 millicpu and 512 megabytes.
limits are 1000 millicpu and 1 gigabyte.
service type is ClusterIP, port is 8000.
ingress is disabled by default.
env sets LOG_LEVEL to info and WORKERS to 2.
envFrom references a secret called financial-rag-secrets.
livenessProbe and readinessProbe both check /health on port 8000.
liveness has initialDelaySeconds 15, readiness has 10.
HPA is enabled with minReplicas 2, maxReplicas 6.
targetCPUUtilizationPercentage is 70, targetMemoryUtilizationPercentage is 80.
Now the agentPool section.
enabled is true. image repository is financial-rag-agent/agent. tag is latest.
replicaCount is 2. resources requests are 500 millicpu and 1 gigabyte.
limits are 2000 millicpu and 2 gigabytes.
env sets AGENT_CONCURRENCY to 4 and LOG_LEVEL to info.
livenessProbe checks /health on port 8001.
HPA is enabled with minReplicas 2, maxReplicas 8.
targetCPUUtilizationPercentage is 65, targetMemoryUtilizationPercentage is 75.
Now the ingestion CronJob.
enabled is true. image repository is financial-rag-agent/ingestion. tag is latest.
schedule is 0 2 asterisk asterisk asterisk, which is 2 AM UTC daily.
concurrencyPolicy is Forbid to prevent overlapping runs.
successfulJobsHistoryLimit and failedJobsHistoryLimit are both 3.
restartPolicy is OnFailure.
resources requests are 250 millicpu and 512 megabytes.
limits are 1000 millicpu and 1 gigabyte.
env sets INGESTION_BATCH_SIZE to 50 and LOG_LEVEL to info.
Now the pgvector StatefulSet.
enabled is true. image repository is pgvector/pgvector. tag is pg16.
replicaCount is 1. resources requests are 500 millicpu and 1 gigabyte.
limits are 2000 millicpu and 4 gigabytes.
storage uses storageClassName gp3 and size 50 gigabytes.
service port is 5432.
env sets POSTGRES_DB to financial_rag and POSTGRES_USER to raguser.
envFrom references the financial-rag-secrets secret.
persistence is enabled.
livenessProbe and readinessProbe use pg_isready.
Now the Redis StatefulSet.
enabled is true. image repository is redis. tag is 7-alpine.
replicaCount is 1. resources requests are 100 millicpu and 256 megabytes.
limits are 500 millicpu and 512 megabytes.
storage uses storageClassName gp3 and size 10 gigabytes.
service port is 6379.
args enable appendonly, set maxmemory to 400 megabytes, and maxmemory-policy to allkeys-lru.
livenessProbe and readinessProbe use redis-cli ping.
Finally, the serviceMonitor.
enabled is false by default. namespace is monitoring.
interval is 30 seconds. path is slash metrics.
Our base values are complete.
Every workload follows a consistent pattern.
#[## [SECTION: Step 4 — Production Values Override (Component #99)]]
Now let's create the production values override file.
We'll put it in infrastructure/helm/values.prod.yaml
These override only the keys that differ from base values.
Helm merges the two files when deploying.
First, global section.
image registry is set to your ECR registry URL. pullPolicy becomes Always.
nodeSelector sets role to application.
tolerations for dedicated application nodes.
podAnnotations enable prometheus.io/scrape and set the port to 8000.
Now the API production overrides.
replicaCount is 5. image tag is pinned to 1.0.0, never latest in production.
resources requests are 1000 millicpu and 1 gigabyte.
limits are 2000 millicpu and 2 gigabytes.
env sets LOG_LEVEL to warning and WORKERS to 4.
ingress is enabled. className is alb.
annotations configure the AWS ALB for internet-facing traffic.
target-type is ip. listen-ports is HTTPS 443.
ssl-redirect is enabled. certificate-arn must be set.
healthcheck-path is slash health.
group.name is financial-rag-prod.
host is api.financial-rag.cloudfrugal.com.
tls secretName is financial-rag-tls.
HPA minReplicas is 5, maxReplicas is 20.
targetCPUUtilizationPercentage is 60, targetMemoryUtilizationPercentage is 70.
Now the agentPool production overrides.
replicaCount is 5. image tag is 1.0.0.
resources requests are 2000 millicpu and 4 gigabytes.
limits are 4000 millicpu and 8 gigabytes.
env sets AGENT_CONCURRENCY to 8 and LOG_LEVEL to warning.
HPA minReplicas is 5, maxReplicas is 25.
targetCPUUtilizationPercentage is 55, targetMemoryUtilizationPercentage is 65.
Now the ingestion production overrides.
image tag is 1.0.0. schedule is 0 1 asterisk asterisk asterisk, which is 1 AM UTC.
resources requests are 1000 millicpu and 2 gigabytes.
limits are 2000 millicpu and 4 gigabytes.
env sets INGESTION_BATCH_SIZE to 200 and LOG_LEVEL to warning.
Now the pgvector production overrides.
resources requests are 2000 millicpu and 8 gigabytes.
limits are 4000 millicpu and 16 gigabytes.
storage size is 500 gigabytes, storageClassName is gp3-iops.
Now the Redis production overrides.
resources requests are 500 millicpu and 2 gigabytes.
limits are 1000 millicpu and 4 gigabytes.
storage size is 50 gigabytes.
maxmemory is 3500 megabytes.
Finally, the serviceMonitor is enabled.
namespace is monitoring. interval is 15 seconds.
Key production differences.
Never use latest tag in production. If a pod restarts and pulls a new latest image, your production environment silently changes.
Always pin to a specific semver tag or git SHA in production.
Our production values override is complete.
#[## [SECTION: Step 5 — StatefulSets: pgvector and Redis (Components #78–80)]]
Now let's understand StatefulSets for pgvector and Redis.
Why StatefulSet, not Deployment?
Deployments are for stateless workloads. Pods are interchangeable.
If a pod is replaced, local storage is lost.
That's fine for the API. State lives in PostgreSQL.
But catastrophic for PostgreSQL itself.
StatefulSets provide stable pod names.
fra-pgvector-0, not fra-pgvector-abc123.
They provide stable DNS for pod-to-pod communication.
And ordered startup and shutdown.
Most importantly, volumeClaimTemplates create a dedicated PVC per pod.
Each replica has its own persistent storage.
The pgvector StatefulSet defines the image, ports, and environment variables.
It mounts pgdata from a volumeClaimTemplate.
If persistence is enabled, it creates a PVC named pgdata.
With storageClassName and size from values.
Two services for pgvector.
A headless service with clusterIP None for stable DNS.
And a regular ClusterIP service that load-balances.
The API uses the regular service for read-write operations.
The Redis StatefulSet follows the same pattern.
Stable pod names, persistent storage, headless service.
Redis args enable appendonly persistence and set maxmemory-policy to allkeys-lru.
This is the correct eviction policy for a cache.
Our StatefulSets are complete.
pgvector and Redis now have persistent storage.
#[## [SECTION: Step 6 — API and Agent Deployments (Components #81, #84)]]
Now let's create the API and Agent Deployments.
First, the security context applied to every workload.
runAsNonRoot true prevents running as user ID zero.
allowPrivilegeEscalation false prevents setuid binaries from gaining root.
readOnlyRootFilesystem true prevents writing to the container filesystem.
capabilities drop ALL removes all Linux kernel capabilities.
This is defense in depth.
readOnlyRootFilesystem requires a tmp volume mounted at slash tmp.
We add an emptyDir volume for temporary files.
The rolling update strategy controls how pods are replaced.
maxUnavailable one means at most one pod is down during upgrade.
maxSurge two means at most two extra pods can run during upgrade.
With five replicas in production, you have fast rollouts without interruption.
The API Deployment includes livenessProbe and readinessProbe on port 8000.
ServiceAccountName is set to the API service account.
The Agent Deployment has an in-memory model cache.
emptyDir with medium Memory, size limit 500 megabytes.
This is a tmpfs filesystem stored in RAM.
The local embedding model stays in memory between requests.
Both Deployments have a ClusterIP service for internal communication.
The API service is used by the ALB Ingress.
The Agent service is only for health checks, not external traffic.
Our Deployments are complete.
#[## [SECTION: Step 7 — HPAs (Components #83, #85)]]
Now let's configure HorizontalPodAutoscalers.
The API HPA scales on CPU and memory utilization.
Target CPU utilization is 70 percent, memory is 80 percent.
Minimum replicas 2, maximum 20 in production.
The Agent HPA has lower thresholds, 55 percent CPU and 65 percent memory.
Agent loops are CPU-spiky during embedding and LLM inference.
Both HPAs have asymmetric scale-up and scale-down behavior.
Scale up fast, scale down slow.
The API scales up 4 pods per minute after a 60 second stabilization window.
It scales down 2 pods per 2 minutes after a 5 minute window.
The Agent scales up 5 pods per minute after just 30 seconds.
But it scales down only 1 pod per 3 minutes after a 10 minute window.
Why the difference? Agent reasoning loops can run for 30 to 60 seconds.
Removing a pod mid-loop drops the request.
Our HPAs are complete.
The API and Agent will scale automatically based on load.
#[## [SECTION: Step 8 — Ingestion CronJob (Component #86)]]
Now let's create the Ingestion CronJob.
schedule is set from values, default 2 AM UTC.
concurrencyPolicy Forbid is critical.
Without it, if one job runs longer than expected, the next starts concurrently.
Two concurrent ingestion jobs would exceed EDGAR's rate limit.
And could corrupt the deduplication logic.
activeDeadlineSeconds is a 3 hour hard cap.
If the job runs longer than that, Kubernetes kills it.
backoffLimit 2 means it retries at most twice on failure.
The job uses a service account with IRSA annotations.
Same security context as other workloads.
readOnlyRootFilesystem true with a tmp emptyDir.
Our ingestion CronJob is complete.
#[## [SECTION: Step 9 — ALB Ingress (Component #87)]]
Now let's create the ALB Ingress.
This creates an AWS Application Load Balancer for external traffic.
target-type ip routes traffic directly to pod IPs.
Avoids the double-hop through kube-proxy.
ip mode requires pods to be in subnets the ALB can reach.
Use private subnets with the ALB in public subnets.
group.name allows multiple Ingress objects to share one ALB.
Without grouping, each Ingress creates a new ALB.
That would cost about $0.008 per hour, per ALB.
Grouping saves money and management overhead.
The Ingress routes all traffic to the API service.
TLS is terminated at the ALB using an ACM certificate.
Our ALB Ingress is complete.
#[## [SECTION: Step 10 — ServiceMonitor (Component #88)]]
Now let's create the Prometheus ServiceMonitor.
This tells Prometheus to scrape metrics from the API.
The label release equals kube-prometheus-stack is not arbitrary.
The Prometheus operator only picks up ServiceMonitors that match its label selector.
If you installed kube-prometheus-stack with a different release name, change this label.
namespaceSelector matches the financial-rag namespace.
selector matches pods with component api.
endpoints specify port http, path slash metrics, interval 30 seconds.
honorLabels true preserves existing metric labels.
Our ServiceMonitor is complete.
Prometheus will now scrape API metrics.
[## [SECTION: PART 2 — KARPENTER NODE PROVISIONING]]
#[## [SECTION: Step 11 — Karpenter IAM Role (Component #89)]]
Now let's configure Karpenter for node provisioning.
Karpenter is AWS's modern node autoscaler for Kubernetes.
Unlike the Cluster Autoscaler, Karpenter launches nodes directly.
It is much faster and more efficient.
First, create the Karpenter IAM role.
We use eksctl to create the service account.
The role needs permissions to run and terminate EC2 instances.
Describe instances and instance types.
iam PassRole to pass the node IAM role to new instances.
And SSM GetParameter for AMI discovery.
#[## [SECTION: Step 12 — Karpenter Installation (Component #90)]]
Now install Karpenter using the Helm chart.
Version 0.37.0 is stable.
The service account annotation sets the IAM role.
Cluster name and interruption queue are required settings.
Karpenter will now manage node scaling.
It launches nodes when pods are pending and consolidates when nodes are underutilized.
#[## [SECTION: Step 13 — EC2NodeClass and NodePools (Components #91–93)]]
Now create the EC2NodeClass.
This defines what kind of EC2 instances Karpenter can launch.
amiFamily is Amazon Linux 2.
The role is KarpenterNodeRole, which we create separately.
Subnet selector terms look for tags.
karpenter.sh slash discovery equals the cluster name.
Security group selector terms use the same tag.
Block device mapping uses gp3 with 50 gigabytes, encrypted.
User data runs the EKS bootstrap script.
This joins the node to the cluster.
Now create the first NodePool for the API.
This uses on-demand instances.
On-demand nodes have consistent latency and no interruption risk.
Perfect for the API service.
Instance families are m5, m6i, and m6a.
General purpose, consistent performance.
Instance sizes are xlarge and 2xlarge.
A taint prevents pods that don't tolerate it from scheduling here.
Disruption policy is WhenUnderutilized.
It consolidates after 5 minutes.
Now create the second NodePool for ingestion.
This uses spot instances.
Spot instances are up to 70 percent cheaper than on-demand.
But they can be interrupted at any time.
Ingestion is idempotent. SHA-256 deduplication prevents duplicates.
If a spot instance is interrupted, the job just retries.
Diverse instance families like m5, m6i, c5, and c6i.
Better spot availability across different types.
Disruption policy is WhenEmpty, not WhenUnderutilized.
It consolidates after just 30 seconds.
Why the difference? Spot nodes are ephemeral.
Don't keep expensive nodes idle longer than necessary.
Apply all three resources with kubectl apply.
EC2NodeClass, api-ondemand NodePool, and ingestion-spot NodePool.
Karpenter node provisioning is complete.
The cluster can now scale dynamically and cost-effectively.
[## [SECTION: PART 3 — TERRAGRUNT INFRASTRUCTURE]]
#[## [SECTION: Step 14 — Terragrunt Root Config (Component #94)]]
Now let's set up Terragrunt for infrastructure provisioning.
Terragrunt wraps Terraform to provide DRY infrastructure code.
One module definition, multiple environment instantiations.
Dev, staging, and prod each get their own configuration.
First, create the root terragrunt.hcl file.
This is inherited by every environment module.
The locals block reads the environment configuration.
It finds env.hcl in the parent folder.
We extract the aws region, account ID, project name, and environment name.
The env name comes from the directory name.
Next, remote state configuration.
State is stored in S3 with DynamoDB for locking.
The bucket name combines project, account ID, and region.
The key includes environment and module path.
DynamoDB table prevents concurrent state modifications.
This is critical for team workflows.
Terragrunt generates the provider configuration at plan time.
It writes a provider.tf file into each module directory.
We define required providers. AWS, Kubernetes, Helm, TLS, and Random.
All with specific version constraints.
The AWS provider has default tags.
Project, environment, managed by, owner, and repo.
This tags every AWS resource automatically.
No need to add tags manually to each resource.
Finally, common inputs are passed to every module.
Project name, environment, AWS region, and account ID.
Each module can access these without re-declaring them.
Our root Terragrunt config is complete.
#[## [SECTION: Step 15 — Environment Configs (Component #99)]]
Now let's create the environment configurations.
First, dev environment in env.hcl.
Development uses smaller, cheaper resources.
VPC CIDR is 10.2.0.0 slash 16.
Two private subnets, two public subnets, two availability zones.
EKS cluster version 1.29.
Node groups are t3 dot large for application, t3 dot medium for ingestion.
Minimal sizes to keep costs low.
RDS uses db.t3.medium with 20 gigabytes of storage.
Backup retention is just 1 day. Multi-AZ is false.
ElastiCache uses cache.t3.micro with one node.
Now staging environment.
Staging should mirror production as closely as possible.
VPC CIDR is 10.1.0.0 slash 16.
EKS version is still 1.29.
Node groups use m5 dot xlarge for application, c5 dot large for ingestion.
Larger instances than dev.
RDS uses db.r6g.large with 100 gigabytes of storage.
Backup retention is 7 days.
ElastiCache uses cache.r6g.large.
Still single node to save cost.
Finally, production environment.
This is where the actual costs run.
VPC CIDR is 10.30.0.0 slash 16.
Three private subnets, three public subnets, three availability zones.
EKS cluster version 1.30, the latest stable.
Node groups are for system workloads only.
Note that Karpenter handles application and ingestion nodes.
The managed node group only runs system components.
RDS uses db.r6g.xlarge with 500 gigabytes of storage.
Backup retention is 30 days. Multi-AZ is true for high availability.
ElastiCache uses cache.r6g.large with two nodes.
Multi-AZ is true. Redis replicates across availability zones.
Our environment configs are complete.
Each environment has its own isolated state and resources.
#[## [SECTION: Step 16 — Terragrunt Module Configs (Component #100)]]
Now let's configure the Terragrunt child modules.
Each module handles one piece of infrastructure.
Every module includes the root configuration and the environment configuration.
The terraform source points to the module directory.
Inputs come from the environment locals.
Modules declare dependencies on other modules.
The EKS module depends on the VPC module.
The RDS module depends on VPC and EKS.
ElastiCache depends on VPC and EKS.
IAM depends on EKS and RDS for OIDC and secret ARNs.
Terragrunt automatically orders applies based on these dependencies.
Notice the mock_outputs in each dependency block.
These are used during terragrunt plan.
If the dependency hasn't been applied yet, mock outputs stand in.
This allows planning the entire stack at once.
The ECR module is account-level, no VPC or EKS dependency.
The S3 module is special. It creates the state bucket itself.
It has a chicken-and-egg problem.
You need S3 for remote state, but you need Terraform to create S3.
The solution is to apply the S3 module first with a local backend.
After the bucket exists, all other modules use it as remote state.
Our Terragrunt module configs are complete.
#[## [SECTION: Step 17 — Apply Order]]
Now let's talk about apply order.
Terragrunt automatically orders applies based on dependencies.
VPC first, then EKS, then RDS and ElastiCache in parallel, then IAM.
To apply a full environment, go to the environment directory.
Run terragrunt run-all apply with non-interactive flag.
To apply a single module, cd into its directory.
Then run terragrunt apply.
The bootstrap sequence for a new environment is.
First, cd into the S3 module and apply it.
Then you can apply all other modules.
The state backend is now configured.
Our Terragrunt infrastructure is complete.
The entire AWS stack is now codified and repeatable.
#[## [SECTION: Step 18 — Deploy the Helm Chart]]
Now that infrastructure is provisioned, let's deploy the Helm chart.
This installs the entire application on Kubernetes.
First, create the namespace.
kubectl create namespace financial-rag.
Then create the secrets. For production, these come from Vault.
For first deployment, you can create them manually.
Always do a dry-run before deploying.
helm upgrade with dash dry-run and dash debug.
This renders all templates and validates against the Kubernetes API.
It catches syntax errors before anything changes.
Then deploy with dash wait and dash timeout 10 minutes.
Helm waits for all pods to become ready before completing.
Verify with kubectl get pods.
You should see five pods running.
API pods, agent pods, pgvector statefulset, and redis statefulset.
All with status Running.
Our Helm deployment is complete.
The application is now running on Kubernetes.
#[## [SECTION: Common Errors and Fixes — Phase 8]]
Let me walk through common errors in Phase 8.
And how to fix them.
Error one. field is immutable on upgrade.
The cause is helm.sh/chart in matchLabels.
The fix is to use selectorLabels in matchLabels.
And put helm.sh/chart only in metadata labels.
Error two. ImagePullBackOff.
ECR is not authenticated.
Run aws ecr get-login-password and pipe to docker login.
Or verify your IRSA role has ECR pull permissions.
Error three. PVC stuck in Pending.
The gp3 storage class is not installed.
Install the EBS CSI driver.
eksctl utils install-ebs-csi-driver.
Error four. no nodes available.
Karpenter is not provisioning nodes.
Check the Karpenter controller logs.
kubectl logs dash n karpenter deployment slash karpenter.
Error five. HPA not scaling.
The metrics server is not installed.
Apply the metrics server components from GitHub.
This provides the CPU and memory metrics that HPAs need.
Error six. terragrunt S3 bucket not found.
The state bucket hasn't been created yet.
Apply the S3 module first with local backend.
Then all other modules use it as remote state.
Error seven. dependency cycle between modules.
Your dependencies form a circle.
Check each dependency.config_path.
The graph must be a directed acyclic graph, or DAG.
Error eight. ingestion pod not scheduled.
Missing spot capacity in your region.
Add more instance families to the spot nodepool.
Diverse families have better spot availability.
Error nine. connection refused to pgvector.
The pod is not yet ready.
Check the readiness probe. pg_isready must pass before traffic is sent.
The pod may still be initializing.
Bookmark this section.
When you hit an error, you'll know exactly where to look.
#[## [SECTION: What's Next — Phase 9]]
Now let me preview Phase 9.
In Phase 9, we implement GitOps and zero-trust networking.
ArgoCD for continuous delivery and Cilium eBPF networking.
You'll learn the App of Apps pattern.
One root ApplicationSet manages all environments.
Three-environment promotion pipeline.
Dev auto-syncs, staging auto-syncs, prod manual sync only.
ArgoCD Project with RBAC roles and sync windows.
No prod deploys during business hours.
Cilium replacing kube-proxy with eBPF.
Deny-all NetworkPolicy with DNS egress exception.
L7 HTTP policies. Cilium enforces allowed HTTP methods and paths at the kernel level.
Istio service mesh for mTLS between services.
Hubble and Cilium ServiceMonitors for Prometheus.
Full network observability.
The file tree for Phase 9 will include.
argocd/bootstrap/bootstrap.sh.
argocd/projects/financial-rag-project.yaml.
argocd/appsets/apps-appset.yaml.
cilium/network-policies/default-deny-all.yaml.
cilium/network-policies/api-l7-policy.yaml.
istio-mesh/authorization-policies.yaml.
istio-mesh/destination-rules.yaml.
Phase 8 is complete.
Your Kubernetes infrastructure is production-ready.
In Phase 9, we add GitOps and zero-trust networking.
The cluster becomes fully automated and secure.
Ready to proceed to Phase 9?
---
**End of Phase 8. Phase 9 covers GitOps and Zero-Trust Networking. Shall I continue?**