Now let's move to Phase 11. End-to-end observability.
Logs, metrics, traces, and alerts all connected.
First, create the observability namespace.
kubectl create namespace observability
Create the monitoring namespace if not already created.
kubectl create namespace monitoring
Now install the LGTM stack via Helm.
Loki for logs, Grafana for dashboards, Tempo for traces, Mimir for metrics.
Add the Grafana Helm repository.
helm repo add grafana https://grafana.github.io/helm-charts
Install Loki for log aggregation.
helm upgrade dash dash install loki grafana/loki with namespace observability.
Set loki.storage.type to s3.
Set bucket names for chunks and ruler. Set region to us-east-1.
Install Tempo for distributed tracing storage.
helm upgrade dash dash install tempo grafana/tempo-distributed with namespace observability.
Set storage.trace.backend to s3.
Set bucket name and region.
Install Mimir for long-term metrics.
helm upgrade dash dash install mimir grafana/mimir-distributed with namespace observability.
Set mimir structured config common storage backend to s3.
Set bucket name and region.
Install Grafana for visualization.
helm upgrade dash dash install grafana grafana/grafana with namespace observability.
Set persistence enabled to true.
Set admin password from environment variable.
Configure datasources using the datasources.yaml file.
Our LGTM stack is installed.
[## [SECTION: Step 2 — OpenTelemetry Dependencies (Component #157)]]
Now add OpenTelemetry dependencies to pyproject.toml.
Add opentelemetry-api version 1.24.0 or higher.
Add opentelemetry-sdk version 1.24.0 or higher.
Add opentelemetry-exporter-otlp-proto-grpc version 1.24.0 or higher.
This exports traces to the OpenTelemetry Collector.
Add opentelemetry-instrumentation-fastapi version 0.45b0 or higher.
This instruments FastAPI automatically.
Add opentelemetry-instrumentation-sqlalchemy version 0.45b0 or higher.
This instruments SQLAlchemy queries.
Add opentelemetry-instrumentation-redis version 0.45b0 or higher.
This instruments Redis calls.
Add opentelemetry-instrumentation-httpx version 0.45b0 or higher.
This instruments HTTPX requests to LLM APIs.
Add opentelemetry-instrumentation-logging version 0.45b0 or higher.
This injects trace IDs into logs.
Install the dependencies.
pip install minus e dot dev.
Our OpenTelemetry dependencies are ready.
Now let's configure the tracer provider.
[## [SECTION: Step 3 — Tracer Provider Configuration (Components #158–165)]]
Now let's create the tracer provider configuration.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/telemetry/tracing.py
First, imports. We need logging and os.
From opentelemetry, we import trace.
From opentelemetry.exporter.otlp.proto.grpc.trace_exporter, import OTLPSpanExporter.
This exports spans to the OpenTelemetry Collector.
From opentelemetry.instrumentation.fastapi, import FastAPIInstrumentor.
From opentelemetry.instrumentation.httpx, import HTTPXClientInstrumentor.
From opentelemetry.instrumentation.logging, import LoggingInstrumentor.
From opentelemetry.instrumentation.redis, import RedisInstrumentor.
From opentelemetry.instrumentation.sqlalchemy, import SQLAlchemyInstrumentor.
From opentelemetry.sdk.resources, import Resource.
From opentelemetry.sdk.trace, import TracerProvider.
From opentelemetry.sdk.trace.export, import BatchSpanProcessor, ConsoleSpanExporter.
From opentelemetry.sdk.trace.sampling, import ParentBased, TraceIdRatioBased.
Now define the configure_tracing function.
It takes an optional FastAPI app and optional SQLAlchemy engine.
First, create the resource.
It identifies this service in all traces.
Resource includes service name, service version, service namespace.
Deployment environment, Kubernetes namespace, and Kubernetes pod name.
Next, create the sampler.
ParentBased with root TraceIdRatioBased at SAMPLING_RATE.
SAMPLING_RATE defaults to 0.01 which is 1 percent.
This means 99 percent of successful, fast traces are dropped at the SDK before export.
The OpenTelemetry Collector then applies tail sampling.
After seeing the full trace, it keeps 100 percent of error traces regardless of head sampling.
Create the TracerProvider with resource and sampler.
Create the OTLP exporter pointing to the OpenTelemetry Collector.
Set insecure equals True for development, False for production.
Add a batch span processor to the provider.
If environment is dev, add a console exporter for local debugging.
Set the provider as the global tracer provider.
Now instrument FastAPI.
Call FastAPIInstrumentor.instrument_app with the app.
Exclude health and metrics endpoints.
They generate thousands of spans with zero debugging value.
Add a server request hook to tag agent spans.
If the path contains slash query, set component to query-endpoint.
Now instrument SQLAlchemy.
Call SQLAlchemyInstrumentor.instrument with the sync engine.
Enable commenter to add traceparent comment to SQL queries.
This allows you to find the exact trace ID from a slow query log.
Now instrument Redis.
Call RedisInstrumentor.instrument.
Now instrument httpx.
Call HTTPXClientInstrumentor.instrument with a request hook.
The request hook adds LLM provider info to outbound spans.
If the URL contains openai, set llm.provider to openai.
If the URL contains groq, set llm.provider to groq.
If the URL contains azure, set llm.provider to azure-openai.
Finally, instrument logging.
LoggingInstrumentor.instrument with set_logging_format equals True.
This adds trace_id and span_id to every Python log record.
Combined with Loki's Grafana datasource, you can click a log line and jump directly to the trace.
Define the get_tracer function.
It returns a named tracer for manual instrumentation.
Now wire it into server.py lifespan.
Call configure_tracing before initialising dependencies.
This ensures DB connection spans are captured from the start.
Our tracer provider configuration is complete.
[## [SECTION: Step 4 — Custom RAG Spans (Components #162–164)]]
Auto-instrumentation covers HTTP, DB, and Redis.
The RAG-specific operations need manual spans.
First, add spans to the embedding client.
In embeddings.py, import get_tracer from telemetry.
Create a tracer named financial_rag.embeddings.
In embed_texts, create a span named rag.embedding.
Set attributes on the span.
embedding.provider, embedding.text_count, embedding.dimensions.
This shows exactly how long embedding takes for each batch.
Next, add spans to the hybrid searcher.
In hybrid_search.py, import get_tracer from telemetry.
Create a tracer named financial_rag.search.
In the search method, create a span named rag.search.
Set attributes. search.type, search.question_length, search.alpha.
After the search, set search.results_count.
This shows how long vector and text search take combined.
Next, add spans to the query engine.
In query_engine.py, import get_tracer from telemetry.
Create a tracer named financial_rag.llm.
In _generate_answer, create a span named rag.llm.
Set attributes. llm.model, llm.provider, llm.analysis_style, llm.context_length.
This shows exactly how long LLM inference takes.
These three spans produce a flame graph in Jaeger.
It shows exactly where time is spent in a RAG query.
HTTP POST slash query takes 400 milliseconds total.
rag.embedding takes 45 milliseconds.
rag.search takes 180 milliseconds.
pgvector query takes 90 milliseconds automatically from SQLAlchemy instrumentation.
redis get takes 5 milliseconds automatically from Redis instrumentation.
rag.llm takes 170 milliseconds.
httpx POST takes 165 milliseconds automatically from httpx instrumentation.
Our custom RAG spans are complete.
[## [SECTION: Step 5 — OpenTelemetry Collector (Component #158)]]
Now let's configure the OpenTelemetry Collector.
We'll put it in observability/tracing/tracer-provider.yaml
The collector receives traces from the FastAPI application.
It processes and exports them to multiple backends.
Receivers. otlp protocol with grpc on port 4317 and http on port 4318.
Processors. resource adds attributes to all spans.
service.namespace to financial-rag, deployment.environment from namespace.
Batch processor for performance.
timeout 5 seconds, send batch size 1024, send batch max size 2048.
Tail sampling processor. This is the most important part.
decision_wait is 10 seconds. num_traces is 100000.
expected_new_traces_per_sec is 500.
Policies. errors-policy based on status code.
Keep 100 percent of error traces.
slow-traces-policy based on latency threshold 2000 milliseconds.
Keep 100 percent of slow traces.
llm-traces-policy based on string attribute component equals llm-client or agent.
Keep 100 percent of LLM-related traces.
probabilistic-policy with sampling percentage 1 percent.
Keep only 1 percent of everything else.
Memory limiter prevents OOM on trace bursts.
Check interval 1 second, limit 512 megabytes, spike limit 128 megabytes.
Exporters. jaeger for in-cluster trace visualization.
endpoint is jaeger-collector.monitoring.svc.cluster.local port 14250.
awsxray for prod trace storage with 30-day retention.
region us-east-1.
prometheus exporter for trace-based metrics.
endpoint port 8889, namespace financial_rag.
Service pipelines.
traces pipeline uses otlp receiver, memory_limiter, resource, tail_sampling, batch processors.
Exporters are jaeger and awsxray.
Metrics pipeline uses otlp receiver, memory_limiter, resource, batch processors.
Exporter is prometheus.
Apply the collector configuration.
kubectl apply -f observability/tracing/tracer-provider.yaml
Apply Jaeger for dev and staging.
kubectl apply -f observability/tracing/jaeger-install.yaml
Our OpenTelemetry Collector is complete.
Traces now flow from the application to Jaeger and X-Ray.
[## [SECTION: Step 6 — Structured JSON Logging (Component #166)]]
Now let's add structured JSON logging.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/api/logging_config.py
First, imports. We need logging and structlog.
From opentelemetry, we import trace.
Define the configure_logging function.
It loads settings from get_settings.
Define shared_processors list.
structlog.contextvars.merge_contextvars, structlog.stdlib.add_logger_name.
structlog.stdlib.add_log_level, structlog.processors.TimeStamper with fmt iso.
And _add_trace_context to inject trace ID and span ID.
If LOG_FORMAT is json, add JSONRenderer for production.
If not, add ConsoleRenderer for development.
Configure structlog with the processors.
Set wrapper_class to structlog.make_filtering_bound_logger with the log level.
Set logger_factory to structlog.PrintLoggerFactory.
Now define the _add_trace_context function.
It gets the current span from OpenTelemetry.
If the span exists and is recording, add trace_id and span_id to the event_dict.
Format trace_id as 32 hex characters, span_id as 16 hex characters.
Call configure_logging at the start of the lifespan function.
Before any other imports that might call logging.getLogger.
Our structured logging is complete.
Every log line now contains trace_id and span_id for correlation.
[## [SECTION: Step 7 — SLO Recording Rules and Alerts (Components #172–173)]]
Now let's create SLO recording rules and alerts.
We'll put them in observability/slo/slo-rules.yaml
Three SLOs defined.
SLO-1. API availability at 99.5 percent.
Error budget over 30 days is 3.65 hours of downtime.
SLO-2. Query latency P99 under 120 seconds for 95 percent of requests.
5 percent of requests can be slow.
SLO-3. Ingestion success rate at 99 percent over 7 days.
1 percent of filings can fail.
First, recording rules for SLO-1 availability.
good requests equals non-5xx status codes.
record financial_rag:api_request_success:rate5m.
Sum of rate of successful requests divided by sum of rate of all requests.
Record error rates for different time windows.
1 hour, 6 hours, 24 hours, and 72 hours.
Now alerting rules for SLO-1.
Fast burn alert at 14.4 times the error rate.
Burns 2 percent of monthly budget in 1 hour.
Pages immediately.
Slow burn alert at 6 times the error rate.
Burns 5 percent of monthly budget in 6 hours.
Warning level, investigate today.
Now SLO-2 for query latency.
Use http_request_duration_seconds_bucket with le 120.
Calculate the ratio of requests under 120 seconds.
Same multi-window multi-burn-rate approach.
SLO-3 for ingestion success.
Record financial_rag:ingestion_success_rate:rate24h.
Sum of processed total divided by sum of processed total plus failed total.
Alert if success rate is below 99 percent for 30 minutes.
Now create the SLO alerting rules in a separate file.
observability/slo/slo-alerts.yaml
Page alert when burns more than 2 percent budget in 1 hour.
Fast burn 14.4 times error rate.
Warning alert when burns more than 5 percent budget in 6 hours.
Slow burn 6 times error rate.
Apply the rules.
kubectl apply -f observability/slo/slo-rules.yaml
kubectl apply -f observability/slo/slo-alerts.yaml
Our SLO recording rules and alerts are complete.
Error budget is now monitored and alertable.
[## [SECTION: Step 8 — ArgoCD Notifications (Component #116 wiring)]]
Now let's configure ArgoCD notifications.
We'll put them in argocd/notifications/templates.yaml
First, define the Slack service.
token from environment variable, username ArgoCD, icon colon argo colon.
Define the PagerDuty service.
serviceKeys with prod-oncall from environment variable.
Define the app-sync-succeeded template.
Slack attachment with green color.
Title shows the app name synced.
Fields include environment and revision.
Define the app-sync-failed template.
Slack attachment with red color.
Title shows the app name sync FAILED.
Fields include environment and error message.
PagerDuty summary. ArgoCD sync failed colon app name.
Severity error.
Define the app-health-degraded template.
Slack attachment with yellow color.
Title shows the app name health DEGRADED.
Field includes health status.
PagerDuty summary. App degraded colon app name.
Severity warning.
Define triggers.
on-sync-succeeded triggers when operationState phase is Succeeded.
on-sync-failed triggers when operationState phase is Error or Failed.
on-health-degraded triggers when health status is Degraded.
Set default triggers to on-sync-failed and on-health-degraded.
Sync succeeded is optional, only for info.
Apply the notifications.
kubectl apply -f argocd/notifications/templates.yaml
The PagerDuty integration only fires on prod application failures.
The annotation uses environment-oncall which only resolves in prod.
Our ArgoCD notifications are complete.
Deployment status now goes to Slack and PagerDuty.
[## [SECTION: Step 9 — OPA Rego Policies (CI enforcement)]]
Now let's create OPA Rego policies for CI enforcement.
Three policy files and a test file.
First, k8s_admission.rego. Pod admission rules.
These run in CI via conftest and optionally at admission via OPA Gatekeeper.
Rule one. No latest image tags in production.
Every image must have a pinned tag.
Rule two. All containers must declare resource requests AND limits.
HPA requires requests. Limits prevent noisy-neighbour OOM on shared nodes.
Rule three. readOnlyRootFilesystem must be true.
Writable root filesystem allows post-exploit persistence.
Rule four. allowPrivilegeEscalation must be false.
Prevents setuid binary escalation.
Rule five. Must not run as root.
runAsNonRoot true at pod level, or runAsUser greater than 0 at container level.
Rule six. No host network, host PID, host IPC.
These grant access to the node's namespaces.
Rule seven. ALL capabilities must be dropped.
Privileged containers are also denied.
Rule eight. Required labels must be present.
app.kubernetes.io/name and app.kubernetes.io/component.
Now helm_policy.rego. Helm manifest rules.
Checks for deprecated Kubernetes APIs.
Rule one. No autoscaling/v2beta1 or batch/v1beta1.
These are removed in Kubernetes 1.29.
Rule two. HPA must use autoscaling/v2.
v1 does not support multi-metric scaling.
Rule three. CronJob must have concurrencyPolicy.
Set to Forbid for ingestion jobs.
Rule four. StatefulSet must have serviceName.
Headless service required for stable DNS.
Now terraform_policy.rego. Infrastructure rules.
Checks Terraform plan JSON for misconfigurations.
Rule one. S3 buckets must block public ACLs.
block_public_acls true, restrict_public_buckets true.
Rule two. S3 encryption required.
Server-side encryption must be configured.
Rule three. RDS must have storage encryption.
storage_encrypted true. Not publicly accessible.
Rule four. RDS must have backup retention.
backup_retention_period at least 1 day.
Rule five. EKS in prod must have private endpoint.
endpoint_public_access false in production.
Rule six. EKS must have secrets encryption with KMS.
encryption_config must be set.
Rule seven. ElastiCache must have at-rest and in-transit encryption.
at_rest_encryption_enabled true, transit_encryption_enabled true.
Rule eight. No SSH or PostgreSQL from 0.0.0.0/0.
Security group rules must restrict access.
Now the k8s_admission_test.rego file.
Unit tests for the admission policy.
Tests cover. latest tag is denied, image with no tag is denied.
Compliant pod passes all 10 checks.
Missing CPU request is denied.
Privileged container is denied.
Run OPA tests with conftest.
Install conftest with brew install conftest or pip install conftest.
Test the admission policy.
conftest verify dash dash policy policies/rego/ dash dash namespace financial_rag
Test Helm templates.
helm template infrastructure/helm/ -f infrastructure/helm/values.yaml pipe conftest test dash dash policy policies/rego/
Test Terraform plan.
cd infrastructure/terraform/environments/prod/vpc
terragrunt plan -out plan.out
terraform show -json plan.out pipe conftest test dash dash policy policies/rego/
Our OPA Rego policies are complete.
CI now catches violations before they reach production.
[## [SECTION: Phase 11 Verification]]
Now let's verify Phase 11.
First, check that traces are visible in Jaeger.
Port-forward to the Jaeger query service.
kubectl port-forward -n monitoring svc/jaeger-query 16686:16686
Open localhost 16686 and search for service financial-rag-api.
You should see traces with the custom spans.
rag.embedding, rag.search, rag.llm.
Next, check that metrics are flowing to Prometheus.
Port-forward to Prometheus.
kubectl port-forward -n monitoring svc/kube-prometheus-stack-prometheus 9090:9090
Query for financial_rag:api_error_rate:rate1h.
Next, check SLO error budget.
Query for financial_rag:slo1:error_budget_remaining.
You should see a percentage value between 0 and 100.
Next, check trace-to-log correlation.
In Grafana, open a Loki log entry.
Click View Trace. It should open the trace in Tempo.
If the trace opens, correlation is working.
Next, check ArgoCD notifications.
Deploy a change to dev. Watch Slack for the sync succeeded message.
Next, check OPA policies in CI.
Push a PR with a missing CPU request. The CI should fail.
Push a PR with an S3 bucket that blocks public ACLs. The CI should pass.
Let me summarize Phase 11.
We installed the LGTM stack with Loki, Tempo, Mimir, and Grafana.
All on S3 for cheap long-term storage.
OpenTelemetry added tracing automatically.
Tail sampling keeps 100 percent of errors, 1 percent of successes.
Trace IDs injected into every log line.
Log, trace, metrics all correlated.
Custom spans for embedding, search, and LLM calls.
Flame graphs show exactly where time is spent.
Three SLOs with multi-window burn rate alerts.
Your phone rings only when something is really wrong.
ArgoCD notifications to Slack and PagerDuty.
OPA Rego policies enforce everything in CI.
Phase 11 is complete.
The Financial RAG Agent now has full observability.
Logs, metrics, traces, and alerts all connected.
Every component is monitored and observable.
---
**End of Phase 11. Phase 12 covers Production Hardening, FinOps, and Capstone. Shall I continue?**