Now let's move to Phase 12. Production hardening, FinOps, and the final capstone.
This is where we put everything together and validate the entire system.
Here are the new files we'll create in Phase 12.
infrastructure/kubecost/kubecost-cost-allocation.yaml
Cost allocation labels for Kubecost.
infrastructure/vpa/financial-rag-api.yaml
VerticalPodAutoscaler for the API.
infrastructure/karpenter/nodepool-consolidation.yaml
Karpenter NodePool with consolidation policies.
infrastructure/velero/backup-schedule.yaml
Velero backup schedule.
observability/grafana/finops-dashboard.json
FinOps dashboard for Grafana.
scripts/production-readiness-check.sh
Production readiness validation script.
infrastructure/gatekeeper/no-latest-tag.yaml
OPA Gatekeeper constraint template.
[## [SECTION: Step 10 — Kubecost (Components #179–181)]]
Now let's install Kubecost for cost visibility.
Kubecost tells you how much your Kubernetes cluster costs, down to the pod level.
First, add the Kubecost Helm repository.
helm repo add kubecost https://kubecost.github.io/cost-analyzer/
Install Kubecost in the monitoring namespace.
helm upgrade dash dash install kubecost kubecost/cost-analyzer dash dash namespace monitoring
Set kubecostToken to your token.
Set prometheus.enabled to false and prometheus.fqdn to the kube-prometheus-stack Prometheus.
Now create the cost allocation config.
We'll put it in infrastructure/kubecost/kubecost-cost-allocation.yaml
The labelConfig splits cost by component using app.kubernetes.io/component.
And by environment using the environment label.
shareTenancyCosts is set to true.
sharedNamespaces include monitoring, kube-system, and vault.
This shares the cost of monitoring and system components across all tenants.
Apply the config with kubectl apply.
Access the Kubecost dashboard.
kubectl port-forward dash n monitoring svc/kubecost-cost-analyzer 9090:9090
Open localhost 9090.
Three key cost reports to review.
Namespace costs. financial-rag versus monitoring versus kube-system.
Component costs. API pod hours versus agent pod hours versus pgvector storage.
Efficiency. requested versus used CPU and memory.
This gives you right-sizing signals.
Our Kubecost installation is complete.
You can now see exactly where your cloud spend is going.
[## [SECTION: Step 11 — VPA (Components #182–185)]]
Now let's install Vertical Pod Autoscaler or VPA.
VPA watches how much CPU and memory your pods actually use.
Add the Fairwinds Helm repository.
helm repo add fairwinds-stable https://charts.fairwinds.com/stable
Install VPA in the kube-system namespace.
helm upgrade dash dash install vpa fairwinds-stable/vpa dash dash namespace kube-system
Set recommender.enabled to true.
Set updater.enabled to false and admissionPlugin.enabled to false.
Now create the VPA for the API.
We'll put it in infrastructure/vpa/financial-rag-api.yaml
The VPA targets the API Deployment.
updatePolicy updateMode is set to Off.
Why Off mode? VPA in Auto mode restarts pods to apply new resource values.
For an LLM agent mid-reasoning-loop, a restart drops the request.
Use Recommend mode, review weekly, and apply manually during the maintenance window.
MinAllowed is 100 millicpu and 256 megabytes.
MaxAllowed is 4000 millicpu and 8 gigabytes.
Controlled resources are CPU and memory.
Create a similar VPA for the Agent Deployment.
MinAllowed 250 millicpu and 512 megabytes.
MaxAllowed 8000 millicpu and 16 gigabytes.
Apply the VPAs.
kubectl apply -f infrastructure/vpa/financial-rag-api.yaml
Wait 24 hours for VPA to collect data.
Then review recommendations with kubectl describe vpa.
Our VPA configuration is complete.
We now have right-sizing recommendations.
[## [SECTION: Step 12 — Karpenter Consolidation (Components #186–188)]]
Now let's configure Karpenter consolidation policies.
These control how nodes are replaced and consolidated.
The application NodePool uses consolidationPolicy WhenUnderutilized.
consolidateAfter is 30 seconds.
This consolidates quickly when underutilised.
expireAfter is 720 hours, which is 30 days.
Nodes are replaced after 30 days for OS patches.
The ingestion NodePool for spot instances uses consolidationPolicy WhenEmpty.
consolidateAfter is 5 minutes.
Wait 5 minutes after pods exit before terminating the node.
This gives the node time to finish any pending jobs.
The spot-burst NodePool uses consolidationPolicy WhenUnderutilized.
consolidateAfter is 2 minutes.
expireAfter is 24 hours. Short-lived burst nodes expire daily.
Apply the NodePools.
kubectl apply -f infrastructure/helm/karpenter/
Watch consolidation in action.
Scale down replicas, then watch Karpenter logs.
kubectl logs -n karpenter deployment/karpenter --follow pipe grep -i consolidate
Our Karpenter consolidation is complete.
Nodes now scale down efficiently to save cost.
[## [SECTION: Step 13 — Pod Security Admission (Components #191–192)]]
Now let's enable Pod Security Admission.
This is a built-in Kubernetes feature. No extra components to install.
Label the namespace with the restricted Pod Security Standard.
kubectl label namespace financial-rag pod-security.kubernetes.io/enforce=restricted
Also set enforce-version to v1.29.
Set warn and audit to restricted as well.
Now test that privileged pods are rejected.
kubectl run test-privileged with image alpine.
Set securityContext privileged to true.
Expected output shows Error from server Forbidden.
The error says violates PodSecurity restricted.
Privileged containers are now blocked.
Our Pod Security Admission is complete.
The namespace now enforces restricted security standards.
[## [SECTION: Step 14 — OPA Gatekeeper (Components #193–194)]]
Now let's install OPA Gatekeeper.
Gatekeeper is like Pod Security Admission but much more powerful.
You can write any policy you want.
Add the Gatekeeper Helm repository.
helm repo add gatekeeper https://open-policy-agent.github.io/gatekeeper/charts
Install Gatekeeper in the gatekeeper-system namespace.
helm upgrade dash dash install gatekeeper gatekeeper/gatekeeper dash dash namespace gatekeeper-system dash dash create-namespace
Now create a constraint from the k8s_admission.rego policies.
We'll put it in infrastructure/gatekeeper/no-latest-tag.yaml
First, define the ConstraintTemplate.
It wraps the Rego policy for Kubernetes.
The template name is nolatestimage.
The rego code checks if any container image ends with colon latest.
If it does, return a violation message.
Then create the Constraint that applies the template.
kind is NoLatestImage.
The match block applies to the financial-rag namespace.
enforcementAction is set to deny.
Apply the constraint.
kubectl apply -f infrastructure/gatekeeper/no-latest-tag.yaml
Now test that a pod with latest image is rejected.
kubectl run test-latest with image nginx colon latest.
Expected output shows the pod is blocked.
With message that latest tag is not allowed.
Our OPA Gatekeeper is complete.
Kubernetes now enforces no latest tags at admission time.
[## [SECTION: Step 15 — Velero Backup (Components #195–199)]]
Now let's install Velero for backup and restore.
Velero backs up your entire Kubernetes cluster.
Pods, config maps, secrets, and persistent volumes.
Install the Velero CLI first.
brew install velero on macOS.
Install Velero server with S3 backend.
velero install dash dash provider aws dash dash plugins velero/velero-plugin-for-aws
Set bucket to financial-rag-velero-backups.
Set backup-location-config region to us-east-1.
Set snapshot-location-config region to us-east-1.
Provide the secret file with AWS credentials.
Now create the backup schedule.
We'll put it in infrastructure/velero/backup-schedule.yaml
The schedule runs daily at 1 AM UTC.
Why 1 AM? Because the ingestion CronJob runs at 2 AM.
You want the backup before ingestion, not after.
includedNamespaces are financial-rag and vault.
includedResources is star, all resources.
includeClusterResources is true.
TTL is 336 hours, which is 14 days of retention.
snapshotVolumes is true.
labelSelector matches app.kubernetes.io/name equals financial-rag-agent.
Apply the backup schedule.
kubectl apply -f infrastructure/velero/backup-schedule.yaml
Create an on-demand backup before any major upgrade.
velero backup create pre-upgrade-backup dash dash include-namespaces financial-rag dash dash wait
Verify the backup.
velero backup describe pre-upgrade-backup
Test restore to a different namespace.
Never restore directly over production.
velero restore create test-restore dash dash from-backup pre-upgrade-backup
dash dash namespace-mappings financial-rag colon financial-rag-restore dash dash wait
Verify the restore.
kubectl get pods in the financial-rag-restore namespace.
Clean up the test restore.
kubectl delete namespace financial-rag-restore
Our Velero backup is complete.
The cluster now has daily backups and restore capability.
[## [SECTION: Step 16 — Production Readiness Check (Component #203)]]
Now let's create the production readiness check script.
We'll put it in scripts/production-readiness-check.sh
This script validates everything before a major deployment.
It produces a pass or fail report.
First, it checks infrastructure.
Cluster connectivity and all nodes ready.
Next, application pods.
API pods, agent pods, pgvector statefulset, redis statefulset.
All should be running with the correct replica counts.
Next, health endpoints.
API slash health should return status healthy or degraded.
Next, security.
All containers running as non-root. No UID zero.
No latest image tags in production.
Vault agent sidecars running.
Falco running in kube-system.
Next, autoscaling.
HPA for API and agent should be able to scale.
Next, observability.
Prometheus running, Grafana running, OTel Collector running.
Next, backup.
Latest Velero backup should be Completed.
Each check prints a green checkmark, a red X, or a yellow warning.
At the end, it prints passed, failed, and warning counts.
If any failures exist, the script exits with code 1.
Your CI pipeline can block deployment until issues are fixed.
Make the script executable.
chmod plus x scripts/production-readiness-check.sh
Run the check.
./scripts/production-readiness-check.sh financial-rag
Our production readiness check is complete.
Every deployment can now be validated before rollout.
[## [SECTION: Step 17 — FinOps Dashboard (Component #200)]]
Now let's create the FinOps dashboard.
We'll put it in observability/grafana/finops-dashboard.json
The dashboard has four panels.
Panel one. Monthly Cost by Component.
Pie chart using sum by component of kubecost_cluster_costs_total.
This shows where your money is going.
API versus agent versus ingestion versus pgvector versus redis.
Panel two. Cost per Query in cents.
Stat panel using financial_rag:cost_per_query_cents:1h.
This shows your unit economics.
How much each query costs to run.
Panel three. Error Budget Remaining as a percentage.
Gauge panel using financial_rag:slo_availability:error_budget_remaining.
Color thresholds. Red at 0 percent, yellow at 25 percent, green at 50 percent.
Panel four. LLM Token Cost per hour.
Time series panel using rate of financial_rag_llm_cost_usd_total.
Apply the budget alerts.
Create a PrometheusRule for FinOps.
MonthlyBudgetExceeded alert.
Triggers if sum of kubecost_cluster_costs_total in financial-rag namespace exceeds 5000.
For 1 hour. Severity warning, team finops.
LLMCostSpike alert.
Triggers if rate of LLM cost per hour exceeds 50 dollars.
For 15 minutes. Severity warning, team finops.
Apply the budget alerts.
kubectl apply with the PrometheusRule YAML.
Import the dashboard via Grafana UI.
Dashboards, Import, upload the JSON file.
Our FinOps dashboard is complete.
Cost and efficiency metrics are now visible.
[## [SECTION: Final Checklist — All 12 Phases]]
Let me present the final checklist across all 12 phases.
Phase 1. Infrastructure and Configuration.
PostgreSQL, Redis, settings, and database client.
Phase 2. Ingestion Pipeline.
SEC EDGAR, HTML parser, text parser, and exceptions.
Phase 3. Processing and Chunking.
tiktoken, section-aware chunking, and embeddings.
Phase 4. Retrieval and Agents.
Document retriever, hybrid search, query engine, and financial agent.
Phase 5. API and Monitoring.
FastAPI, authentication, Prometheus metrics, and middleware.
Phase 6. Secrets Management with Vault.
Dynamic database credentials, PKI, and per-role policies.
Phase 7. CI/CD Pipeline.
GitHub Actions, secret scanning, dependency scanning, and image scanning.
Phase 8. Kubernetes Production.
Helm charts, EKS, Karpenter, and Terragrunt.
Phase 9. GitOps and Zero-Trust Networking.
ArgoCD, Cilium eBPF, and Istio service mesh.
Phase 10. Falco Runtime Security.
Syscall-level detection, eight custom rules, and Falcosidekick.
Phase 11. LGTM Observability.
Loki logs, Tempo traces, Mimir metrics, and SLOs.
Phase 12. Production Hardening and FinOps.
Kubecost, VPA, Velero backup, and readiness check.
All 12 phases are complete.
You have built a production-grade financial AI system from scratch.
[## [SECTION: Common Errors and Fixes — Phases 11 & 12]]
Let me walk through common errors in Phases 11 and 12.
And how to fix them.
Error one. OTLPSpanExporter failed to export.
The OpenTelemetry Collector is not running.
Check kubectl get pods in the financial-rag namespace for opentelemetry-collector.
If not running, check the logs and restart.
Error two. Traces not in Jaeger.
Sampling rate is too low.
Set OTEL_TRACE_SAMPLE_RATE to 1.0 temporarily in development.
This captures 100 percent of traces for debugging.
Error three. engine.sync_engine AttributeError.
SQLAlchemy async engine issue.
Call configure_tracing after get_db_client connects.
The engine must be initialised before instrumentation.
Error four. SLO recording rules not found.
Prometheus is not loading the rules.
Check the label release equals kube-prometheus-stack on the PrometheusRule.
The Prometheus operator requires this label.
Error five. Conftest deny on compliant pod.
Missing required label.
Add app.kubernetes.io/component label to the pod spec.
The Rego policy requires this label for Cilium selectors.
Error six. VPA shows no recommendations.
Insufficient history.
Wait 24 to 48 hours after applying VPA.
The recommender needs time to collect usage data.
Error seven. Velero backup PartiallyFailed.
PVC snapshot permissions missing.
Verify velero-credentials has ec2:CreateSnapshot IAM permission.
The role must allow snapshot creation.
Error eight. Production readiness check fails.
Pods using latest image tag.
Pin image tags in values.prod.yaml to a semver or SHA.
Never use latest in production.
Error nine. Grafana no data on FinOps panels.
Kubecost is not scraping.
Check Kubecost ServiceMonitor and the release label.
Prometheus must be configured to scrape Kubecost.
Error ten. conftest verify test failures.
Policy logic error.
Run opa test policies/rego/ dash v directly.
This shows which specific tests are failing.
Bookmark this section.
When you hit an error, you'll know exactly where to look.
Congratulations on completing the entire Financial RAG Agent course.
From a single Python script to a multi-cluster Kubernetes deployment.
You have implemented zero-trust security, GitOps, and full observability.
You have cost visibility, backup and restore, and production readiness validation.
This is the level of quality that enterprise companies expect.
This is what senior platform engineers build.
Thank you for learning.
Go build amazing things. The world needs your skills.
---
**END OF PHASE 12 — COMPLETE COURSE**
**All 12 Phases have been delivered in full SRT format with proper sequencing and headers.**
**The Financial RAG Agent course is now ready for your Audio-First recording.**