Now let's move to Phase 7. The CI/CD pipeline.
This automates testing, security scanning, and building our Docker images.
Here are the new files we'll create in Phase 7.
.github/workflows/ci.yml
GitHub Actions workflow for CI/CD.
infrastructure/docker/Dockerfile
Multi-stage Docker build for the application.
infrastructure/docker/docker-compose.prod.yml
Production Docker Compose with all services.
infrastructure/docker/prometheus/prometheus.yml
Prometheus configuration for production.
scripts/start.sh
Utility script to start development services.
scripts/stop.sh
Utility script to stop all services.
scripts/cleanup.sh
Utility script to remove containers and volumes.
policies/rego/vault_policy.rego
OPA Rego policy for Vault configuration validation.
[## [SECTION: Step 12 — The CI Pipeline Architecture]]
Now let's build our GitHub Actions workflow.
We'll put it in .github/workflows/ci.yml
The workflow runs on pushes to main and develop, and on pull requests.
It has seven jobs that run in parallel with dependencies.
First, secret scanning with gitleaks.
It scans your git history for accidentally committed secrets.
API keys, passwords, tokens that were committed by mistake.
gitleaks finds them even if they were deleted later.
fetch-depth zero is critical. It fetches the full git history.
Otherwise, gitleaks only sees the latest commit.
Second job. dependency vulnerability scan with pip-audit.
It checks if any of your Python packages have known CVEs.
Third job. lint and type check.
ruff checks code style and common errors.
mypy checks type annotations.
This catches bugs before runtime.
Fourth job. unit tests.
These run fast with mocked dependencies.
We set APP_ENV to testing, and provide test passwords.
We run pytest with coverage and fail if coverage drops below 50 percent.
Fifth job. integration tests.
These require real PostgreSQL and Redis containers.
GitHub Actions provides services for this.
We define a postgres container and a redis container.
We apply the schema, then run pytest.
Integration tests only run on pushes, not on pull requests.
Sixth job. build the Docker image.
This only runs on pushes to the main branch.
We set up Docker Buildx for multi-platform builds.
We log in to GitHub Container Registry.
We extract metadata for tags. branch name, commit SHA, and latest.
Then we build and push the image.
Seventh job. container security scan with Trivy.
Trivy scans the image for CVEs in OS and Python packages.
It produces a SARIF report. This gets uploaded to the GitHub Security tab.
You can see all vulnerabilities in your repository's security dashboard.
Concurrency prevents multiple workflows from running simultaneously.
If a new push happens, the previous workflow is cancelled.
This saves CI minutes and prevents wasted work.
[## [SECTION: Step 13 — Multi-Stage Dockerfile (Component #71)]]
Now let's build our multi-stage Dockerfile.
We'll put it in infrastructure/docker/Dockerfile
Let me explain three important Docker patterns.
First, layer caching order.
Docker caches each layer. If nothing changed, it reuses the cache.
This makes builds much faster.
Copy dependency files first. pyproject.toml changes rarely.
Install pip dependencies next. This layer is cached until pyproject.toml changes.
Then copy application code. Code changes frequently.
But the pip install layer is still cached.
Second pattern. non-root user.
Containers run as root by default.
If an attacker escapes the container, they have root on the host.
Running as a non-root user limits the damage.
We create a finrag user and group.
Then change ownership of the app directory and switch to that user.
Third pattern. HEALTHCHECK in the image.
This checks if the container is still alive.
The healthcheck runs curl to the health endpoint every 30 seconds.
It waits 40 seconds for startup before checking.
This is redundant with Docker Compose and Kubernetes healthchecks.
But defense in depth means having it in the image as a fallback.
The Dockerfile uses multi-stage builds.
First stage is builder. It installs dependencies and compiles anything needed.
Second stage is production. It copies only the virtual environment and source code.
No build tools in the final image. This makes it smaller and more secure.
We use a slim Python base image.
Alpine is even smaller but can have compatibility issues.
Our Dockerfile is complete.
Now we can build secure, production-ready images.
[## [SECTION: Step 14 — Container Scanning with Trivy (Component #72)]]
Now let's understand container scanning with Trivy.
Trivy scans the built image for CVEs in OS and Python packages.
The workflow uploads results in SARIF format to GitHub Security tab.
This gives you a dashboard of all vulnerabilities.
exit-code zero means Trivy reports findings but does not fail the build.
Change to one to block deployments with CRITICAL vulnerabilities.
You can test Trivy locally before pushing.
Install Trivy, then run trivy image against your image.
Scan with severity CRITICAL, HIGH and format table.
This shows you exactly what vulnerabilities exist.
Our container scanning is integrated into CI.
Every image is scanned before deployment.
[## [SECTION: Step 15 — Secret Scanning with gitleaks (Component #73)]]
Now let's understand secret scanning with gitleaks.
gitleaks scans your git history for secrets that were accidentally committed.
The workflow uses the official gitleaks GitHub Action.
It scans the entire repository history.
fetch-depth zero is critical. Without it, Actions only fetches the latest commit.
gitleaks needs full history to catch secrets that were added in commit A and deleted in commit B.
Even if a secret is deleted, it still exists in the git object store.
Anyone who clones the repo can see it.
You can test gitleaks locally before pushing.
gitleaks detect with the source flag.
Add a dot gitleaks.toml file to allowlist false positives.
Test passwords in CI YAML, and placeholder values.
Our secret scanning is integrated into CI.
If a secret is found, the workflow fails.
[## [SECTION: Step 16 — OPA Rego Policy (Component #74)]]
Now let's look at the OPA Rego policy for Vault.
This validates Vault policy HCL files before they are applied.
Three rules are enforced by the Rego policy.
First, no wildcard write on secret paths.
This prevents secret star with write capability.
Second, no delete on secret paths.
Application roles should never delete secrets.
Third, no sudo capability except for admin policies.
And no sys slash access from non-admin workloads.
Use the file from your repo as-is.
Test it with conftest.
Install conftest. pip install conftest.
Create a test input with a bad policy that grants write on a wildcard path.
Run conftest test against the input.
Using vault_policy.rego as the policy.
Expected output shows failures.
The policy catches the wildcard write and the delete capability.
Our OPA Rego policy is complete.
Vault policies are validated before they reach production.
[## [SECTION: Step 17 — Production Docker Compose]]
Now let's set up the production Docker Compose configuration.
We'll put it in infrastructure/docker/docker-compose.prod.yml
This runs the entire application stack in production.
We have five core services.
The FastAPI application, PostgreSQL, Redis, Prometheus, and Grafana.
First, the app service.
It builds the Docker image using the production target.
Environment variables come from a dot env dot prod file.
All required variables have the colon question mark syntax.
If POSTGRES_PASSWORD is missing, Docker Compose refuses to start.
This is fail-fast at startup.
The app depends on postgres and redis with condition service_healthy.
It only starts after both dependencies are healthy.
The app has its own healthcheck.
curl to the health endpoint every 30 seconds.
This tells Docker if the container is alive.
If the healthcheck fails, the container can be restarted.
Second, the PostgreSQL service.
We use the pgvector slash pg16 image.
Environment variables include the database name, user, and password.
Notice the password is not using colon question mark here.
It comes from the same environment variable.
But the check happens at the app level.
Volumes mount persistent data storage.
And the init SQL scripts run on first start.
Third, the Redis service.
Redis 7 on Alpine Linux for a small image size.
The command configures the server.
Requirepass uses the password from environment.
Maxmemory is set to 1 gigabyte.
The eviction policy is allkeys-lru, correct for a cache.
Appendonly yes enables persistence to disk.
This means Redis survives container restarts.
Fourth, Prometheus for metrics collection.
It scrapes the app's metrics endpoint every 10 seconds.
Prometheus stores data for 30 days.
It has a web lifecycle enabled for reloads without restart.
Fifth, Grafana for metrics visualization.
It connects to Prometheus as a data source.
The admin password is set from environment variables.
User sign-up is disabled for security.
We need to create the Prometheus configuration file.
It goes in infrastructure slash docker slash prometheus.
Global scrape interval is 15 seconds.
Evaluation interval is also 15 seconds.
Scrape configs define which targets to monitor.
One job for the financial-rag-api, target app port 8000.
And one job for Prometheus itself, target localhost 9090.
To start the production stack, first create a dot env dot prod file.
Copy from dot env example and edit with production values.
Then run docker compose with the production compose file.
Use the dash dash env dash file flag to specify your environment file.
Verify all services are running with docker compose ps.
You should see five services all in the Up state.
Let me summarize the production architecture.
The app service connects to PostgreSQL and Redis.
It exposes Prometheus metrics on the slash metrics endpoint.
Prometheus scrapes those metrics every 10 seconds.
Grafana visualizes them in dashboards.
All data is persisted in Docker volumes.
PostgreSQL data, Redis data, Prometheus data, and Grafana data.
Our production Docker Compose stack is complete.
The entire application is ready for deployment.
[## [SECTION: Step 18 — Utility Scripts]]
Now let's create the utility scripts for development.
These make starting and stopping the environment much easier.
First, start.sh. This script starts the development environment.
It has error handling with set dash e uo pipefail.
If any command fails, the script exits immediately.
This prevents running with half-initialized services.
The script does preflight checks first.
It checks if dot env file exists.
Then it sources the dot env file to load environment variables.
It sets all variables, then unsets the automatic export.
It checks if docker is installed.
And if the docker daemon is actually running.
Next, it starts the core services.
PostgreSQL and Redis with docker compose up minus d.
The wait_healthy function loops until each container is healthy.
It checks docker inspect for the health status.
It retries up to 30 times, waiting 2 seconds between tries.
If a container never becomes healthy, the script fails with an error.
Then it asks if you want to start management tools.
pgAdmin and Redis Commander are in the tools profile.
If you say yes, it runs docker compose with the profile flag.
These tools are optional and not required for the app to run.
Finally, it prints a summary of where services are running.
PostgreSQL on localhost with the configured port.
Redis on localhost with its port.
And if you started tools, pgAdmin on port 5050, Redis UI on port 8081.
Second, stop.sh. This is the simplest script.
It just runs docker compose down.
This stops all containers but preserves the data volumes.
Your PostgreSQL and Redis data remain on disk.
Third, cleanup.sh. This is destructive.
It asks for confirmation before doing anything.
If you type y or Y, it runs docker compose down with the minus v flag.
The minus v flag removes all named volumes.
This deletes your PostgreSQL database, Redis data, and any other persistent storage.
Use this to completely reset your development environment.
Make the scripts executable first.
chmod plus x scripts slash start.sh, stop.sh, and cleanup.sh.
Here is the development workflow.
First, run dot slash scripts slash start.sh.
This starts PostgreSQL and Redis.
It waits for them to be healthy.
Do your development work.
Run your application, run tests.
When you're done, run dot slash scripts slash stop.sh.
The data stays on disk for next time.
If you want a completely fresh start, run dot slash scripts slash cleanup.sh.
This removes everything, including your data.
Our utility scripts are complete.
Development environment management is now simple and consistent.
[## [SECTION: Final File Tree — Phases 6 & 7]]
Let me show you the complete file tree for Phases 6 and 7.
Phase 6 files.
infrastructure/vault/vault-bootstrap.sh
infrastructure/vault/policies/api-policy.hcl
infrastructure/vault/policies/agent-policy.hcl
infrastructure/vault/policies/ingestion-policy.hcl
infrastructure/k8s/service-accounts.yaml
infrastructure/vault/vault-agent-config.hcl
src/financial_rag/security/vault.py
src/financial_rag/security/__init__.py
Phase 7 files.
.github/workflows/ci.yml
infrastructure/docker/Dockerfile
infrastructure/docker/docker-compose.prod.yml
infrastructure/docker/prometheus/prometheus.yml
scripts/start.sh
scripts/stop.sh
scripts/cleanup.sh
policies/rego/vault_policy.rego
All these files work together.
The CI pipeline builds and tests everything.
The production compose file runs the stack.
[## [SECTION: Common Errors and Fixes — Phases 6 & 7]]
Let me walk through common errors in Phases 6 and 7.
And how to fix them.
Error one. permission denied on vault-bootstrap.sh.
The file is not executable.
The fix is simple. Run chmod plus x on the script file.
Then try again.
Error two. listener permission denied on port 8200.
Another process is already using that port.
Run lsof dash i colon 8200 to find the process.
Then kill it and restart Vault.
Error three. connection refused to Vault in CI.
Vault is only for Kubernetes, not for CI.
CI should use environment variables from GitHub Secrets.
Not try to connect to a Vault instance.
Error four. POSTGRES_PASSWORD required in unit tests.
Your settings validation requires the password.
Set POSTGRES_PASSWORD in your CI environment variables.
Use a test password like test dash pg dash password.
Error five. gitleaks fails on dot env example.
The placeholder values look like real secrets.
The fix is to add these placeholders to the allowlist.
Update dot gitleaks.toml with the regexes.
Error six. Trivy not finding the image.
The image hasn't been built locally.
Run docker build first.
Then run trivy image against the local image name.
Error seven. conftest command not found.
The tool isn't installed on your system.
On macOS, run brew install conftest.
On Linux, download the binary from GitHub.
Error eight. schema not found in CI.
The path to the SQL file is incorrect.
Check your ci.yml file. Make sure the path matches.
Should be infrastructure slash docker slash init slash create_schema.sql.
Error nine. dynamic credentials expire mid-request.
The TTL is too short or the renewal is missed.
In production, Vault Agent handles renewal automatically.
Make sure the sidecar is running in your pod.
Bookmark this section.
When you hit an error, you'll know exactly where to look.
[## [SECTION: What's Next — Phase 8]]
Now let me preview Phase 8.
In Phase 8, we move to full Kubernetes deployment.
This is production-grade infrastructure.
You'll learn Helm chart structure with underscore helpers dot tpl.
StatefulSets for PostgreSQL and Redis with persistent volumes.
HorizontalPodAutoscaler for the API.
Scaling based on CPU and custom metrics.
Karpenter for node provisioning.
Spot instances for ingestion workloads to save money.
AWS ALB Ingress with SSL termination.
Terragrunt modules for VPC, EKS, RDS, and ElastiCache.
Multi-environment configuration.
Separate deployments for dev, staging, and production.
The file tree for Phase 8 will include.
infrastructure/helm/Chart.yaml and values.yaml.
infrastructure/helm/templates/api-deployment.yaml.
infrastructure/helm/templates/agent-deployment.yaml.
infrastructure/helm/templates/pgvector-statefulset.yaml.
infrastructure/helm/templates/redis-statefulset.yaml.
infrastructure/terraform/environments/dev/env.hcl.
infrastructure/terraform/environments/staging/env.hcl.
infrastructure/terraform/environments/prod/env.hcl.
Phase 7 is complete.
Our CI/CD pipeline is ready.
In Phase 8, we deploy everything to Kubernetes.
The application becomes truly production-ready.
Ready to proceed to Phase 8?
---
**End of Phase 7. Phase 8 covers Kubernetes Production Deployment. Shall I continue?**