Now let's move to Phase 4. The intelligent reasoning layer.
This is where we add LLM intelligence on top of our vector search.
Here are the new files we'll create in Phase 4.
src/financial_rag/retrieval/query_engine.py
The public interface for the entire retrieval layer.
src/financial_rag/storage/repositories/analysis.py
Analysis history repository for audit trail.
src/financial_rag/agents/financial_agent.py
The intelligent agent with tool calling.
src/financial_rag/agents/__init__.py
Exports the FinancialAgent and AgentResult.
tests/integration/test_phase4_agent.py
Integration tests for Phase 4.
We'll also update existing files.
api/models.py adds new request/response models.
api/routes.py adds the /query endpoint.
And storage/__init__.py exports the analysis repository.
[## [SECTION: Step 1 — Extend VectorStore with ingest() and stats()]]
Before we build the query engine, we need to extend our VectorStore.
The API routes will call store.ingest and store.stats.
Open src/financial_rag/storage/vector_store.py.
We already have the VectorStore class. Now we add two methods.
First, the ingest method.
This is the full pipeline for ingesting a single filing.
It takes three parameters.
chunks from the text processor, filing metadata, and the file hash.
It returns a tuple of filing ID and the number of chunks stored.
Let me walk through each step.
Step one. deduplication check.
We create a database session and instantiate FilingsRepository.
We check if a filing with this hash already exists.
If yes, we raise DuplicateFilingError.
This prevents ingesting the same filing twice.
The ingestion pipeline must be idempotent.
Step two. embed all chunks.
We call embed_chunks on the embedding client.
This method takes a list of FinancialChunk objects.
It populates the embedding field on each one.
The embedding client handles batching automatically.
It also tracks token usage and cost.
Step three. register the filing.
We generate a new UUID for the filing ID.
We create a Filing ORM instance with all the metadata.
Ticker, filing type, fiscal year, source URL, and file hash.
We set ingested_by to VectorStore and is_active to True.
Then we add it to the database using FilingsRepository.
Step four. bulk upsert the chunks.
First, we set the filing_id on all chunks.
They had placeholder UUIDs from the text processor.
Now we attach them to the correct filing.
Then we call bulk_upsert on ChunksRepository.
This inserts or updates all chunks in a single operation.
We log the completion with filing ID and chunk count.
Then return both to the caller.
Now the stats method.
This returns storage statistics for monitoring.
The stats method takes an optional ticker parameter.
If provided, it returns counts for just that company.
We create a database session and instantiate both repositories.
ChunksRepository and FilingsRepository.
If a ticker is provided, we use count_by_ticker and get_by_ticker.
If not, we use the global count methods.
The result is a dictionary with ticker, total chunks,
total filings, embedding provider, and dimensions.
This is useful for monitoring your ingestion progress.
And for debugging configuration issues.
With both methods added, the VectorStore is now complete.
The API routes can call ingest for new filings and stats for dashboards.
[## [SECTION: Step 2 — Extend DatabaseClient with health_check() and verify_pgvector()]]
Now let's extend our DatabaseClient with two methods.
Health check and verify pgvector.
These are called by the API routes and startup dependencies.
They give us visibility into database health.
Open src/financial_rag/storage/database.py.
We already have the DatabaseClient class.
First, let's add the health_check method.
This runs a lightweight liveness probe against PostgreSQL.
If the engine is None, meaning the client isn't initialised,
we return a disconnected status.
If connected, we open a connection and run a query.
We select the PostgreSQL version and the server start time.
We also get pool statistics from the engine's pool.
Pool size, checked out connections, and overflow.
The result is a dictionary with status, PostgreSQL version,
server start time, and pool statistics.
If any exception occurs, we log the error.
And we raise DatabaseConnectionError with the details.
Now let's add verify_pgvector.
This checks that the pgvector extension is installed and accessible.
We query the pg_extension table.
We look for the extension named vector.
If the scalar result is not None, the extension exists.
We log success and return True.
If not, we log an error with instructions.
Run CREATE EXTENSION IF NOT EXISTS vector.
We call this method at application startup.
Before any embedding operations begin.
If pgvector is missing, we can fail fast.
Better to know at startup than when the first query fails.
Our database client now has health checks.
The system can now self-monitor.
[## [SECTION: Step 3 — Extend CacheClient with health_check()]]
Now let's extend CacheClient with health_check.
Open src/financial_rag/storage/cache.py.
The health_check method for Redis is similar to the database version.
If Redis is None, return disconnected status.
If connected, we ping Redis to verify it's responding.
Then we fetch server info using the info command.
We extract Redis version, memory usage, and connected clients.
We also include pool statistics if available.
If a RedisError occurs, we log it.
And we raise CacheConnectionError.
These health check methods are critical for production.
They let your monitoring system know if a service is down.
A typical health endpoint would call both.
If either fails, the API returns 503 Service Unavailable.
Our database and cache clients now have health checks.
The system can now self-monitor.
[## [SECTION: Step 4 — Query Engine (Components #29, #38)]]
Now let's build the query engine.
This is the public interface for the entire retrieval layer.
Everything above this, like API routes and agents,
talks only to QueryEngine. Never directly to DocumentRetriever or HybridSearcher.
The QueryEngine orchestrates the full RAG pipeline.
Retrieve relevant chunks, assemble context, call the LLM, and return the result.
First, imports. We need logging, time, and dataclasses.
From typing, we import Literal for type hints.
From openai, we import AsyncOpenAI.
From our application, we import get_settings.
From retrieval, we import DocumentRetriever, RetrievalResult, and HybridSearcher.
From storage, we import VectorStore.
And from utils, we import RetrievalError.
Now define the system prompts for each analysis style.
Three styles. analyst, executive, and risk.
The analyst prompt asks for detailed, precise analysis.
Cite specific figures, dates, and sections.
The executive prompt is for CFO-level advisors.
Concise, decision-ready, lead with the most important finding.
The risk prompt is for a chief risk officer.
Analyse for financial risks, regulatory exposures, and operational vulnerabilities.
Now define the QueryResult dataclass.
This is the complete result from a RAG query.
It contains the question, answer, analysis style, search type,
latency in milliseconds, source documents, and any error.
The latency_seconds property converts milliseconds to seconds.
And the repr method gives us readable debug output.
Now the QueryEngine class.
In __init__, we load settings and create the vector store.
We instantiate DocumentRetriever and HybridSearcher.
And we build the LLM client.
The _build_llm_client method is our circuit breaker.
If MOCK_EXTERNAL_APIS is True, we return None.
If OPENAI_API_KEY is not set, we log a warning and return None.
The query method will return raw context instead of crashing.
This is the simplest possible circuit breaker.
Never let the LLM being down take down the entire service.
Now the main query method.
This runs the full RAG pipeline for a question.
We record the start time with time.monotonic.
This gives us high-precision latency measurement.
If the analysis style is invalid, we fall back to analyst.
Then we call _retrieve to get relevant chunks.
Here's an important feature. auto-upgrade.
If we used similarity search and the top result's score is below the threshold.
We automatically upgrade to hybrid search.
This gives better results for queries that need exact term matching.
If no results are found at all, we return a friendly message.
I could not find relevant information in the available financial documents.
If we have results, we build the context using build_context.
This respects the token budget.
Then we call _generate_answer with the question, context, and style.
The LLM produces a grounded answer.
We calculate the total latency and log the result.
Then we return a QueryResult with all the information.
If any exception occurs during the query, we catch it.
We log the error and return a QueryResult with the error field set.
The API never crashes. It always returns a valid response.
This is the graceful degradation principle.
The _retrieve method routes to the appropriate retrieval strategy.
If search_type is hybrid, we call HybridSearcher.
Otherwise we call DocumentRetriever with the requested search_type.
Similarity or MMR.
The _generate_answer method calls the LLM.
We format the system prompt and user message.
If the LLM client is None, we return the raw context.
This is the circuit breaker in action.
Let me explain the routing table one more time.
Search type similarity goes to DocumentRetriever with pgvector.
Search type MMR also goes to DocumentRetriever but with diversity ranking.
Search type hybrid goes to HybridSearcher.
Vector plus full-text with RRF fusion.
And if similarity scores are below the threshold, we auto-upgrade to hybrid.
This gives you the best of both worlds automatically.
Let me also explain the LLM_BASE_URL configuration.
Your .env defaults set LLM_BASE_URL to Groq's endpoint.
But LLM_PROVIDER is still OpenAI.
This is intentional. Groq exposes an OpenAI-compatible API.
You can use the OpenAI SDK with Groq's faster inference.
In development, this saves money significantly.
For production with GPT-4o, simply remove LLM_BASE_URL from .env.
Our query engine is complete.
Now the API routes can use it to answer questions.
We import QueryEngine and QueryResult from QueryEngine.
Then we add them to __all__.
Our QueryEngine repository is complete.
[## [SECTION: Step 5 — Analysis History Repository (Components #36–37)]]
Now let's build the analysis history repository.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/storage/repositories/analysis.py
This is the audit trail for every query that goes through the system.
All analysis records are stored here permanently.
The table is append-only by design. No updates, no deletions.
Every query gets a permanent record.
Why append-only? Financial analysis systems need tamper-evident audit logs.
If a user later disputes an answer, you can show exactly what was asked.
You can see what documents were retrieved, what the model said, and the timestamp.
This is also essential for debugging model drift over time.
First, imports. We need logging, datetime with UTC, typing, and UUID.
From SQLAlchemy, we import Boolean, Integer, String, Text, func, and select.
From postgresql dialects, we import ARRAY and UUID types.
From our application, we import Base, BaseRepository, and DatabaseQueryError.
Now define the AnalysisRecord ORM model.
This maps to the analysis_history table we created in Phase one.
We have id as primary key, ticker, question, and answer.
Analysis style, agent type, search type, and latency in milliseconds.
Notice latency_ms is stored as integer, not float.
This is for efficient range queries and aggregations.
AVG latency on an integer column is faster than on a float.
Convert to seconds only at the presentation layer.
We have source_chunk_ids as a PostgreSQL array of UUIDs.
This stores which chunks were used to generate the answer.
Real_time_used is a boolean for live market data.
Error field captures any failures.
Session_id groups multiple queries from the same conversation.
And created_at is automatically set to the current UTC time.
Now the AnalysisRepository class.
It inherits from BaseRepository with AnalysisRecord as the model.
The record method is the primary write method.
It appends a completed analysis to the history table.
We generate a new UUID for the record.
We convert ticker to uppercase if provided.
We store the question, answer, analysis style, agent type, and search type.
Latency is stored as milliseconds.
Source chunk IDs default to an empty list.
Error and session_id are optional.
Then we call the base repository's add method.
This persists the record to the database.
Now the read methods.
get_by_ticker returns analysis history for a ticker, newest first.
We order by created_at descending and apply limit and offset for pagination.
get_by_session returns all records belonging to a session.
In chronological order, not newest first, because conversation order matters.
get_recent returns the most recent analyses globally.
Useful for monitoring dashboards and debugging.
We can filter by agent type or only show errors.
This helps identify which agents are having problems.
Now aggregation methods for monitoring.
average_latency_ms returns the average query latency.
We can filter by ticker or agent type.
This helps track performance per company or per agent.
error_rate returns the fraction of analyses that resulted in an error.
Returns 0.0 if no records exist.
We calculate total records and error records separately.
Then divide errors by total.
These aggregations are critical for production monitoring.
You can alert if error rate spikes above a threshold.
Now let's update the repositories __init__.py to export AnalysisRepository.
Open src/financial_rag/storage/repositories/__init__.py.
We import AnalysisRecord and AnalysisRepository from analysis.
Then we add them to __all__.
Our analysis repository is complete.
The audit trail is now ready to record every query.
[## [SECTION: Step 6 — Financial Agent (Components #30–35)]]
Now let's build the financial agent.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/agents/financial_agent.py
This is the intelligent reasoning layer.
It adds multi-step search orchestration on top of the query engine.
Instead of a single retrieval call, the agent can decide what to search for.
And it can search multiple times before synthesizing an answer.
First, imports. We need json, logging, time, and dataclasses.
From typing, we import Any and Literal.
From openai, we import AsyncOpenAI.
From our application, we import get_settings.
From retrieval, we import RetrievalResult and QueryEngine.
From storage, we import VectorStore.
Now define the AgentResult dataclass.
This is richer than QueryResult because it includes the tool call trace.
It contains the question, answer, analysis style, latency,
source documents, tool calls, reasoning steps, and any error.
The to_query_result method converts to QueryResult for API compatibility.
This lets you use the agent anywhere you'd use the query engine.
Now the system prompts for each analysis style.
Analyst, executive, and risk.
The analyst prompt asks for detailed, evidence-based answers.
Cite specific figures, dates, and document sections.
The executive prompt is for CFO-level advisors.
Lead with the most important finding, be direct and quantitative.
The risk prompt focuses on risk factors and legal proceedings.
Quantify risks where possible and flag exposures explicitly.
Now define the tools for OpenAI function calling.
First tool. search_filings.
It takes a query string, optional ticker, optional section, and optional fiscal year.
The model uses this to retrieve relevant passages from SEC filings.
Second tool. compare_filings.
Use this when the question asks about trends or year-over-year changes.
It takes a query, a ticker, and an optional list of years.
The model calls this to compare data across multiple fiscal periods.
Now the FinancialAgent class.
In __init__, we load settings and create the query engine.
We also build the LLM client. If OpenAI is unavailable,
the agent falls back to direct query engine.
The analyze method is the main public API.
It takes a question, optional ticker and fiscal year, analysis style, and max tool calls.
First, we check if the LLM is available.
If not, we fall back to QueryEngine immediately.
If LLM is available, we run the agent loop.
This is where the magic happens.
Let me explain the agent loop in plain English.
Step one. Send the question to the LLM with tool definitions attached.
The model sees what tools are available.
Step two. The LLM decides what to search for.
It returns structured JSON describing which tool to call and with what arguments.
Step three. Your code executes the tool call.
We call search_filings or compare_filings against our database.
Step four. The tool result goes back into the conversation.
The LLM sees what was retrieved.
Step five. Loop. The LLM may call more tools, or produce a final answer.
Continue until the model stops requesting tool calls.
Notice the max_tool_calls safety cap.
Without this, a misbehaving model could loop indefinitely.
The cap defaults to five. Enough for complex multi-year comparisons.
But prevents runaway API costs.
When the cap is hit, we call the LLM one final time without the tools parameter.
This forces it to answer from whatever context it has accumulated.
Now the tool execution methods.
_execute_tool routes to the appropriate tool handler.
_tool_search_filings calls the query engine with the provided parameters.
It returns a formatted context string and the retrieved chunks.
_tool_compare_filings runs multiple searches across different years.
It caps at three years to keep responses reasonable.
It returns a combined context string with year-by-year breakdowns.
And all source chunks for the audit trail.
Let me highlight the fallback layers.
If the LLM client can't be built, we fall back to QueryEngine.
If the agent loop hits an exception, we also fall back.
The API never crashes. It always returns a response.
This is the graceful degradation principle.
Better to return a slightly less intelligent answer than no answer at all.
Now let's create the agents package __init__.py.
Open src/financial_rag/agents/__init__.py.
We import AgentResult and FinancialAgent from financial_agent.
Then we expose both in __all__.
Now anywhere in the application, you can import.
from financial_rag.agents import FinancialAgent
Our financial agent is complete.
Now the API can offer intelligent, multi-step reasoning to users.
[## [SECTION: Step 7 — Phase 4 Verification Test]]
Now let's write integration tests for Phase 4.
We'll put them in tests/integration/test_phase4_agent.py
These tests verify the query engine, agent, and analysis repository.
Unit tests run without an LLM API key using mock mode.
Integration tests require a live LLM API key.
They are marked with the integration pytest marker.
First, TestQueryResult.
This verifies the QueryResult value object works correctly.
The first test checks that latency_seconds converts correctly.
1500 milliseconds should become 1.5 seconds.
The second test checks that repr includes key fields.
Analysis style and latency should appear in the string representation.
Now TestAgentResult.
This verifies the AgentResult value object.
The first test checks to_query_result conversion.
It ensures an AgentResult can become a QueryResult for API compatibility.
The second test checks that latency_seconds works correctly.
2000 milliseconds should become 2.0 seconds.
Now TestAnalysisRepository.
These are integration tests that require a real database.
The record test creates a new analysis record.
It verifies that an ID was generated and the fields match.
The get_by_ticker test retrieves records for a specific company.
It should always return a list, even if empty.
The average_latency test inserts a record and computes the average.
It verifies the aggregation method works.
The error_rate test checks that a non-existent ticker returns zero.
No records means zero percent error rate.
Now TestQueryEngineMocked.
These tests run without an LLM API key using mock mode.
We monkeypatch MOCK_EXTERNAL_APIS to true.
Then we clear the settings cache so the change takes effect.
The first test verifies the query engine returns a QueryResult.
Even without an LLM, the engine returns the question and context.
The second test verifies the agent falls back to query engine.
When the LLM is unavailable, agent_type becomes query_engine_fallback.
Finally, the db fixture.
This creates a real database client and connects.
It yields the client to the test, then disconnects afterward.
This ensures each test gets a fresh database connection.
Now let's talk about how to run these tests.
To run only the unit tests that don't need a database,
use pytest with the minus k flag to exclude integration.
These tests are fast and don't require any external services.
To run the integration tests that require a live database and LLM API key,
use pytest with the minus m integration flag.
These tests will incur API costs if you have an LLM key set.
Run them sparingly during development.
Our Phase four integration tests are complete.
The query engine, agent, and analysis repository are verified.
---
**End of Phase 4. Phase 5 will cover API, Monitoring, and Metrics. Shall I continue?**