In Phase 3, we build the core retrieval infrastructure.
This is where text becomes vectors and vectors become searchable.
You will learn how to use tiktoken for exact token counting.
How to build section-aware chunkers that respect document structure.
How to generate embeddings using both OpenAI and local models.
And how to store and search those embeddings using pgvector.
By the end of this phase, you'll have a fully functional vector search system.
You can ingest documents and find relevant passages by semantic meaning.
[## [SECTION: New Files in This Phase]]
Here are the new files we'll create in Phase 3.
src/financial_rag/processing/text_processor.py
This handles token counting and chunking.
src/financial_rag/processing/__init__.py
Exports the TextProcessor.
src/financial_rag/retrieval/embeddings.py
Dual-provider embedding client for OpenAI and local models.
src/financial_rag/retrieval/__init__.py
Exports the EmbeddingClient.
src/financial_rag/storage/repositories/chunks.py
Chunks repository with similarity search and MMR.
src/financial_rag/storage/vector_store.py
Orchestrates the full chunk to embed to store pipeline.
src/financial_rag/storage/cache.py
Add NS_QUERY namespace constant.
src/financial_rag/retrieval/document_retriever.py
Cache-aware document retrieval.
src/financial_rag/retrieval/hybrid_search.py
Combines vector and full-text search with RRF.
tests/unit/test_retrieval.py
Unit tests for retrieval components.
And migrations/versions/001_initial_migration.py
Alembic baseline for our schema.
[## [SECTION: Step 9 — Alembic Baseline Migration (Component #22)]]
Now let's set up Alembic for database migrations.
Alembic is the official migration tool for SQLAlchemy.
In Phase one, we used Docker's init script to create the schema.
Now we establish Alembic as the official source of migration truth.
Why Alembic? Because as our application evolves,
we will need to add columns, create new tables, or modify indexes.
Alembic tracks these changes in versioned migration files.
Each migration can be applied or rolled back.
First, initialize Alembic with the init command.
alembic init migrations
This creates a migrations directory with configuration files.
It also creates a versions directory where our migration scripts will live.
Now edit alembic.ini in the project root.
Find the sqlalchemy.url line.
You can leave the placeholder value.
We will override the database URL in env.py instead.
This is safer because it keeps credentials out of version control.
The actual URL will come from our settings at runtime.
Now replace the entire migrations/env.py file with our custom version.
Let me explain what this env.py does.
It configures Alembic to run migrations in two modes. Offline and online.
Offline mode generates SQL scripts without connecting to a database.
Online mode connects directly and applies migrations.
Notice that target_metadata is set to None.
We will update this later when we have our ORM models.
The run_migrations_offline function gets the database URL from the config.
It configures Alembic to generate SQL without a live connection.
The run_migrations_online function creates an engine from the config.
It connects to the database and runs migrations directly.
Finally, we check if Alembic is in offline mode.
If yes, run offline. If no, run online.
Now let's create our first migration script.
This will establish the baseline schema.
Create a file in migrations/versions called 001_initial_migration.py
The revision ID is 001.
down_revision is None because this is the first migration.
The upgrade function adds the PostgreSQL extensions we need.
Vector for embeddings, uuid-ossp for UUID generation.
Also pg_trgm for trigram text search.
And btree_gin for advanced indexing.
These are the same extensions we enabled in Docker's init script.
We include them here for Alembic to track.
The downgrade function is empty.
Dropping extensions is risky, so we leave it as a no-op.
Notice that this migration does NOT create the tables.
Our tables were already created by the Docker init script.
But future migrations will use Alembic's create_table operations.
This ensures all schema changes are versioned and repeatable.
Why does upgrade only create extensions?
The filings, financial_chunks, and analysis_history tables were created by the Docker init script in Phase 1.
Alembic's job going forward is to track schema changes.
Migration 001 is the baseline that says everything up to this point already exists.
Future migrations add columns, create indexes, or modify tables.
They go in 002, 003, and so on.
Now apply the migration.
alembic upgrade head
Verify with alembic current.
Output should show 001 followed by head in parentheses.
Alembic is now ready to track all future schema changes.
[## [SECTION: Step 10 — Token Counter & Chunker (Components #16–17)]]
Now let's build our text processor for chunking.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/processing/text_processor.py
This converts ParsedFiling objects into FinancialChunk ORM instances.
Ready for vector embedding and database storage.
Let me explain two key design decisions before we write code.
First, why tiktoken instead of estimating with len divided by 4?
The divide by 4 estimate is wrong in every edge case that matters.
Short words, numbers, financial abbreviations, and non-ASCII text
all tokenise differently. tiktoken gives you exact token counts.
It uses the same BPE tokeniser as the actual model.
So chunk boundaries are precise, not estimates.
Second, why section-aware chunking?
A naive chunker splits at 512 tokens regardless of content structure.
This puts the end of MD&A and the start of Risk Factors in the same chunk.
That confuses the retriever.
Section-aware chunking guarantees a chunk never spans two different sections.
Each chunk belongs to exactly one section.
Now let's import our dependencies.
We need logging, uuid, and dataclasses.
We import tiktoken for token counting.
From our application, we import get_settings and FinancialChunk.
And from utils, we import ChunkingError.
We also use TYPE_CHECKING for conditional imports.
First, define a ChunkSpec dataclass.
This is a specification for how a single chunk should be created.
It contains the text, section name, chunk index, token count,
filing ID, ticker, filing type, fiscal year, and optional metrics.
Now the TextProcessor class.
In __init__, we load settings and get the tiktoken encoding.
We use the cl100k_base encoding.
This covers GPT-4 and the text-embedding-3 series.
We store chunk size and overlap from settings.
If tiktoken fails to load, we raise ChunkingError.
Now the process method.
This is the public entry point for chunking a parsed filing.
First, we check if the parsed filing has any sections.
If not, we raise ChunkingError.
Then we iterate through each section.
If a section has no text, we skip it.
For each section, we call _chunk_section.
This returns a list of chunks for that section.
We extend the overall chunk list and update the global index.
Finally, we log how many sections became how many chunks.
Two utility methods.
count_tokens returns the exact token count for a string.
estimate_cost calculates the OpenAI embedding cost for a list of chunks.
It returns total tokens and estimated cost in US dollars.
This is useful for understanding your embedding budget.
For text-embedding-3-large, the cost is about 13 cents per million tokens.
Now the internal _chunk_section method.
This splits a single section's text into overlapping token-bounded chunks.
First, we tokenise the full section text using tiktoken.
If there are no tokens, we return an empty list.
If the entire section fits in one chunk,
we return a single chunk with all the text.
Otherwise, we use a sliding window.
We set a start pointer and move it forward by chunk size minus overlap.
For each window, we take tokens from start to end.
We decode them back to text using tiktoken's decode method.
If the decoded text is very short, less than 50 characters,
we skip it and break out of the loop.
We build a chunk for each window and increment the chunk index.
We advance the start pointer by the step size.
If step size is zero or negative, we log a warning and break.
This prevents infinite loops if overlap is set incorrectly.
Finally, _build_chunk constructs a FinancialChunk ORM instance.
We instantiate a TextParser to extract metrics from the chunk text.
Note that this happens on every call, which is fine for a tutorial.
In production, you would inject the TextParser once in __init__.
But for clarity in a course, we keep it explicit.
We call extract_metrics on the chunk text.
This returns a dictionary of financial metrics.
Then we create a FinancialChunk with all the fields.
Note that embedding is set to an empty list.
The embedding will be populated later by the embeddings module.
This separation of concerns keeps each module focused.
Now let's update the processing package __init__.py.
We import TextProcessor from text_processor.
Then expose it in __all__.
Now anywhere in the application, you can import.
from financial_rag.processing import TextProcessor
Our text processor is complete.
[## [SECTION: Step 11 — Embedding Client (Components #18–21)]]
Now let's build our embeddings module.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/retrieval/embeddings.py
This is a dual-provider embedding client.
OpenAI for production, sentence-transformers for development.
Before we write code, let me explain a critical issue.
The dimension mismatch problem.
Your SQL schema has vector with 3072 dimensions.
That's for OpenAI's text-embedding-3-large model.
But your development settings default to all-MiniLM-L6-v2.
That model produces only 384-dimensional vectors.
You cannot insert a 384-dim vector into a 3072-dim column.
PostgreSQL will reject it with a dimension mismatch error.
For local development, change your .env file.
Set EMBEDDING_PROVIDER to local, and EMBEDDING_DIMENSIONS to 384.
For production with OpenAI, use provider openai,
model text-embedding-3-large, and dimensions 3072.
Now let's understand the design of this module.
First, imports. We need logging and time.
From tenacity, we import retry, retry_if_exception_type, stop_after_attempt, and wait_exponential.
From our application, we import get_settings.
From utils, we import EmbeddingError.
We also define cost per million tokens for OpenAI models.
text-embedding-3-large costs 13 cents per million tokens.
Now define the EmbeddingProvider abstract base class.
This defines the protocol that all providers must follow.
Each provider must have a dimensions property,
and both sync and async embed_batch methods.
Now the OpenAIEmbeddingProvider.
This uses text-embedding-3-large and requires an API key.
In __init__, we check if the API key exists.
If not, we raise EmbeddingError with a helpful message.
We create both sync and async OpenAI clients.
The sync client is for bulk ingestion, the async client for real-time queries.
Notice the retry decorator on embed_batch.
It retries only on EmbeddingError, up to 3 attempts.
It uses exponential backoff. wait 2 seconds, then 4, then up to 30 seconds.
This handles rate limits gracefully.
Inside the method, we call the OpenAI embeddings API.
We pass the model, input texts, and requested dimensions.
We track latency and token usage.
We also calculate the cost of the request.
Then we validate that the returned dimensions match what we expected.
If not, we raise EmbeddingError.
The async version uses the async OpenAI client.
The structure is identical but uses await.
Both methods have the same retry decorator and error handling.
This ensures consistency across sync and async usage.
Now the LocalEmbeddingProvider.
This uses sentence-transformers with no API key required.
In __init__, we import SentenceTransformer inside the method.
This prevents import errors if the package isn't installed.
We load the model by name from settings.
This may take a moment on first run as it downloads the model.
The embed_batch method encodes texts using the local model.
We use convert_to_numpy equals True for performance.
Then we convert each numpy array to a Python list.
This ensures we return plain lists, not numpy arrays.
The async version runs the sync method in an executor.
This prevents blocking the async event loop.
Now the EmbeddingClient class.
This is the public interface that the rest of the application uses.
In __init__, we load settings and call _build_provider.
The provider is selected based on EMBEDDING_PROVIDER.
_build_provider has auto-fallback logic.
If OpenAI is requested but no API key exists, we fall back to local.
But only in development or testing environments.
In production, missing API key raises an error.
The embed_texts method handles batching automatically.
It splits the input texts into batches of EMBEDDING_BATCH_SIZE.
For each batch, it calls the provider's async embed method.
Then it extends the results list.
This is where the actual HTTP calls happen.
Batching is critical for efficiency with OpenAI.
The embed_chunks method takes a list of FinancialChunk objects.
It extracts the chunk_text from each chunk.
It calls embed_texts to get all embeddings.
Then it populates each chunk's embedding field in place.
This method is the primary interface for the ingestion pipeline.
You pass your chunks, and it returns them with embeddings.
Finally, embed_query is a convenience wrapper.
It embeds a single query string for similarity search.
Now let's update the retrieval package __init__.py.
We import EmbeddingClient from embeddings.
Then expose it in __all__.
Now anywhere in the application, you can import.
from financial_rag.retrieval import EmbeddingClient
Our embeddings module is complete.
Now you can turn text chunks into vectors.
[## [SECTION: Step 12 — Chunks Repository (Component #23)]]
Now let's build the chunks repository.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/storage/repositories/chunks.py
This is the core RAG retrieval table.
It owns vector similarity search for the entire application.
The chunks repository has three critical operations.
Similarity search, MMR search, and bulk upsert.
First, imports. We need logging and UUID.
From pgvector.sqlalchemy, we import Vector.
From SQLAlchemy, we import Float, Integer, SmallInteger, String, Text, func, select, and text.
And the JSONB and UUID types from postgresql dialects.
From our application, we import Base from database,
BaseRepository from base, and our custom exceptions.
Now define the FinancialChunk ORM model.
This maps to the financial_chunks table we created in Phase one.
We have id as primary key, filing_id as foreign key,
and denormalised fields like ticker, filing type, and fiscal year.
Denormalisation means we store these values directly in the chunks table.
This avoids expensive joins on every similarity search.
The embedding column uses pgvector's Vector type.
Notice it's set to 384 dimensions for local development.
We also have metrics and entities as JSONB columns.
These store extracted financial data and named entities.
And a sentiment score from minus one to plus one.
Finally, model_version tracks which embedding model produced this vector.
Now the ChunksRepository class.
It inherits from BaseRepository with FinancialChunk as the model.
We set model_class equal to FinancialChunk.
Then let's add the similarity search method.
First, similarity_search. This finds the most semantically similar chunks.
It uses cosine distance, the standard metric for embeddings.
Let me explain the ef_search parameter.
HNSW stands for Hierarchical Navigable Small World.
It's the index type pgvector uses for approximate nearest neighbour search.
ef_search controls the recall versus speed trade-off.
Higher ef_search, like 200, searches more graph nodes.
This gives better recall but is slower.
Lower ef_search, like 40, is faster but may miss true nearest neighbours.
The default 100 is a good balance for financial text.
Notice we use SET LOCAL to scope the setting to the current transaction.
It resets automatically when the session closes.
We use the cosine_distance operator on the embedding column.
This returns distance, where zero means identical and two means opposite.
We convert distance to similarity with one minus distance.
Then we add metadata filters for ticker, filing type, fiscal year, and section.
We order by distance ascending and limit the results.
The method returns a list of chunks with their similarity scores.
Now the MMR search method.
MMR stands for Maximal Marginal Relevance.
Standard similarity search can return ten near-duplicate chunks.
All from the same paragraph, just repeating the same information.
MMR solves this by balancing two things.
Relevance to the query and diversity among the results.
The formula is. lambda times similarity, minus one minus lambda times redundancy.
Lambda of 1.0 means pure similarity, zero means maximum diversity.
First, we fetch fetch_k candidates by similarity search.
Typically 20 candidates for every 5 results returned.
Then we iteratively select the candidate that maximizes the MMR score.
We remove selected candidates from the remaining list.
The result is a diverse set of chunks that still match the query.
This is much better for RAG than pure similarity search.
Now bulk_upsert. This inserts or updates chunks in bulk.
Upsert means update if exists, insert if not.
We use PostgreSQL's INSERT with ON CONFLICT DO UPDATE.
This makes re-ingestion safe.
If a chunk with the same ID already exists, we update its text, embedding, and metadata.
If not, we insert a new row.
This is critical for idempotent ingestion pipelines.
You can run the same ingestion twice without creating duplicates.
Two more utility methods.
get_by_filing returns all chunks for a filing, ordered by chunk index.
count_by_ticker returns the total chunk count for a ticker.
This is useful for monitoring and analytics.
Finally, a static method _cosine_similarity.
This computes cosine similarity between two vectors in pure Python.
Note that this is only used during MMR candidate re-ranking.
It is not on the hot path for similarity search.
The actual similarity search uses pgvector's native operator.
That is much faster because it runs inside PostgreSQL.
Now let's update the processing package __init__.py file.
We import TextProcessor from text_processor.
Then we expose it in __all__.
Now anywhere in our code, we can simply write.
from financial_rag.processing import TextProcessor
The processing package is complete.
Text chunking is now available to the rest of the application.
[## [SECTION: Step 13 — Vector Store (storage/vector_store.py)]]
Now let's build the vector store orchestrator.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/storage/vector_store.py
This sits between the processing layer and the retrieval layer.
It orchestrates the full chunk to embed to store pipeline.
The vector store has three main responsibilities.
Embedding chunks, upserting into PostgreSQL, and registering filings.
First, imports. We need logging and TYPE_CHECKING.
From retrieval, we import EmbeddingClient.
From storage, we import get_db_client.
And from repositories, we import ChunksRepository, FilingsRepository, and Filing.
Now the VectorStore class.
In __init__, we create an EmbeddingClient instance.
We log which provider is being used and the embedding dimensions.
This helps with debugging configuration issues.
The ingest method is the full pipeline for a single filing.
It takes chunks, filing metadata, and a file hash.
It returns a tuple of filing ID and the number of chunks stored.
Let me walk through each step.
Step one. deduplication check.
We create a database session and instantiate FilingsRepository.
We check if a filing with this hash already exists.
If yes, we raise DuplicateFilingError.
This prevents ingesting the same filing twice.
The ingestion pipeline is idempotent.
Step two. embed all chunks.
We call embed_chunks on the embedding client.
This method takes a list of FinancialChunk objects.
It populates the embedding field on each one.
The embedding client handles batching automatically.
It also tracks token usage and cost.
Step three. register the filing.
We generate a new UUID for the filing ID.
We create a Filing ORM instance with all the metadata.
Ticker, filing type, fiscal year, source URL, and file hash.
We set ingested_by to VectorStore and is_active to True.
Then we add it to the database using FilingsRepository.
Step four. bulk upsert the chunks.
First, we set the filing_id on all chunks.
They had placeholder IDs from the text processor.
Now we attach them to the correct filing.
Then we call bulk_upsert on ChunksRepository.
This inserts or updates all chunks in a single operation.
We log the completion with filing ID and chunk count.
Then return both to the caller.
Now the stats method.
This returns storage statistics for monitoring.
We get counts for chunks and filings.
Optionally filtered by a specific ticker.
We also include the embedding provider and dimensions.
This helps track which model is powering your vectors.
The stats method will be called by the API routes.
It gives you visibility into your vector store size.
Our vector store is complete.
Now you can ingest filings and search them with natural language.
[## [SECTION: Step 14 — Cache Namespace Constant]]
Now let's add the cache namespace constant for queries.
Open src/financial_rag/storage/cache.py
We already have namespace constants for chunks, embeddings, and analysis.
Now we need NS_QUERY for document retrieval results.
Add this constant just after the build_key function.
NS_QUERY equals query.
This will be used by the document retriever to scope cache keys.
All query results will be stored under finrag colon query colon namespace.
The cache client is now ready for the document retriever.
Now let's update the storage package __init__.py to include NS_QUERY.
We already have namespace constants from the cache module.
NS_CHUNKS, NS_EMBEDDINGS, NS_ANALYSIS, NS_MARKET.
Now we add NS_QUERY to the imports.
And add it to __all__.
This constant is used by the document retriever for cache keys.
All query results will be stored under finrag colon query namespace.
The storage package now exports all namespace constants.
Other parts of the application can access them easily.
[## [SECTION: Step 15 — Document Retriever & Hybrid Search (Components #24–28)]]
Now let's build the document retriever.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/retrieval/document_retriever.py
This retrieves relevant chunks for a query using vector similarity search.
It adds a Redis cache layer on top of VectorStore.
Why caching? Repeated queries with the same question and filters
hit the database and embedding API on every request.
That's expensive and slow.
Caching returns results instantly without recomputing.
First, imports. We need hashlib, json, logging, and dataclasses.
From config, we import get_settings.
From storage.cache, we import NS_QUERY, build_key, and get_cache_client.
From storage.vector_store, we import VectorStore.
And from utils, we import RetrievalError.
Now define the RetrievalResult dataclass.
This represents a single retrieved chunk with its similarity score.
It contains chunk ID, text, ticker, filing type, fiscal year,
section name, similarity score, and extracted metrics.
The to_context_string method formats this result for the LLM prompt.
It includes a source header so the model can cite its sources.
For example. source AAPL 10-K FY2023, Risk Factors, score zero point nine two.
Then the chunk text.
The from_chunk class method converts a FinancialChunk ORM object
into a RetrievalResult with its similarity score.
Now the DocumentRetriever class.
In __init__, we load settings and optionally accept a VectorStore instance.
If no vector store is provided, we create one.
This allows dependency injection for testing.
The retrieve method is the main public API.
It takes a question and optional filters.
We determine the effective limit and score threshold.
Limit defaults to TOP_K_RESULTS from settings.
Score threshold defaults to VECTOR_SEARCH_THRESHOLD.
Chunks below this score are filtered out.
First, we check the cache.
If use_cache is True, we build a cache key from all query parameters.
The cache key is a SHA-256 hash of the question and filters.
We scope it under the NS_QUERY namespace.
If we find a cached result, we return it immediately.
This bypasses the vector search entirely.
If not cached, we call search on the vector store.
We pass the question and all filters.
The vector store handles embedding and similarity search.
It returns raw results with similarity scores.
We convert each raw result to a RetrievalResult.
We filter out any chunks below the score threshold.
Then we cache the results for future queries.
We only cache if we have results and caching is enabled.
The cache TTL comes from settings.
Default is one hour.
Now the build_context method.
This assembles retrieved chunks into a single context string for the LLM.
It respects a token budget to avoid exceeding the model's context window.
Budget defaults to MAX_CONTEXT_TOKENS from settings.
We use tiktoken again to count tokens exactly.
We iterate through results in order of relevance.
For each result, we call to_context_string to get a formatted block.
We encode it and count the tokens.
If adding this block would exceed the budget, we stop.
We log how many tokens and chunks were used.
Then we join all blocks with a separator of two newlines and dashes.
This creates a clear separation between sources.
Now the cache helper methods.
_build_cache_key creates a deterministic key from query parameters.
We put all parameters into a dictionary and serialize to JSON.
We sort keys to ensure the same parameters produce the same string.
Then we take a SHA-256 hash of that string.
This gives us a fixed-length, unique identifier.
We use build_key with NS_QUERY to namespace the key.
Final format. finrag colon query colon the hash.
_get_cached retrieves from Redis and deserializes.
If Redis fails, we log a warning and return None.
Cache failures are non-fatal.
We fall back to vector search instead of crashing.
_set_cached serializes results and stores them in Redis.
We convert each RetrievalResult to a dictionary first.
Then we call client.set with the key and serializable data.
The TTL is handled automatically by the cache client.
Now let's build the hybrid search module.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/retrieval/hybrid_search.py
Hybrid search combines vector similarity with full-text search.
It uses Reciprocal Rank Fusion, or RRF, to combine scores.
Why do we need this? Vector search alone works well for semantic questions.
But it can struggle with exact terms like ticker symbols or dollar amounts.
Full-text search excels at exact matches.
Hybrid search gives you the best of both worlds.
First, imports. We need logging and TYPE_CHECKING.
From sqlalchemy, we import text for raw SQL queries.
From our application, we import get_settings.
From retrieval, we import RetrievalResult and EmbeddingClient.
From storage, we import get_db_client and ChunksRepository.
And from utils, we import RetrievalError.
Now the HybridSearcher class.
In __init__, we load settings and create an embedding client.
We also define the RRF constant K.
60 is the standard value from the original 2009 paper.
The search method is the public entry point.
It takes a question and optional filters.
We determine the effective limit and alpha weight.
Alpha defaults to HYBRID_SEARCH_ALPHA from settings, which is 0.7.
We fetch three times the requested limit for candidates.
Fusion will narrow the list down.
Then we run both searches concurrently using asyncio.gather.
Vector search and text search happen in parallel.
After both searches complete, we fuse the results using RRF.
The fused results are sorted by combined score.
The _vector_search method embeds the question.
Then it calls similarity_search on the chunks repository.
This returns a list of chunks with cosine similarity scores.
The scores range from 0 to 1, where 1 is identical.
The _text_search method uses PostgreSQL's trigram similarity.
It requires the idx_chunks_text_trgm GIN index we created in Phase one.
We build a parameterized SQL query with similarity function.
The similarity function compares chunk_text to the query string.
We apply the same metadata filters as vector search.
Ticker, filing type, and fiscal year.
We order by trigram similarity descending.
And limit to the requested number.
If the text search fails, we log a warning and return an empty list.
Text search failures are non-fatal.
After getting matching IDs and scores, we fetch the full chunk objects.
Then we return them as a list of chunk and score tuples.
Now the most important method. _reciprocal_rank_fusion.
This combines the two ranked lists into one.
Let me explain RRF.
Reciprocal Rank Fusion combines two ranked lists without needing raw scores.
Vector similarity and trigram similarity are not on the same scale.
Vector scores cluster around 0.7 to 0.9.
Text scores cluster around 0.1 to 0.4.
You cannot average them directly. RRF solves this by using rank position.
It cares about where a document appears in each list, not the raw score.
The formula is. alpha times one over K plus vector rank,
plus one minus alpha times one over K plus text rank.
K is 60, the standard RRF constant.
Alpha is the weight for vector results, default 0.7.
Documents that appear in both lists get contributions from both terms.
They receive a higher fused score.
Documents that appear in only one list still get a partial score.
They are included but ranked lower.
First, we build rank maps for both result sets.
Rank is one-indexed, meaning the first result has rank 1.
We collect all unique chunk IDs across both lists.
Then we build a lookup dictionary from ID to chunk object.
For each chunk ID, we compute the vector RRF contribution.
If the chunk is in the vector list, we add one over K plus its rank.
If not, we add zero.
Same for text RRF.
Then we compute the fused score as alpha times vector RRF
plus one minus alpha times text RRF.
We sort by fused score descending and take the top limit.
Then we convert each to a RetrievalResult and return.
Now let's update the retrieval package __init__.py.
We import DocumentRetriever, RetrievalResult, HybridSearcher, EmbeddingClient.
And from query_engine we import QueryEngine and QueryResult.
Then we expose all six in __all__.
Now any part of the application can import from financial_rag.retrieval.
Let me summarize when to use hybrid search.
Use hybrid search as a fallback when vector search confidence is low.
When the best vector score is below VECTOR_SEARCH_THRESHOLD.
Also use it when the query contains specific financial terms.
Ticker symbols, dollar amounts, dates, or product names.
The hybrid search module is complete.
You now have three retrieval options. vector, MMR, and hybrid.
[## [SECTION: Common Errors and Fixes — Phases 2 & 3]]
Let me walk through common errors in Phases 2 and 3.
And how to fix them.
Error one. tiktoken loading fails.
cl100k_base encoding not available.
The cause is an outdated tiktoken version.
Or network issues downloading the encoding.
The fix. upgrade tiktoken with pip install.
pip install dash upgrade tiktoken.
Error two. dimension mismatch on insert.
384-dim vector into 3072-dim column.
The cause is using local embeddings but production schema.
Set EMBEDDING_DIMENSIONS to 384 in your .env file.
Or change the schema to vector of 384.
But better to keep schema as 3072 and configure .env correctly.
Error three. Chunk overlap validation fails.
CHUNK_OVERLAP_TOKENS must be less than CHUNK_SIZE_TOKENS.
The cause is .env file has overlap greater than or equal to chunk size.
Reduce CHUNK_OVERLAP_TOKENS to 50 or 100.
Error four. OpenAI API key missing in production.
EmbeddingError at runtime.
The cause is EMBEDDING_PROVIDER set to openai but no key.
The fix. set OPENAI_API_KEY in .env or switch to local provider.
Error five. sentence-transformers not installed.
LocalEmbeddingProvider import error.
The cause is missing package.
Run pip install sentence-transformers.
Error six. pgvector operator not found.
cosine_distance operator doesn't exist.
The cause is pgvector extension not created in database.
Run CREATE EXTENSION IF NOT EXISTS vector in psql.
Then recreate your containers with docker compose down minus v and up minus d.
Error seven. SQLAlchemy async engine not connected.
DatabaseClient._engine is None.
The cause is calling get_db_client without calling connect first.
Call await db.connect() at application startup.
Error eight. HNSW ef_search parameter not applied.
SET LOCAL hnsw.ef_search fails.
The cause is using pgvector version older than 0.5.0.
Upgrade pgvector in your Docker image.
Bookmark this section.
When you hit an error, you'll know exactly where to look.
[## [SECTION: What's Next — Phase 4]]
Now let me preview Phase 4.
In Phase 4, we build the intelligent reasoning layer.
The LLM agent with tool calling.
We'll create a multi-provider LLM client.
OpenAI, Groq, and Anthropic with a unified interface.
We'll define tool definitions for OpenAI function calling.
search_filings and compare_filings.
We'll build an agent reasoning loop.
The model decides what to search for and when.
Three analysis styles. analyst, executive, risk.
Each with a different system prompt.
An append-only analysis_history audit trail in PostgreSQL.
Every query is recorded for compliance.
A circuit breaker that gracefully falls back to QueryEngine.
When the LLM is down, you still get answers from retrieved context.
And the /query endpoint wiring everything together.
The file tree for Phase 4 will include.
src/financial_rag/retrieval/query_engine.py.
src/financial_rag/agents/financial_agent.py.
src/financial_rag/agents/__init__.py.
src/financial_rag/storage/repositories/analysis.py.
And updates to api/routes.py and api/models.py.
Phase 3 is complete.
Your vector search infrastructure is ready.
In Phase 4, we add the LLM intelligence on top.
The system will answer questions in natural language.
Ready to proceed to Phase 4?
---
**End of Phase 3. I have Phases 4 through 12 ready. Shall I continue with Phase 4?**