Before building an AI project, you need three things:
Python, a code editor, and a terminal.
Head over to python.org and download the
latest stable version of Python.
When you install Python, you also get Pip
—short for "Pip Installs Packages."
Instead of writing everything from scratch,
Pip lets you add database drivers, API frameworks,
or AI libraries instantly.
It also keeps your tools up to date,
ensuring everything works smoothly together.
In simple terms, Pip saves you time by giving you
access to thousands of packages for modern AI apps.
Now that you have the tools, we're ready to
create our AI agent.
Create a folder on your desktop called
financial-rag-agents.
Drag and drop this folder into VS Code,
or open it with your preferred editor.
I recommend VS Code because it's free,
fully featured, and built for Python and AI.
You get integrated terminal, error reporting,
and quick project setup out of the box.
I'll be using uv to bootstrap the project.
It offers lightning-fast dependency resolution
and optimized build speed.
It's an excellent choice for quickly setting up
a Python project.
Open the VS Code terminal.
Go to View > Terminal, or press Ctrl + Backtick.
Type: pip install uv
Then type: uv init .
This initializes uv in your current directory.
uv has bootstrapped several files for us.
Let's quickly go over what each one does.
The .gitignore file tells Git which files or folders
to exclude from version control.
This prevents committing sensitive data, large files,
or temporary files to your repository.
Files listed here are never uploaded to GitHub.
Next is .python-version.
This single-line file specifies which Python version to use.
uv reads this to know which Python to download or use.
pyenv reads it to switch versions automatically.
This ensures all team members use the same Python version.
main.py is the entry point of your application.
This is the first file that runs.
uv creates this as a starting template.
Next is pyproject.toml.
This is the central configuration file for modern Python projects.
It replaces setup.py, requirements.txt, and setup.cfg.
One file that rules every other.
uv uses this for dependencies, scripts, and settings.
README.md is the markdown file that describes your project.
This is what you and others see on the GitHub front page.
Now let's create a file called .env.
This is a private file containing your actual configuration values.
It holds secrets like API keys and passwords.
You must never commit this file to GitHub.
Add .env to your .gitignore so Git ignores it.
If you want a template showing what configuration values are needed
without the actual secrets, create a .env.example file.
Now let's create our project structure using mkdir -p.
We'll build out our main financial_rag package with subdirectories
for config, storage with repositories, ingestion, parsing,
processing, retrieval, agents, API routes, monitoring, and security.
Then our supporting folders: infrastructure with Docker init,
migrations versions, unit and integration tests,
plus notebooks, scripts, and docs.
One command, and your entire scaffold is ready.
Now we need to mark these directories as Python packages.
We'll use touch to create an __init__.py file in
every directory inside src and tests.
Starting with the src directory itself, then financial_rag,
and every subfolder beneath it: agents, api, config,
ingestion, monitoring, procesing, retrieval, storage, utils
Then the tests directory, plus unit and integration.
This ensures Python treats them as importable modules.
Run these commands, and our package structure is ready for code.
Before we install dependencies,
let's set up a virtual environment.
A virtual environment is an isolated Python workspace
for each project. Here's why it's essential.
Imagine two projects needing different versions of Django.
If you install both globally, the second one overwrites the first.
Project A needs Django 3.2. Project B needs Django 5.0.
Only one version can exist globally, so they conflict.
The solution is a virtual environment per project.
Project A gets its own venv with Django 3.2.
Project B gets its own venv with Django 5.0.
They never interfere with each other.
Virtual environments solve three real problems:
version conflicts, permission errors, and team collaboration.
You can create a virtual environment using uv.
Just type: uv venv
Then activate it. On Mac or Linux, type:
source .venv/bin/activate
On Windows, type:
.venv\Scripts\activate
You can also use the traditional Python command:
python -m venv .venv
This creates the same virtual environment.
Activate it the same way we just showed.
If you're curious what's inside .venv, it contains
all your isolated dependencies—FastAPI, SQLAlchemy, and more.
This folder is large and fully managed by pip.
You never need to interact with it directly.
Virtual environments are not optional for professional development.
They are essential.
Now let's install our project dependencies using pip.
Type: pip install -e .[dev]
The -e flag installs in editable mode,
and [dev] includes our development dependencies.
Now that our initial setup is complete,
let's move to the config directory.
[## FILE: src/financial_rag/config/settings.py]
Let's create our unified settings file.
This is the single source of truth for all configuration.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/config/settings.py
First, imports. We need logging, lru_cache from functools,
Path from pathlib, and Literal from typing.
From Pydantic, we import Field, SecretStr,
computed_field, and model_validator.
From pydantic_settings, we import BaseSettings
and SettingsConfigDict.
Now our Settings class inherits from BaseSettings.
Inside model_config, we tell Pydantic to read from a .env file,
ignore case, ignore extra fields, and validate defaults.
First section: Environment.
APP_ENV can be development, staging, production, or testing.
Default is development.
APP_NAME and APP_VERSION are simple strings.
Next, derived flags. DEBUG, TESTING, and MOCK_EXTERNAL_APIS.
These are auto-set based on APP_ENV.
We use a model validator called apply_env_defaults.
In development or testing, DEBUG becomes True automatically.
In testing mode, TESTING and MOCK_EXTERNAL_APIS
both become True.
Now paths. These are computed fields, not stored values.
PROJECT_ROOT finds the absolute path where pyproject.toml lives.
It goes up three directories from the current file.
DATA_DIR, RAW_DATA_DIR, PROCESSED_DATA_DIR,
and VECTOR_STORE_DIR all derive from PROJECT_ROOT.
Notice VECTOR_STORE_DIR has special logic.
In testing mode, it uses /tmp to avoid polluting real data.
Next, API Server settings. Host, port, and worker count.
CORS_ORIGINS is stored as a comma-separated string.
We also provide a computed CORS_ORIGINS_LIST that parses it.
Now API keys. OPENAI_API_KEY and GROQ_API_KEY
use SecretStr so they never appear in logs.
Embedding configuration. Provider can be OpenAI or local.
Default is local with the all-MiniLM model.
LLM configuration. Provider can be OpenAI, Anthropic, or local.
Default model is GPT 3.5 Turbo.
LLM_BASE_URL is set to Groq's endpoint,
giving you fast inference with OpenAI's API format.
PostgreSQL with pgvector. Host, port, user,
and a required password with no default.
Without POSTGRES_PASSWORD in your .env file,
the app will refuse to start.
Two computed fields: DATABASE_URL for asyncpg,
and DATABASE_URL_SYNC for Alembic migrations.
Redis configuration follows the same pattern.
Host, port, DB, and a required password.
REDIS_URL is computed to format the connection string
with the password embedded.
Processing and retrieval settings. Chunk size in tokens,
overlap, top K results, and hybrid search alpha.
Logging. Log level and format.
In production, we automatically switch to JSON format
and WARNING level.
Rate limiting and API key authentication.
You can enable API keys by setting API_KEY_ENABLED to True.
SEC EDGAR ingestion settings. User agent is required
by the SEC. We respect their 10 request per second limit.
Now the validators. First, validate_chunk_settings
ensures overlap is less than chunk size.
The main startup validator collects ALL configuration issues
before raising. You see every problem at once,
not one at a time.
It checks for missing API keys in production,
and enforces production hardening like specific CORS origins
and DEBUG turned off.
Finally, get_settings is decorated with lru_cache.
The Settings object is instantiated exactly once per process.
Now let me explain three critical patterns you just saw.
Pattern one: SecretStr for secrets that never leak.
When you print a SecretStr field, you only see asterisks.
It never appears in logs, repr, or error messages.
To actually use the value, call get_secret_value.
This forces you to be explicit about where secrets are exposed.
Pattern two: computed_field for derived values.
DATABASE_URL is not stored in .env.
It's built on-demand from individual fields.
The password is assembled at runtime
and never cached in a plain string that might appear
in a stack trace.
Pattern three: lru_cache with maxsize one.
Settings reads and validates every field from the environment.
That's expensive work. lru_cache ensures it happens once.
In tests, you clear the cache before changing
environment variables with get_settings.cache_clear.
Our settings file is complete.
Now let's create the config package __init__.
```
---
[## FILE: src/financial_rag/config/__init__.py]
Now let's create the __init__.py file inside our config directory.
This file is deliberately minimal.
It gives us a clean import surface for the rest of the application.
We import Settings and get_settings from the settings module,
then expose them in __all__.
Now anywhere in our code, we can simply write:
from financial_rag.config import get_settings
The config package is complete. Settings are ready.
```
---
[## FILE: src/financial_rag/storage/database.py]
Now let's create our database client.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/storage/database.py
This is an async PostgreSQL client
built on SQLAlchemy 2.0 with asyncpg.
First, let's import our dependencies.
We need logging, asynccontextmanager, and typing.
From SQLAlchemy, we need text, async engine components,
and DeclarativeBase for our ORM models.
From our application, we import get_settings
and two custom exceptions.
Now define our Base class for all ORM models.
It inherits from DeclarativeBase. This is where
our table mappings will live later.
Next, an internal function called _build_engine.
This creates the async SQLAlchemy engine from our settings.
We load our settings, then call create_async_engine
with the DATABASE_URL from settings.
The pool configuration uses our DB_POOL_MIN_SIZE as pool_size,
and max_overflow is DB_POOL_MAX_SIZE minus the minimum.
We set pool_recycle to recycle old connections,
and pool_pre_ping to True to silently evict dead connections.
Asyncpg-specific connect_args include a command_timeout
and server_settings like application_name.
Echo and echo_pool are set to settings.DEBUG.
In development, you'll see SQL logs.
In production, silence.
Now the DatabaseClient class. This owns the engine
and session factory for the entire application lifetime.
The __init__ declares _engine and _session_factory,
both starting as None.
The connect method initialises the engine and session factory.
Call this once at application startup.
It calls _build_engine to create the engine,
then builds an async session factory bound to that engine.
We set expire_on_commit to False to avoid
lazy-load errors after commit.
Then we verify the connection with _verify_connection,
which runs SELECT 1.
If anything fails, we raise a DatabaseConnectionError
with the actual error message.
The disconnect method disposes the engine
and drains the connection pool.
Call this once at application shutdown.
Now the session context manager.
This yields a transactional AsyncSession.
If the session factory is None, we raise
DatabaseConnectionError saying connect first.
Inside the context, we yield the session.
On clean exit, we commit. On any exception, we roll back.
Finally, we always close the session
to return it to the connection pool.
Next, the connection context manager.
This yields a raw AsyncConnection for DDL operations.
This is not for request handlers.
Use session for queries. Use connection for schema creation.
Now health_check. This runs a lightweight liveness probe
against the database.
It returns PostgreSQL version, server start time,
pool size, checked out connections, and overflow.
If the database is unreachable, we raise
DatabaseConnectionError.
Next, verify_pgvector. This checks if the pgvector
extension is installed in PostgreSQL.
We run SELECT from pg_extension where extname is vector.
If installed, it returns True and logs success.
If not, we log an error telling the user
to run CREATE EXTENSION IF NOT EXISTS vector.
Finally, the internal _verify_connection method.
This is a simple ping to confirm connectivity at startup.
We also have an engine property that raises
DatabaseConnectionError if accessed before connect.
Now the singleton pattern.
_db_client is a module-level variable starting as None.
get_db_client is async.
If the client doesn't exist, we create a new DatabaseClient.
Note that connect is NOT called here.
The caller is responsible for calling connect
at application startup.
Finally, get_session is a FastAPI dependency.
It gets the client and yields a session per HTTP request.
Usage in a route looks like this:
async def list_items, with session as a dependency.
Our database client is complete.
```
---
[## FILE: src/financial_rag/storage/cache.py]
Now let's create our Redis cache client.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/storage/cache.py
This is an async Redis client with JSON serialisation
and connection pool lifecycle management.
First, let's import our dependencies.
We need json, logging, and typing.
From redis.asyncio, we need Redis and ConnectionPool.
From redis.exceptions, we need RedisError.
From our application, we import get_settings
and two custom exceptions.
Now define our key namespace constants.
All cache keys follow this format: finrag colon namespace colon identifier.
We have namespaces for chunks, embeddings, queries,
analysis, and market. And a build_key helper.
Now the CacheClient class.
This owns the connection pool for the application lifetime.
The __init__ declares _pool and _redis,
both starting as None.
The connect method initialises the Redis connection pool.
Call this once at application startup.
We create a ConnectionPool from our REDIS_URL
with max connections, socket timeouts, and decode_responses set to True.
decode_responses means Redis always returns strings,
never bytes. This simplifies our code.
We set health_check_interval to 30 seconds
for background pings.
Then we create the Redis client from the pool
and ping immediately to verify connectivity.
The disconnect method calls aclose on the Redis client
and the pool, then resets both references.
Now core typed operations. First, get.
It retrieves the raw value from Redis.
If the key doesn't exist, it returns None.
If it finds a value, it runs json.loads to deserialise it.
If JSON parsing fails, we log a warning and return None.
Next, set. This serialises a value with json.dumps
and stores it with a TTL.
If you don't provide a TTL, it falls back to
REDIS_DEFAULT_TTL_SECONDS from settings.
We use default=str in json.dumps so any non-standard types
are converted to strings automatically.
Then we call setex with the key, TTL, and serialised value.
Returns True on success.
Delete removes a key from cache.
Returns True if the key existed, False if it did not.
Exists returns True if the key is present.
Expire resets the TTL on an existing key.
Now clear_namespace. This deletes all keys under a namespace prefix.
We build a pattern like finrag colon namespace colon star.
Then we use scan_iter to iterate without blocking the Redis server.
For each key, we delete it and count the deletions.
This is much safer than the KEYS command, which blocks.
Now health_check. This pings Redis and returns
version, memory usage, connected clients, and pool stats.
If the client isn't initialised, we return disconnected status.
If ping fails, we raise CacheConnectionError.
The internal _assert_connected raises
CacheConnectionError if _redis is None.
_pool_stats extracts connection pool information
like max_connections and created_connections if available.
Now the singleton pattern.
_cache_client is a module-level variable starting as None.
get_cache_client is async.
If the client doesn't exist, we create a new CacheClient.
Note that connect is NOT called here.
The caller must call connect at application startup.
Our cache client is complete.
Now let's update the storage package __init__.
```
---
[## FILE: src/financial_rag/storage/__init__.py]
Now let's update the storage package __init__.py file.
This file consolidates all storage-related exports
into a single clean import surface.
From the cache module, we import namespace constants,
CacheClient, build_key, and get_cache_client.
From the database module, we import Base, DatabaseClient,
get_db_client, and get_session.
Then we define __all__ to explicitly declare our public API.
This includes all namespace constants, Base, both clients,
and all three accessor functions.
Now anywhere in our application, we can import like this.
From financial_rag.storage import get_db_client.
No more long nested imports.
The storage package is now a clean, well-organized module.
Our storage package is complete.
Both database and cache are ready to be used across the application.
```
---
[## FILE: infrastructure/docker/init/create_schema.sql]
Now let's create our database initialization script.
We'll put it in infrastructure/docker/init/create_schema.sql
This script runs automatically the first time the PostgreSQL container starts.
These statements are idempotent, so they can run safely multiple times.
First, we enable four PostgreSQL extensions.
vector for embeddings, uuid-ossp for generating UUIDs.
pg_trgm for trigram text search, and btree_gin for advanced indexing.
All use IF NOT EXISTS so they only install once.
Now create the filings table.
This stores metadata for each SEC filing we ingest.
We have ticker, filing type, fiscal year and quarter,
filed date, source URL, and a unique file hash.
Ingested at timestamp with time zone defaults to now.
Is active flag lets us soft-delete filings.
A CHECK constraint ensures filing type is one of six allowed values:
10-K, 10-Q, 8-K, 20-F, DEF 14A, or S-1.
Three indexes on filings. One on ticker with fiscal year descending.
One on filing type with fiscal year descending.
And a partial index on active filings only.
The WHERE clause makes this index smaller and faster.
Now the financial_chunks table.
This is our core table for embedding storage.
Each chunk belongs to a filing via foreign key to filings.id.
On delete cascade means when a filing is deleted, all its chunks are deleted.
We store ticker and filing type denormalized.
This avoids joins for common queries and keeps vector search fast.
Chunk_text contains the actual text content.
Token_count is useful for monitoring token usage.
The embedding column uses vector data type with 3072 dimensions.
This matches OpenAI's text-embedding-3-large model.
Metrics is a JSONB column for chunk-level statistics.
Entities is another JSONB for named entity extraction.
Sentiment score ranges from negative 1.0 to positive 1.0.
model_version tracks which embedding model produced the vector.
Several indexes on financial_chunks.
Ticker with fiscal year descending, and filing id with section.
We also index the JSONB columns metrics and entities using GIN.
GIN indexes are designed for array and JSON data.
Finally, a trigram index on chunk_text.
This enables fast text search without needing a separate search engine.
Now the analysis_history table.
This logs every query users make to our RAG system.
We store the question, answer, analysis style, and agent type.
Analysis style can be analyst, executive, or risk.
Latency in milliseconds helps monitor performance.
Source chunk IDs is a PostgreSQL array of UUIDs.
Real time used indicates if we fetched live market data.
Error captures any failures during the query.
Session ID lets us group related queries.
Created at with time zone defaults to now.
Three indexes on analysis history.
One on ticker with creation time descending.
One on session ID where session ID is not null.
And one on agent type with creation time descending,
useful for analyzing which agents are used most.
Finally, a schema migrations table.
This tracks which database migrations have been applied.
We insert one record for version 001 with a description.
When you add new tables or columns later, add another migration.
This script is now complete.
When Docker starts PostgreSQL, it will run this automatically.
You can verify the schema by connecting to the database
and running backslash dt to list tables.
# PHASE 1 — CONTINUED
[## [SECTION: Docker Compose — Development Environment]]
Now that we have our schema ready, let's set up the services that will run our database and cache.
We'll use Docker Compose to orchestrate everything.
First, let me explain what Docker Compose does.
It lets us define multiple containers that work together as one application.
We need two core services to start.
PostgreSQL with the pgvector extension for our vector database.
And Redis for caching query results and rate limiting.
Both will run in containers on your machine.
We'll also have optional tools you can start if you want.
pgAdmin for browsing the database with a web interface.
And Redis Commander for inspecting what's in your cache.
These are in a separate profile so they don't run by default.
Let's create the docker-compose.yml file in the project root.
We'll define reusable anchors first to keep the configuration DRY.
x-logging sets up JSON file logging with a max size of 10 megabytes.
It keeps 5 rotated files so logs don't fill up your disk.
x-restart sets the restart policy to unless-stopped.
This means containers automatically restart unless you manually stop them.
Now healthchecks. These tell Docker when a service is actually ready.
Not just when the container started, but when it can accept traffic.
x-postgres-healthcheck uses pg_isready to verify PostgreSQL is accepting connections.
It retries 5 times, waiting 10 seconds between checks.
x-redis-healthcheck uses redis-cli ping with the password.
It confirms Redis is responding before other services try to connect.
Now the services section. First, PostgreSQL with pgvector.
We use the official image pgvector/pgvector:pg17.
The container name comes from an environment variable with a fallback.
If POSTGRES_CONTAINER is not set, it defaults to finrag-postgres.
We apply the restart and healthcheck anchors using YAML merge syntax.
The double asterisk and less than less than syntax pulls in both anchors.
Environment variables are read from your .env file with fallbacks.
If POSTGRES_DB is not in .env, it defaults to financial_rag.
Notice the syntax on POSTGRES_PASSWORD.
The colon question mark means Docker Compose will refuse to start.
If this variable is not set in .env, the command fails immediately.
This is fail-fast at startup, not fail-at-connection.
Much better than finding out the password is missing when your app tries to connect.
Ports maps the container's internal port 5432 to a host port.
You can override the host port with POSTGRES_PORT in .env.
Volumes mounts two things. postgres_data for persistent storage.
This named volume survives container restarts, so your data isn't lost.
And a read-only mount of our init directory.
Any dot SQL file in infrastructure/docker/init runs automatically.
On the first container start only.
The colon ro means read-only.
The container cannot modify your init scripts.
This is a security best practice.
Resource limits let you cap memory and CPU.
Default is 2 gigabytes of memory and 2 CPUs.
With a reservation of 512 megabytes guaranteed.
Now Redis. We use the redis:7-alpine image.
Alpine is a lightweight Linux distribution.
The image is around 30 megabytes instead of 300.
The command section configures Redis at runtime.
appendonly yes enables persistence to disk.
requirepass sets the password from your .env file.
maxmemory limits Redis to 512 megabytes by default.
maxmemory-policy allkeys-lru is the eviction policy.
When Redis hits its memory limit, it evicts the least recently used key.
This is the correct policy for a cache.
You would never use this for a primary data store like PostgreSQL.
Now the tools profile. These services only start if you ask for them.
docker compose up with the profile tools flag.
pgAdmin is a web-based PostgreSQL administration tool.
You can browse tables, run queries, and inspect indexes.
Email and password come from environment variables.
The password uses the same colon question mark syntax.
It is required.
depends_on with condition service_healthy waits for PostgreSQL.
pgAdmin won't start until postgres is ready to accept connections.
Redis Commander is a web-based Redis administration tool.
It runs on port 8081 by default.
We pass the Redis password through the REDIS_HOSTS variable.
HTTP_USER and HTTP_PASSWORD control access to the web UI.
Both tools have memory limits to prevent them from starving core services.
pgAdmin gets 512 megabytes. Redis Commander gets 256 megabytes.
Now the network. We create a bridge network called finrag-network.
All services can communicate with each other using container names as hostnames.
The subnet is 172.28.0.0 slash 16.
You can override this with NETWORK_SUBNET in .env if there's a conflict.
Finally, volumes. These persist data outside the containers.
postgres_data for your database files.
redis_data for Redis persistence files.
pgadmin_data for pgAdmin's saved connections and query histories.
Named volumes survive docker compose down.
To also delete your data volumes, you need docker compose down minus v.
Let me recap the key things to understand.
First, the colon question mark syntax on passwords.
Docker Compose will refuse to start if these variables are missing.
Fail-fast, not fail-at-connection.
Second, the init directory mount with colon ro.
Any SQL file in infrastructure/docker/init runs once on first start.
The container cannot modify your scripts.
Third, Redis eviction policy allkeys-lru.
Least recently used keys are evicted first.
Correct for a cache, wrong for a primary database.
To start only the core services, run docker compose up minus d.
To include the admin tools, run docker compose with profile tools up minus d.
To tear everything down, docker compose down.
To also delete your data volumes, add the minus v flag.
Now that our docker-compose.yml is ready,
let's start the services and verify everything works.
[## [SECTION: Infrastructure Verification — Testing PostgreSQL, Extensions, and Redis]]
Now that our docker-compose.yml is ready, let's start the services.
We'll use the utility script to make this easier.
First, make sure your .env file exists with the required passwords.
POSTGRES_PASSWORD and REDIS_PASSWORD must be set.
Then run the start script.
./scripts/start.sh
The script does preflight checks first.
It verifies .env exists, docker is installed, and the daemon is running.
Then it starts PostgreSQL and Redis.
It waits for both to become healthy before continuing.
You should see output like this.
Starting PostgreSQL and Redis...
Waiting for finrag-postgres to be healthy...
✅ finrag-postgres is healthy
Waiting for finrag-redis to be healthy...
✅ finrag-redis is healthy
The script will then ask if you want to start management tools.
Type y for pgAdmin and Redis Commander if you want them.
Once everything is running, let's verify our schema was created correctly.
First, check that all four tables exist.
Run this command.
docker exec finrag-postgres psql -U finrag -d financial_rag -c backslash dt
You should see four tables.
filings, financial_chunks, analysis_history, and schema_migrations.
Now let's verify our PostgreSQL extensions are installed.
Run this command.
docker exec finrag-postgres psql -U finrag -d financial_rag -c
SELECT extname FROM pg_extension WHERE extname IN ('vector','pg_trgm','uuid-ossp')
You should see three rows returned.
vector, pg_trgm, and uuid-ossp.
If any are missing, the init script did not run correctly.
Check that create_schema.sql is in the infrastructure/docker/init directory.
Finally, let's verify Redis is responding.
Run this command.
docker exec finrag-redis redis-cli -a your-redis-password ping
You should get back PONG in all capital letters.
If you get an error, check that REDIS_PASSWORD matches what's in your .env file.
If all three checks pass, your infrastructure is ready.
PostgreSQL has the correct schema, extensions are installed, and Redis is responding.
Now let's verify our settings work correctly from Python.
Run this quick smoke test.
python -c "from financial_rag.config import get_settings; s = get_settings(); print(f'env= debug=')"
Expected output. env=development debug=True
Now verify the database connection URL.
python -c "from financial_rag.config import get_settings; s = get_settings(); print(s.DATABASE_URL.startswith('postgresql+asyncpg://'))"
Expected output. True
Finally, verify Redis connection.
python -c "from financial_rag.config import get_settings; s = get_settings(); print(s.REDIS_URL.startswith('redis://'))"
Expected output. True
If all three Python checks pass, your configuration is correct.
Your database and cache clients can connect.
If any check fails, review your .env file.
Make sure POSTGRES_PASSWORD and REDIS_PASSWORD are set correctly.
Our infrastructure is verified and ready.
We can now start writing tests.
[## [FILE: tests/conftest.py — Pytest Fixtures for Mock Database, Cache, Embeddings, and Test Data]]
Now let's set up our test environment.
We'll create tests/conftest.py for shared test fixtures.
conftest.py is a special file that pytest recognizes automatically.
Any fixture defined here is available to every test in the suite.
First, let's understand what a fixture is.
A fixture is code that runs before your test to set up its environment.
Fixtures handle things like database sessions, mock objects,
or environment variables so you don't repeat yourself.
Let's start with imports.
We need os for environment variables, and AsyncMock and patch from unittest.mock.
From our application, we import get_settings.
Now we define VALID_SECRETS, a dictionary with test values for our required secrets.
POSTGRES_PASSWORD, REDIS_PASSWORD, and APP_ENV set to testing.
These satisfy the validation that normally requires a .env file.
Notice the passwords are at least 32 characters.
This matches the real password requirements without triggering any validation errors.
Now the first fixture. clear_settings_cache.
It has autouse equals True, so it runs automatically for every test.
Before the test, it calls get_settings.cache_clear.
After the test, it calls it again.
This ensures each test gets a fresh Settings instance.
Without this, environment variable changes from one test could leak into the next.
Next, the test_env fixture.
It patches os.environ with our VALID_SECRETS dictionary.
clear=False means we add to existing environment variables instead of replacing everything.
This allows the test to run even if other environment variables are needed.
Why is this important? Our Settings class validates that POSTGRES_PASSWORD
and REDIS_PASSWORD exist. Without this patch, tests would fail because those variables are missing.
Now the mock_db_session fixture.
This returns an AsyncMock that simulates a SQLAlchemy async session.
We mock execute, commit, and rollback methods.
None of them do real work, but they exist so our code can call them without errors.
Using AsyncMock is critical here.
Real database sessions use async await syntax, so our mock must also be async.
The mock_cache_client fixture works the same way.
It mocks get, set, delete, and health_check.
get returns None by default, meaning cache miss.
set returns True, simulating a successful write.
delete returns True, simulating successful deletion.
This allows us to test code that uses Redis
without actually running Redis during the test.
Now the sample_embedding fixture.
This returns a list of 384 zeros.
Our local embedding model outputs 384-dimension vectors.
This fixture gives us a predictable zero vector for tests.
Zero is a safe placeholder because it's unlikely to match any real embedding.
It won't accidentally pass a test that should fail.
Finally, the sample_chunk_text fixture.
This returns realistic financial text about Apple's net sales and services revenue.
Using realistic text is important.
It ensures our chunking and embedding tests work with real-world content,
not just dummy data like the word test repeated.
Let me summarize what each fixture does.
clear_settings_cache resets the settings singleton between tests.
test_env patches environment variables with test values.
mock_db_session provides a fake database session.
mock_cache_client provides a fake Redis client.
sample_embedding gives a zero vector for embedding tests.
sample_chunk_text gives realistic financial text.
With these fixtures in place, writing tests becomes much cleaner.
You simply declare the fixture you need in your test function parameter.
For example, async def test_something, then mock_db_session as db.
Pytest automatically provides the mock from conftest.
Our test fixtures are ready.
Now we can start writing actual tests.
[## [FILE: tests/unit/test_config.py — Unit Tests for Settings, Validators, Computed Fields, and Security]]
Now let's write unit tests for our configuration.
We'll create tests/unit/test_config.py
These tests verify that our Settings class works correctly
before we build any other part of the application.
First, let's understand the structure.
We import os, ClassVar from typing, and patch from unittest.mock.
From pytest, we import ValidationError.
From conftest, we import VALID_SECRETS.
And from our application, we import Settings and get_settings.
First, two fixtures. clear_settings_cache runs automatically before every test.
It clears the lru_cache so environment changes don't leak between tests.
The test_settings fixture creates a valid Settings instance for testing.
It patches os.environ with VALID_SECRETS and sets APP_ENV to testing.
Now let's look at each test class and what it verifies.
TestConfigImport is simple.
It just confirms that get_settings returns a Settings instance.
TestRequiredFields checks that every expected field exists.
We have a list of 17 required fields like APP_ENV, POSTGRES_HOST, and CHUNK_SIZE_TOKENS.
It also verifies that POSTGRES_PASSWORD is a SecretStr.
This ensures passwords are never accidentally exposed in logs.
TestNumericConstraints validates port numbers and chunk settings.
API ports, PostgreSQL ports, and Redis ports must be between 1 and 65535.
These are standard valid port ranges.
It also checks that chunk overlap is less than chunk size.
If overlap equals or exceeds chunk size, chunking would be broken.
TestComputedProperties verifies our derived fields.
DATABASE_URL must start with postgresql+asyncpg.
DATABASE_URL_SYNC must start with postgresql+psycopg2.
We also check that the URL contains the host, database name, and user.
This confirms the URL is built correctly from individual fields.
REDIS_URL must start with redis:// and contain the host and password.
The password is embedded in the URL for authentication.
VECTOR_STORE_DIR in testing must use the /tmp directory.
This prevents tests from polluting real data.
PROJECT_ROOT must exist and contain the src directory.
This test catches errors in the parents index if the file structure changes.
TestSecretSafety ensures secrets never leak.
We verify that the raw password value does NOT appear in repr or str output.
If it did, anyone reading logs would see your password.
But we also verify that get_secret_value still returns the actual password.
This is how our code accesses secrets when connecting to databases.
TestEnvironmentDefaults checks that APP_ENV sets appropriate defaults.
In development mode, DEBUG becomes True automatically.
In testing mode, DEBUG, TESTING, and MOCK_EXTERNAL_APIS all become True.
TestEnvironmentOverrides verifies we can override any setting via environment variables.
For example, setting POSTGRES_HOST changes the database host.
Setting CORS_ORIGINS to a comma-separated string produces a parsed list.
The raw CORS_ORIGINS field stores the string as-is.
The computed CORS_ORIGINS_LIST parses it for FastAPI middleware.
TestProviderValidation checks that API keys are required when needed.
If EMBEDDING_PROVIDER is set to openai but OPENAI_API_KEY is missing,
Settings should raise a ValidationError.
This prevents the app from starting with misconfigured providers.
Better to fail at startup than at runtime when the first embedding request comes in.
Finally, TestProductionHardening guards against dangerous production settings.
If APP_ENV is production and CORS_ORIGINS is an asterisk for wildcard,
Settings raises a ValidationError.
Wildcard CORS in production is a security risk.
It allows any website to make requests to your API.
To run these tests, execute pytest tests/unit/test_config.py with the minus v flag for verbose output.
All tests should pass. If any fail, there's a problem with your Settings class
or your environment configuration.
Our config tests are complete. They verify that settings load correctly,
secrets stay secret, computed fields work, and production guards are enforced.
[## [SECTION: Common Errors and Fixes — Phase 1 Troubleshooting]]
Before we move to Phase 2, let me walk you through the most common errors
you might encounter in Phase 1 and how to fix them.
Consider this your troubleshooting reference.
When something breaks, come back to this section.
Error one. POSTGRES_PASSWORD must be set.
The error message says the variable is required but missing.
The cause is that your .env file is either missing,
in the wrong directory, or does not contain the required password.
The fix. Check your working directory.
Ensure .env exists in the same directory where you run docker compose.
Error two. connection refused on port 5432.
This means your application cannot reach PostgreSQL.
The cause is almost always that Docker is not running,
or the containers have not been started.
The fix is simple. run docker compose up minus d.
Wait for the containers to become healthy.
Error three. ModuleNotFoundError for financial_rag.
Python cannot find your application code.
The cause is that you haven't installed your package in editable mode.
Your code exists on disk, but Python doesn't know where to find it.
The fix. run pip install minus e dot dev in brackets.
This installs your package in development mode.
Error four. asyncio_mode warning from pytest.
Pytest is telling you async tests are not properly configured.
The cause is missing pytest-asyncio configuration.
But in our project, the configuration is already in pyproject.toml.
The fix. reinstall your development dependencies.
Run pip install minus e dot dev in brackets again.
Error five. vector type not found.
PostgreSQL does not recognize the vector data type.
The cause is that the pgvector extension was not created.
This happens if your init script did not run.
The fix. Check that create_schema.sql is in the infrastructure
docker init directory. If missing, Docker cannot create the extension.
You may also need to recreate your containers with docker compose down minus v,
then up minus d to force the init script to run again.
Error six. Configuration errors with CHUNK_OVERLAP.
The error says CHUNK_OVERLAP_TOKENS must be less than CHUNK_SIZE_TOKENS.
The cause is that your .env file has overlap set to a value
that is equal to or greater than the chunk size.
The fix. Reduce CHUNK_OVERLAP_TOKENS below CHUNK_SIZE_TOKENS.
For example, if chunk size is 512, set overlap to 50 or 100.
Let me summarize the most important fixes.
If Docker fails, check your .env file first.
If Python can't find your code, run pip install minus e dot dev.
If PostgreSQL is missing the vector type,
check that your init script is in the correct directory.
And if you see configuration validation errors,
check your .env values against the constraints in settings.py.
Bookmark this section.
When you hit an error, you'll know exactly where to look.