Now let's move to Phase 9. GitOps and zero-trust networking.
This is where our deployment becomes truly enterprise-grade.
Here are the new files we'll create in Phase 9.
argocd/bootstrap/bootstrap.sh
ArgoCD installation and bootstrap script.
argocd/projects/financial-rag-project.yaml
ArgoCD Project with RBAC and sync windows.
argocd/appsets/apps-appset.yaml
ApplicationSet for the App of Apps pattern.
cilium/network-policies/default-deny-all.yaml
Baseline deny-all network policy.
cilium/network-policies/api-l7-policy.yaml
L7 HTTP policy for the API service.
cilium/network-policies/agent-l7-policy.yaml
L7 HTTP policy for the agent service.
istio-mesh/authorization-policies.yaml
Istio authorization policies for mTLS.
istio-mesh/destination-rules.yaml
Istio destination rules for traffic management.
istio-mesh/gateway.yaml
Istio ingress gateway.
istio-mesh/kustomization.yaml
Kustomize configuration for Istio.
cilium/ebpf/cilium-servicemonitor.yaml
Prometheus ServiceMonitor for Cilium.
[## [SECTION: Step 1 — Understand the GitOps Architecture]]
Before we write any files, let me explain the GitOps architecture.
A developer pushes code to GitHub.
ArgoCD detects the diff.
It polls every 3 minutes, or you can configure a webhook.
The diff shows what changed in the Git repo.
The ApplicationSet generates one Application per environment.
Dev, staging, and prod each get their own.
Each environment has a different sync policy.
Dev auto-syncs immediately. Changes apply as soon as they're pushed.
Staging also auto-syncs immediately.
For testing before production.
Production requires manual sync only.
And only allowed during a specific window, 2 AM to 6 AM UTC.
ArgoCD renders Helm templates with environment-specific values.
It then runs kubectl apply using server-side apply.
Finally, it sends a Slack notification.
Sync succeeded or failed.
Why GitOps? Without it, deployments happen via helm upgrade.
From someone's laptop or a CI runner.
The cluster state is not reproducible from Git alone.
If the cluster is destroyed, you don't know exactly what was running.
With ArgoCD, the cluster continuously reconciles toward the Git state.
The Git repository IS the source of truth.
Let me summarize the GitOps flow.
Git push triggers ArgoCD diff.
ApplicationSet creates environment Applications.
Dev auto-syncs, staging auto-syncs, prod manual sync only.
Helm renders templates, kubectl applies, Slack notifies.
The cluster always matches what's in Git.
This is the foundation of production-grade Kubernetes.
[## [SECTION: Step 2 — Install Cilium (Component #101)]]
Now let's install Cilium for eBPF networking.
Cilium must be installed before ArgoCD.
Why before? ArgoCD pods need networking to start.
You need the network to sync the network.
First, add the Cilium Helm repository and update it.
Then install Cilium with specific settings.
The most important setting is kubeProxyReplacement equals true.
This replaces kube-proxy entirely with Cilium's eBPF datapath.
kube-proxy traditionally uses iptables for load balancing.
Every packet goes through a chain of rules in userspace.
Cilium's eBPF datapath runs in the Linux kernel.
It is much faster and more efficient.
We also enable Hubble relay and UI.
Hubble is Cilium's observability layer.
Hubble metrics include DNS, drops, TCP flows, and HTTP.
It captures source and destination namespaces, workloads, and traffic direction.
Hubble UI gives you a graphical view of network flows.
You can see which services are talking to which.
On EKS, we use ipam.mode equals eni.
ENI stands for Elastic Network Interface.
Cilium manages pod IPs directly on the EC2 ENI.
No overlay network, native VPC routing.
The EKS API endpoint is required for kube-proxy replacement.
Cilium needs to know where the Kubernetes API server is.
Our Cilium installation is complete.
Now let's verify it.
[## [SECTION: Step 3 — Verify Cilium (Component #102)]]
Now let's verify that Cilium is working correctly.
First, check that all Cilium agents are running.
kubectl get pods in kube-system with the Cilium label.
All pods should be in Running state.
If any are pending or crash looping, check your installation.
Next, run the connectivity test.
cilium connectivity test.
This deploys test pods and verifies L3, L4, and L7 networking.
It checks if pods can reach each other correctly.
If the test passes, Cilium is working.
If it fails, something is wrong with your configuration.
Use the Hubble CLI to observe live network flows.
hubble observe with dash dash namespace and dash dash follow.
This shows every packet flowing through your cluster.
You can filter by namespace, verdict, or protocol.
Finally, launch the Hubble UI in your browser.
cilium hubble ui.
Our Cilium verification is complete.
Cilium is ready for zero-trust policies.
[## [SECTION: Step 4 — Deny-All Network Policy (Component #104)]]
Now let's apply the baseline deny-all network policy.
This is Component 104.
The policy is called default-deny-all.
It matches all pods in the financial-rag namespace.
Ingress is empty, meaning deny all incoming traffic.
No pod can receive traffic from any source.
Egress has one exception. DNS.
Pods need to resolve service names.
Why allow DNS in the deny-all?
Without DNS, pods cannot resolve service names.
For example, financial-rag-agent-pgvector dot svc dot cluster dot local.
That domain name needs to be resolved.
DNS is the one egress that must be permitted.
Before any other allow rules are applied.
The policy targets kube-dns in the kube-system namespace.
UDP port 53 and TCP port 53.
Apply the policy with kubectl apply dash f.
Then verify with Hubble.
hubble observe with dash dash namespace financial-rag.
And dash dash verdict DROPPED.
You should see dropped traffic.
Everything except DNS is now blocked.
Start with default-deny-all. No traffic flows.
Then add specific allow rules for what you need.
This is zero-trust networking.
Deny everything by default, explicitly permit what's necessary.
DNS is the only exception in the baseline.
Pods cannot function without name resolution.
Our deny-all policy is complete.
Zero-trust networking is now active.
[## [SECTION: Step 5 — L7 HTTP Policies (Components #105–107)]]
Now let's add L7 HTTP policies with Cilium.
Let me explain what L7 enforcement means in practice.
This is critical.
Without L7 policy, if someone sends a DELETE request to your API.
The request reaches your FastAPI application.
FastAPI returns a 405 Method Not Allowed.
But the request still consumed resources. It reached your app.
With L7 policy, that DELETE request is dropped at the kernel level.
It never reaches your application at all.
Even if FastAPI had a bug that incorrectly handled DELETE on the wrong route.
The kernel already dropped the packet. The bug never triggers.
This is defense in depth. The network layer protects your application.
Even if your application code has vulnerabilities.
The API L7 policy allows only specific methods and paths.
From the outside world, the ALB can send GET requests to slash health.
And POST requests to slash query.
From the monitoring namespace, Prometheus can send GET requests to slash metrics.
Everything else is dropped.
No DELETE. No PUT. No docs endpoint in production.
This matches what we did in server.py with docs disabled.
The agent L7 policy allows POST requests to slash infer from the API.
And GET slash health from monitoring.
All other requests to the agent are dropped at the kernel level.
Our L7 policies are complete.
[## [SECTION: Step 6 — Istio Service Mesh]]
Now let's add Istio for service mesh.
Istio works alongside Cilium. They do different things.
Cilium enforces which pods can talk to which pods.
And which HTTP methods and paths are allowed.
Istio encrypts all pod-to-pod traffic with mTLS.
And enforces service identity.
Think of it this way.
Cilium is the bouncer at the door. It checks your ID.
Istio is the encrypted tunnel. No one can eavesdrop on your conversation.
Even if they sneak past the bouncer.
Install Istio using Helm charts.
First, add the repo and create the istio-system namespace.
Install the base CRDs, then the control plane called istiod.
Then enable sidecar injection for the financial-rag namespace.
PeerAuthentication enables strict mTLS.
mTLS stands for mutual Transport Layer Security.
Both sides of the connection present certificates.
The client proves its identity to the server.
The server proves its identity to the client.
No one can impersonate either side.
mode STRICT means reject any plaintext traffic.
All communication must be encrypted.
Istio AuthorizationPolicy works on service identities.
Not on IP addresses or pod labels.
The deny-all policy has an empty spec. That means deny everything.
No traffic is allowed in the namespace.
Then we add specific allow rules.
allow-gateway-to-api allows only the Istio ingress gateway.
The principal is a service account.
cluster.local slash ns slash istio-system slash sa slash istio-ingressgateway.
Only that exact service account can call the API.
No other pod can.
DestinationRules control how traffic flows to a service.
Connection pool limits prevent a single pod from being overwhelmed.
Outlier detection is a circuit breaker.
If a pod starts returning errors, Istio ejects it.
For 30 seconds, no traffic goes to that pod.
Then it's re-evaluated.
Load balancing uses LEAST_REQUEST.
Send traffic to the pod with the fewest active requests.
The Gateway defines TLS termination at the mesh edge.
It listens on port 443 for HTTPS traffic.
Our Istio configuration is complete.
The cluster now has mTLS and service identity.
[## [SECTION: Step 7 — Install ArgoCD (Components #108–110)]]
Now let's install ArgoCD for GitOps.
We'll use a bootstrap script that automates everything.
First, it adds the ArgoCD Helm repository and updates it.
The script requires environment variables.
CLUSTER_NAME, ARGOCD_VERSION, and ENV.
It also requires GITHUB_TOKEN for repository access.
And optional SLACK_TOKEN and PAGERDUTY_PROD_KEY for notifications.
The script creates the argocd namespace.
It disables Istio injection for ArgoCD components.
Then it installs ArgoCD using the Helm chart.
With wait and timeout 10 minutes.
After installation, it retrieves the initial admin password.
The password is stored in a Kubernetes secret.
It starts a port-forward to access the ArgoCD server.
Then logs in with the admin credentials.
The script adds your Git repository to ArgoCD.
It uses the GITHUB_TOKEN for authentication.
This allows ArgoCD to pull manifests directly from Git.
No manual kubectl apply needed.
Next, it applies RBAC configuration.
This controls who can do what in ArgoCD.
The policy.csv file defines roles and permissions.
It's patched into the argocd-rbac-cm ConfigMap.
If SLACK_TOKEN is provided, it creates a secret.
This enables Slack notifications for sync events.
You get notified when a deployment succeeds or fails.
No need to watch the ArgoCD UI constantly.
Finally, it applies three ApplicationSets.
infra-appset, env-appset, and apps-appset.
The App of Apps pattern.
One root ApplicationSet manages all other applications.
Let me explain the bootstrap order.
First, apply infra-appset. This deploys infrastructure components.
Namespace operators, service monitors, and cluster add-ons.
Then env-appset deploys environment-specific configurations.
One Application per environment. Dev, staging, prod.
Finally, apps-appset deploys the application itself.
The API, agent, ingestion CronJob, and databases.
Our ArgoCD installation is complete.
Now let's look at the ArgoCD Project.
[## [SECTION: Step 8 — ArgoCD Project (RBAC + Sync Windows)]]
Now let's create the ArgoCD Project.
Think of an ArgoCD Project like a gated community.
It has rules about who can come in and what they can do.
First, sourceRepos lists where you can get your blueprints from.
Your GitHub repo, and Helm repos like Cilium and Istio.
No one can deploy from outside these sources.
This prevents someone from using a fake, malicious chart.
Next, destinations lists which namespaces you can deploy to.
financial-rag, istio-system, karpenter, monitoring, and others.
You cannot deploy to a random namespace.
Every deployment must go to an approved destination.
clusterResourceWhitelist lists cluster-level resources you can create.
Namespaces, ClusterRoles, CustomResourceDefinitions.
Without this, you couldn't create a namespace.
But you also cannot delete or modify critical cluster resources.
Now syncWindows. This is like a schedule.
It says when you ARE allowed to deploy and when you ARE NOT.
Dev and staging have a 24-hour allow window. They can deploy anytime.
Manual sync is allowed but auto-sync is also enabled.
Production has a 4-hour allow window from 2 AM to 6 AM UTC.
Outside that, from 8 AM to 6 PM on weekdays, deployments are DENIED.
This prevents accidental production changes during business hours.
Even if you hit sync, ArgoCD blocks it.
Now RBAC roles. This controls who can do what.
The platform-engineer role can sync anything in any environment.
They are the only ones who can touch production.
The developer role can only sync dev and staging.
They can look at production but cannot change it.
The ci-bot role is for your CI pipeline.
It has full sync permissions but can't approve manual promotions.
Now the ApplicationSet. This creates one Application per environment.
Dev, staging, and prod.
The rolling sync strategy controls promotion order.
First dev, then staging, then prod.
If dev fails to sync, the pipeline stops.
It won't try staging or prod.
The list generator defines each environment's settings.
Dev uses values.yaml, auto-sync enabled, image tag latest.
Staging uses the same values.yaml. Also auto-sync.
Also image tag latest.
Production uses values.prod.yaml. Auto-sync is false.
Image tag is pinned to 1.0.0, not latest.
The template defines what the Application looks like.
It pulls from your Helm chart.
The sync policy has retries. 5 attempts with exponential backoff.
If it fails, it waits 30 seconds, then 60, then 2 minutes, then 4.
ignoreDifferences tells ArgoCD to ignore certain fields.
Here it ignores spec.replicas in Deployments.
Why? Because the HorizontalPodAutoscaler changes replica counts.
ArgoCD would otherwise try to revert them.
Our ArgoCD Project and ApplicationSet are complete.
Now let's promote to production.
[## [SECTION: Step 9 — Promote to Production]]
First, see what's out of sync.
argocd app diff financial-rag-prod.
This shows the difference between Git and the cluster.
Then sync manually with argocd app sync dash dash prune.
This brings the cluster into alignment with Git.
Wait for the rollout with argocd app wait dash dash health.
This blocks until everything is healthy.
If something goes wrong, roll back with argocd app rollback.
Followed by the revision number.
Rollback to revision 1 reverts to the previous known-good state.
No manual fix needed.
Let me summarize the GitOps promotion flow.
Developer pushes to GitHub. ArgoCD sees the change.
Dev auto-syncs. Staging auto-syncs.
Platform engineer manually syncs production within the allowed window.
If something breaks, roll back to previous revision.
Git is the source of truth.
The cluster always tries to match what's in Git.
[## [SECTION: Step 10 — Cilium ServiceMonitor (Component #118)]]
Now let's add the Cilium ServiceMonitor.
This tells Prometheus to scrape metrics from Cilium.
Cilium and Hubble produce important metrics.
Network flows, dropped packets, DNS requests, and HTTP traffic.
We want these metrics in Prometheus.
So we can see them in Grafana dashboards.
The first ServiceMonitor is for the Cilium agent.
It targets pods with the label app.kubernetes.io/name equals hubble.
It scrapes the hubble-metrics port on path slash metrics.
Every 30 seconds.
It adds a relabeling. It copies the node name into a label called node.
So you can see metrics per Kubernetes node.
The second ServiceMonitor is for the Cilium operator.
It targets pods with the label io.cilium/app equals operator.
It scrapes the prometheus port on path slash metrics.
Also every 30 seconds.
Apply the ServiceMonitor with kubectl apply dash f.
It goes in the monitoring namespace.
After applying, check that metrics are flowing.
You can port-forward to Prometheus and query for cilium_ prefix.
Or check the targets page in the Prometheus UI.
The Cilium targets should be UP.
Our Cilium ServiceMonitor is complete.
Cilium metrics are now scraped by Prometheus.
[## [SECTION: Phase 9 Verification]]
Now let's verify everything works.
First, check that all Cilium agents are healthy.
kubectl get pods in kube-system with the Cilium label.
All pods should be Running.
No crash loops, no pending.
Run the Cilium connectivity test.
cilium connectivity test with dash dash test-namespace financial-rag.
This deploys test pods and verifies L3, L4, and L7 policies.
Everything should pass.
Next, check ArgoCD.
argocd app list.
Dev and staging should be Synced.
Production may be OutOfSync until you manually approve.
Now check Hubble for unexpected drops.
hubble observe with dash dash namespace financial-rag.
Add dash dash verdict DROPPED and dash dash last 100.
You should see very few dropped packets.
DNS is allowed. Health checks are allowed.
Everything else should be either allowed or correctly blocked.
Finally, verify Istio mTLS.
istioctl x describe service financial-rag-agent-api.financial-rag.
This shows the service details.
It should confirm that STRICT mTLS is enabled.
Let me summarize Phase 9.
We installed Cilium with eBPF networking.
kubeProxyReplacement true replaced kube-proxy.
We applied a default-deny-all network policy.
Only DNS was allowed out.
Then we added L7 HTTP policies.
Only specific methods and paths are allowed to the API.
We installed Istio for service mesh.
PeerAuthentication with STRICT mTLS encrypts all traffic.
AuthorizationPolicy denies everything by default.
Then allows specific service accounts.
DestinationRules control connection pools and circuit breakers.
Outlier detection ejects failing pods.
We installed ArgoCD for GitOps.
The bootstrap script automated the entire setup.
The AppProject defines which repos, namespaces, and resources are allowed.
SyncWindows block production deployments during business hours.
The ApplicationSet creates one Application per environment.
Dev and staging auto-sync. Production requires manual approval.
We added Cilium ServiceMonitors for Prometheus.
Now we have full network observability.
Phase 9 is complete.
The Financial RAG Agent now runs on a zero-trust, GitOps-managed Kubernetes cluster.
This is production-grade infrastructure.
Every change is reviewed, approved, and audited through Git.
---
**End of Phase 9. Phase 10 covers Falco Runtime Security. Shall I continue?**