Now let's move to Phase 10. Falco runtime security and threat detection.
This is the final security layer.
Before installing anything, understand what Falco detects and why it matters.
For a financial RAG agent specifically.
Your application runs LLM inference, reads sensitive financial data from SEC filings.
And holds database credentials in Vault-injected files.
The realistic attack scenarios are.
Attacker gets RCE via prompt injection, spawns a shell.
Falco detects shell spawned in financial RAG pod.
Malware reads slash vault slash secrets slash database.env.
Falco detects Vault secret read by unexpected process.
Compromised agent pod connects to attacker's command and control server.
Falco detects unexpected outbound connection.
Attacker uses kubectl exec to enter a pod.
Falco detects kubectl exec in financial RAG namespace.
Cryptojacking. attacker runs mining software.
Falco detects crypto mining in financial RAG.
Container escape. writes to read-only filesystem.
Falco detects write outside allowed paths.
Privilege escalation via setuid binary.
Falco detects privilege escalation in financial RAG pod.
Credential harvesting via proc star star environ.
Falco detects read process environment.
Falco detects these at the syscall layer.
Below the application, below the container runtime.
Even if the attacker has full control of the Python process.
Falco sees the underlying open, connect, and execve syscalls.
[## [SECTION: Step 12 — Install Falco (Component #121)]]
Now let's install Falco using Helm.
Add the FalcoSecurity repo, create the falco namespace.
Falco runs in kube-system, not the falco namespace.
Why kube-system? Falco runs as a DaemonSet that must access the host's eBPF subsystem.
Running it in kube-system ensures it starts early and has the required privileges.
Install with eBPF driver and Falcosidekick.
The Helm chart creates its own service account with minimum permissions.
Now verify Falco is running.
Check Falco pods are running on all nodes.
kubectl get pods in kube-system with the Falco label.
Check eBPF probe loaded.
kubectl exec and look for falco directory in the BPF filesystem.
List loaded rules.
kubectl exec with falco minus l and grep for financial-rag.
Our Falco installation is complete.
Now let's add custom rules.
[## [SECTION: Step 13 — Custom Rules (Components #125–131)]]
Now let's create our custom Falco rules.
We'll put them in falco/rules/financial_rag_rules.yaml
Every Falco rule has five parts.
Rule name, description, condition, output, priority, and MITRE tags.
The condition is a boolean expression using Falco fields.
It looks for specific system calls and matches them to labels.
First, define macros for reusable conditions.
financial_rag_namespace condition checks namespace equals financial-rag.
api_container condition checks namespace and component label equals api.
agent_container condition checks namespace and component label equals agent.
ingestion_container condition checks namespace and component label equals ingestion.
vault_agent_container condition checks container name equals vault-agent.
istio_proxy_container condition checks container name equals istio-proxy.
allowed_containers combines vault-agent, istio-proxy, api, agent, and ingestion.
Rule one. Shell spawned in financial-rag pod.
This should never happen in production.
The condition checks for a spawned process, in the financial-rag namespace.
And the process name matches a shell like bash or sh.
It excludes the vault-agent and istio-proxy containers.
They have legitimate reasons to spawn subprocesses.
Priority is CRITICAL. If a shell appears, page someone immediately.
Rule two. Unexpected outbound connection from agent pod.
The condition checks for outbound traffic from the agent container.
And the destination port is NOT in the allowed list.
Allowed ports are 5432 for PostgreSQL, 6379 for Redis.
443 for HTTPS, and 15001 and 15006 for Istio.
This catches Cilium policy bypass attempts.
Even if an attacker bypasses the network policy, Falco still alerts.
Rule three. Write to filesystem outside allowed paths.
All containers have readOnlyRootFilesystem set to true.
Only slash tmp and slash vault slash secrets should be writable.
If a process writes anywhere else, something is wrong.
This catches container escape attempts.
Rule four. Vault secret read by unexpected process.
This is critical for your security model.
The condition checks for a process reading from slash vault slash secrets.
And the process name is NOT python3, uvicorn, gunicorn, or vault.
If a shell reads database.env, Falco fires immediately.
Rule five. Privilege escalation attempt.
Executing a setuid or setgid binary inside a financial-rag pod.
Rule six. Crypto mining detection.
Known miner process names like xmrig or ethminer.
Rule seven. kubectl exec into a financial-rag pod.
Priority is WARNING, not CRITICAL. Exec is allowed, but must be logged.
Rule eight. Read process environment.
Someone reading slash proc slash star slash environ, harvesting credentials.
Our custom rules are complete.
Eight rules covering the financial RAG threat model.
[## [SECTION: Step 14 — Deploy Rules as ConfigMap (Component #132)]]
Now deploy these rules as a ConfigMap.
Create the ConfigMap from the rules file.
kubectl create configmap from-file.
The Helm values mount this ConfigMap into Falco's rules directory.
To update rules without restarting, send SIGHUP to the Falco process.
Update the ConfigMap and then send kill dash 1 to the Falco process.
This reloads rules without restarting the daemon.
Our rules ConfigMap is complete.
Falco now has custom rules for financial-rag.
[## [SECTION: Step 15 — Test Rules (Component #134)]]
Now let's test each rule in a non-production namespace.
Test one. Shell spawn detection.
Create a test pod with the api component label.
kubectl run test-shell with image alpine.
Labels app.kubernetes.io/component equals api.
Then exec into the pod and run bin slash sh.
kubectl exec test-shell dash dash bin slash sh dash c echo test.
Check Falco logs for Shell Spawned in Financial RAG Pod.
Expected priority CRITICAL.
Test two. Vault secret read.
kubectl exec test-shell dash dash cat slash vault slash secrets slash database.env.
Expected alert. Vault Secret Read by Unexpected Process with priority CRITICAL.
Test three. Outbound connection to unexpected port.
kubectl exec test-shell dash dash wget to example.com on port 8080.
Expected alert. Unexpected Outbound Connection with priority HIGH.
Clean up the test pod.
kubectl delete pod test-shell.
Our rules are tested and working.
Falco detects all critical attack patterns.
[## [SECTION: Step 16 — Falcosidekick (Components #136–138)]]
Now let's configure Falcosidekick.
Falcosidekick routes Falco alerts to external destinations.
Three destinations configured.
Slack for warnings and above.
The webhook URL is injected via set at install time.
The message format includes the rule name, priority, and pod name.
PagerDuty for CRITICAL only, wakes someone up.
CloudWatch for all events, SOC2 audit trail.
The log group is slash aws slash falco slash financial-rag.
Two replicas with pod anti-affinity ensures alert delivery.
Even if one node fails, the other continues.
Install Falcosidekick with Helm upgrade.
Use the falco-helm-values.yaml and falcosidekick-values.yaml.
Set falcosidekick.config.slack.webhookurl and pagerduty routingkey.
Verify Falcosidekick is receiving events.
Port-forward to the UI and open localhost 2802.
Our Falcosidekick configuration is complete.
Alerts now route to Slack, PagerDuty, and CloudWatch.
[## [SECTION: Step 17 — Prometheus Integration (Components #144–146)]]
Now let's integrate Falco with Prometheus.
Falco exposes metrics at slash metrics.
The Helm values enable the ServiceMonitor automatically.
Three Prometheus security alerts.
Alert one. FalcoCriticalEventDetected.
expr sums the rate of falco_events_total with priority Critical.
for 0m means fire immediately with zero stabilization period.
Security events at CRITICAL priority require immediate response.
Alert two. CiliumDropRateHigh.
expr sums the rate of hubble_drop_total in the financial-rag namespace.
If drop rate exceeds 10 per second for 2 minutes, fire alert.
Possible lateral movement attempt.
Alert three. VaultTokenRenewalFailure.
expr sums the rate of financial_rag_vault_token_renewal_errors_total.
If token renewal fails for 1 minute, secrets will expire.
Fire alert.
Apply the Prometheus alerts.
kubectl apply with the financial-rag-alerts.yaml file.
Our Prometheus integration is complete.
Falco metrics are now alertable.
[## [SECTION: Step 18 — Gitleaks Standalone Workflow]]
Now let's look at the standalone gitleaks workflow.
It runs separately from the main CI pipeline.
Place it at .github/workflows/gitleaks.yml.
Two important features beyond the basic gitleaks check.
First, weekly full-history scan.
The scheduled run uses fetch-depth zero, full history.
This catches secrets buried in old commits.
Not just the latest 50. Secrets that were deleted six months ago but are still in the git object store.
Second, PR comment on detection.
When a secret is found in a PR, a comment is posted.
With exact remediation steps.
Rotate the credential, use git-filter-repo to remove from history.
Developers get actionable instructions in the PR.
Not just a failed check.
Third, Slack alert.
The security channel gets notified immediately.
Not just the developer who pushed.
The security team sees every detection even if the developer dismisses the PR check.
Our gitleaks standalone workflow is complete.
Secret scanning is now comprehensive.
[## [SECTION: Final File Tree — Phases 9 & 10]]
Let me show you the complete file tree for Phases 9 and 10.
Phase 9 files.
argocd/bootstrap/bootstrap.sh
argocd/projects/financial-rag-project.yaml
argocd/appsets/apps-appset.yaml
argocd/appsets/env-appset.yaml
cilium/network-policies/default-deny-all.yaml
cilium/network-policies/api-l7-policy.yaml
cilium/network-policies/agent-l7-policy.yaml
cilium/ebpf/cilium-servicemonitor.yaml
istio-mesh/authorization-policies.yaml
istio-mesh/destination-rules.yaml
istio-mesh/gateway.yaml
istio-mesh/kustomization.yaml
Phase 10 files.
falco/config/falco.yaml
falco/config/falco-helm-values.yaml
falco/config/falco-financial-rag-configmap.yaml
falco/rules/financial_rag_rules.yaml
falco/sidekick/falcosidekick-values.yaml
observability/prometheus-rules/financial-rag-alerts.yaml
.github/workflows/gitleaks.yml
All these files work together.
GitOps, zero-trust networking, and runtime security are now complete.
[## [SECTION: Common Errors and Fixes — Phases 9 & 10]]
Let me walk through common errors in Phases 9 and 10.
And how to fix them.
Error one. cilium connectivity test fails.
The cause is kube-proxy still running.
The fix is to delete the kube-proxy DaemonSet.
kubectl delete ds kube-proxy in kube-system.
Error two. ArgoCD pods stuck Pending.
Cilium not ready when ArgoCD installs.
Apply default-deny-all.yaml after ArgoCD is running.
Not before.
Error three. OutOfSync never resolves.
Ignored differences not set.
Add HPA slash spec slash replicas to ignoreDifferences in ApplicationSet.
This prevents ArgoCD from fighting with the HPA.
Error four. Falco permission denied on eBPF.
EKS managed node missing BPF capability.
Use driver.kind module on older EKS AMIs.
Or upgrade to AL2023 which supports eBPF.
Error five. Rules not loading.
ConfigMap not mounted.
Check extraVolumeMounts path matches rules_file in falco.yaml.
The mount path must be slash etc slash falco slash rules.d.
Error six. Falcosidekick not routing to Slack.
Webhook URL not set.
Use dash set falcosidekick.config.slack.webhookurl equals dollar SLACK_WEBHOOK.
The URL must be valid.
Error seven. L7 policy blocks health check.
Path mismatch.
Verify slash health is in api-l7-policy.yaml ingress rules.
The health endpoint must be explicitly allowed.
Error eight. ArgoCD sync window blocks prod.
Correct behavior.
Use argocd app sync dash dash force only during allowed window.
Otherwise the sync is denied.
Error nine. istioctl shows plaintext traffic.
PeerAuthentication not applied.
Check peer-auth-strict-mtls.yaml is applied in financial-rag namespace.
The policy must be present.
Error ten. Gitleaks false positive.
Test passwords in YAML.
Add pattern to allowlist in dot gitleaks.toml.
The test passwords should be excluded.
Bookmark this section.
When you hit an error, you'll know exactly where to look.
[## [SECTION: What's Next — Phase 11]]
Now let me preview Phase 11.
In Phase 11, we build end-to-end observability.
Logs, metrics, traces, and alerts all connected.
You'll learn OpenTelemetry auto-instrumentation.
For FastAPI, SQLAlchemy, Redis, and httpx.
Custom RAG spans for embedding, search, and LLM calls.
You'll see exactly where time is spent.
Tail sampling. 100 percent of error traces, 100 percent of slow traces.
Only 1 percent of successful, fast traces.
OpenTelemetry Collector with Jaeger for development and AWS X-Ray for production.
Trace ID injection into structured logs.
SLO recording rules and multi-window multi-burn-rate alerting.
Three SLOs. API availability 99.5 percent, query latency P99 under 120 seconds, ingestion success 99 percent.
Grafana dashboards for RAG performance, error budgets, and LLM cost.
ArgoCD notifications via Slack and PagerDuty.
OPA Rego policies for Helm manifests and Terraform plans.
Policies run in CI before deployment.
The file tree for Phase 11 will include.
src/financial_rag/telemetry/tracing.py
observability/tracing/tracer_config.py
observability/tracing/tracer-provider.yaml
observability/slo/slo-rules.yaml
observability/slo/slo-alerts.yaml
policies/rego/helm_policy.rego
policies/rego/k8s_admission.rego
policies/rego/terraform_policy.rego
Phase 10 is complete.
Your cluster now has runtime threat detection at the kernel level.
Falco detects shell spawns, vault secret reads, outbound connections, and crypto mining.
Alerts go to Slack, PagerDuty, and CloudWatch.
In Phase 11, we add full observability.
Logs, metrics, traces, and alerts all connected.
Ready to proceed to Phase 11?
---
**End of Phase 10. Phase 11 covers LGTM Observability and OPA Rego Policies. Shall I continue?**