Now let's move to Phase 2. The ingestion pipeline.
This is how we get data into our system.
But before we write the ingestor, we need to define our exception hierarchy.
A proper exception hierarchy is one of the first signs of professional Python code.
Why do we need custom exceptions?
Because catching a generic Exception tells you nothing about what went wrong.
Was the database down? Did EDGAR rate limit us? Could we not parse the HTML?
Each of these requires a different recovery strategy.
With custom exceptions, you can catch exactly what you need.
And let everything else bubble up to a higher level.
Every exception in our application will inherit from a single base class.
We'll call it FinRAGError.
This allows us to catch any application-specific error with one except block if needed.
But we can still differentiate between different error types.
We never raise a bare Exception anywhere in our codebase.
Always use our own exception types.
Let's create the hierarchy.
At the root is FinRAGError.
Below it, we have five main categories.
StorageError for database and cache issues.
IngestionError for document ingestion problems.
ProcessingError for chunking and transformation errors.
RetrievalError for embedding and vector search errors.
And ConfigurationError for fatal misconfigurations.
Each of these will have more specific subclasses.
DatabaseConnectionError, DatabaseQueryError, CacheConnectionError, CacheOperationError.
SECFetchError, DocumentParseError, DuplicateFilingError.
ChunkingError, EmbeddingError, VectorSearchError.
Let me show you the complete exception hierarchy.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/utils/exceptions.py
[## [FILE: src/financial_rag/utils/exceptions.py ]]
Now let's create our exception hierarchy.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/utils/exceptions.py
First, let's look at the base FinRAGError class.
It takes a message and an optional cause.
The cause is the original exception that triggered this one.
This preserves the full stack trace.
The string representation includes the cause if present.
This makes debugging much easier.
Now let's implement StorageError.
This is our base for all storage-layer errors.
DatabaseConnectionError is raised when we cannot connect to PostgreSQL.
This happens at startup if the database is unreachable.
DatabaseQueryError wraps SQLAlchemy or asyncpg exceptions
that occur during query execution.
CacheConnectionError and CacheOperationError do the same for Redis.
Connection for connectivity issues, Operation for read or write failures.
RecordNotFoundError is special.
It takes an entity name and an identifier.
For example, if we look up a filing by ID that doesn't exist,
we raise RecordNotFoundError with entity filing and the ID.
This is analogous to HTTP 404 at the storage layer.
It tells you exactly what was missing.
Now IngestionError. This is our base for document ingestion errors.
SECFetchError is raised when the EDGAR API cannot be reached,
or returns an error like a rate limit violation.
DocumentParseError is raised when a document cannot be parsed.
This could be a corrupted PDF or invalid HTML.
DuplicateFilingError is raised when we try to ingest a filing
that already exists in the database.
It takes a ticker symbol and a file hash.
The error message tells you exactly which filing was duplicated.
ProcessingError is our base for document processing errors.
ChunkingError is raised when document chunking fails.
For example, if a document cannot be tokenised or split
within our configured constraints.
RetrievalError is our base for retrieval-layer errors.
EmbeddingError is raised when the embedding API returns an error or times out.
This includes OpenAI rate-limit errors.
VectorSearchError is raised when a pgvector similarity search fails.
Finally, ConfigurationError.
This is raised when the application detects a fatal misconfiguration
that wasn't caught at settings validation time.
Now let me explain why this hierarchy matters.
First, it makes error handling precise.
You can catch exactly what you need and ignore what you don't.
For example, in a web endpoint, you might catch SECFetchError
and return a 503 Service Unavailable response.
But you would not want to catch ConfigurationError the same way.
That should crash the application immediately.
Second, the cause parameter preserves the original error.
When we wrap an exception, we don't lose the stack trace.
Third, consistent exception types make logging and monitoring easier.
You can track how many DatabaseConnectionError events occur each day.
Our exception hierarchy is complete.
Every error in the application now has a clear home.
Now let's update the utils package __init__.py to export all these exceptions.
[## [FILE: src/financial_rag/storage/repositories/base.py — Generic Async Repository Base]]
Before we create specific repositories for filings and chunks,
we need a base repository that all other repositories inherit from.
The repository pattern abstracts database operations.
It gives us a clean interface for working with our data models.
Instead of writing raw SQLAlchemy queries everywhere,
we encapsulate them inside repository classes.
Let me explain the key design decisions.
First, repositories borrow sessions. They do not own transactions.
The service layer decides when to commit or roll back.
This is important. If a repository committed after every operation,
you couldn't group multiple operations into one transaction.
Second, every database operation wraps exceptions in DatabaseQueryError.
This gives us consistent error handling across all repositories.
Third, methods like add and add_many flush but do not commit.
Flush sends the SQL to the database. Commit makes it permanent.
The caller controls the transaction boundary.
This is critical for idempotent ingestion.
Let's create the base repository.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/storage/repositories/base.py
[## [FILE: src/financial_rag/storage/repositories/base.py]]
First, imports. We need logging, Generic and TypeVar from typing, and UUID.
From SQLAlchemy, we import func and select.
From sqlalchemy.ext.asyncio, we import AsyncSession.
From our utils, we import DatabaseQueryError and RecordNotFoundError.
Now define our type variable.
ModelT is a TypeVar that represents any SQLAlchemy ORM model.
This makes BaseRepository a generic class.
When we subclass it, we specify the concrete model type.
For example, FilingsRepository would be BaseRepository with Filing as the model.
The class declaration uses Generic with ModelT.
This tells Python that the class works with a type parameter.
The docstring explains the key contract.
Subclasses must declare a model_class attribute.
And all methods receive an AsyncSession injected from the caller.
Repositories do NOT own sessions. They borrow them.
The __init__ method stores the session.
Every repository instance is tied to one database session.
Now let's look at the create methods.
The add method takes an ORM instance and adds it to the session.
It flushes to send the SQL to the database but does NOT commit.
After flushing, we refresh the instance.
This loads any database-generated values like auto-incrementing IDs.
The add_many method does the same thing for a list of instances.
It uses add_all which is more efficient than calling add in a loop.
If the list is empty, we return early to avoid unnecessary work.
Now the read methods.
get_by_id fetches a single record by its primary key.
It uses the session.get method which is optimized for primary key lookups.
If the instance is None, meaning no record exists,
we raise RecordNotFoundError with the model name and ID.
get_by_id_or_none does the same thing but returns None instead of raising.
This is useful for optional lookups.
list_all returns all records with pagination.
We use limit and offset to control how many records are returned.
The docstring has a warning.
Do not use this on large tables without filters.
Concrete repositories should add WHERE clauses.
The count method returns the total number of records.
It uses SQLAlchemy's func.count to generate a COUNT query.
Now the update method.
This takes an instance and keyword arguments for the fields to update.
We iterate through each field, check if the instance has the attribute,
and then set the new value.
After updating, we flush and refresh the instance.
Refresh reloads the instance from the database with the new values.
If a field name doesn't exist, we raise DatabaseQueryError
with a helpful message.
Finally, the delete methods.
The delete method performs a hard delete.
It removes the record from the database completely.
The soft_delete method performs a soft delete.
It sets is_active to False instead of deleting the record.
Soft delete is useful when you want to keep historical data.
The record still exists in the database but is filtered out of most queries.
Note that soft_delete requires the model to have an is_active column.
It calls the update method we just defined.
Let me summarize the key principles.
First, repositories borrow sessions. They do not own transactions.
The service layer decides when to commit or roll back.
Second, every database operation wraps exceptions in DatabaseQueryError.
This gives us a consistent error type across all repositories.
Third, methods like add and add_many flush but do not commit.
This allows the caller to group multiple operations into one transaction.
Our base repository is complete.
Concrete repositories will inherit from this and add domain-specific queries.
[## [FILE: src/financial_rag/storage/repositories/filings.py — Filings Repository with Deduplication]]
Now let's create our first concrete repository for the filings table.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/storage/repositories/filings.py
This repository handles all database operations for SEC filings.
It inherits from our BaseRepository.
First, let's understand the imports.
We need logging, date from datetime, and UUID.
From SQLAlchemy, we import Boolean, Date, Integer, SmallInteger, String, and select.
From sqlalchemy.orm, we import Mapped and mapped_column.
From our application, we import Base from storage.database,
BaseRepository from repositories.base, and DatabaseQueryError from utils.
Now let's define our ORM model class called Filing.
This maps Python code to the filings table in PostgreSQL.
The __tablename__ is set to filings, matching our schema.
Each field corresponds to a column in the database.
We have id as UUID primary key.
Ticker as string with length 10, marked as nullable False and indexed.
Filing type is also a string.
Fiscal year uses SmallInteger, fiscal quarter uses SmallInteger with a check constraint.
Filed at is a date. Source URL is a string.
File hash is a string with length 64 and marked as unique.
Pages is an integer. Ingested by is a string for tracking who performed the ingestion.
And is_active is a boolean, defaulting to True.
We also define a __repr__ method.
This gives us readable output when we print a Filing object.
It shows the id, ticker, filing type, and fiscal year.
This is helpful for debugging.
Now let's create the FilingsRepository class.
It inherits from BaseRepository with Filing as the model type.
We set model_class equal to Filing.
This tells the base repository which ORM model to use.
Now the deduplication methods. These are critical for ingestion.
get_by_hash looks up a filing by its SHA-256 content hash.
This is how we check if a filing has already been ingested.
We use where Filing.file_hash equals the provided hash.
If found, we return the filing. If not, we return None.
exists_by_hash is a convenience method.
It returns True if a filing with this hash exists, False otherwise.
This is faster than get_by_hash when you don't need the actual record.
It simply checks existence without loading the data.
Now the filtered queries.
get_by_ticker returns all filings for a given ticker symbol.
We convert the ticker to uppercase for consistency.
We order by fiscal year descending so the newest filings come first.
The active_only parameter filters out soft-deleted records.
Limit defaults to 50 to prevent returning too many records.
You can override it for specific use cases.
get_by_ticker_and_type adds a filing type filter.
For example, get all 10-K filings for Apple.
We can also filter by a specific fiscal year.
If fiscal_year is provided, we add that to the WHERE clause.
get_latest returns the most recent active filing for a ticker and type.
We order by fiscal year descending and limit to one row.
This is used to determine whether re-ingestion is needed.
If the latest filing is already ingested, we can skip it.
Finally, list_tickers returns all distinct tickers that have been ingested.
We use SQLAlchemy's distinct function.
We filter for active filings only and order by ticker alphabetically.
The result is a simple list of strings.
Notice that every database operation wraps exceptions in DatabaseQueryError.
This gives us consistent error handling across the entire repository layer.
Let me summarize the key methods.
For deduplication, we have get_by_hash and exists_by_hash.
These prevent re-ingesting the same filing twice.
For filtered queries, we have get_by_ticker, get_by_ticker_and_type,
and get_latest for the most recent filing.
And list_tickers gives us a complete inventory of companies we've ingested.
Our filings repository is complete.
Now the SEC ingestor can use it for deduplication.
[## [FILE: src/financial_rag/storage/repositories/__init__.py — Utils Package Exports]]
Now let's update the storage repoitories package __init__.py file.
This file gives us a clean import surface for all our exceptions.
Instead of importing from multiple nested paths, we can
import everything directly from financial_rag.storage.repositories.base
and do same for Filing, FilingsRepository
We import all base types from the base module.
we do the same for the filing and filings repository.
Then we expose them in __all__.
This explicitly declares what is part of our public API.
This is now complete, Good
[## [SECTION: SEC EDGAR Ingestor — Understanding the Problem]]
Now let's build our SEC EDGAR ingestor.
This is the heart of Phase 2. It downloads SEC filings directly from the government's EDGAR system.
But before we write code, let me explain the challenges we need to solve.
Three big ones.
Challenge one. Rate limiting.
EDGAR enforces a hard limit of 10 requests per second per IP address.
If you exceed this, they return HTTP 429 and may block your IP.
A naive implementation that fires all requests at once would get throttled immediately.
We need a rate limiter that spaces requests evenly.
Exactly one request every 100 milliseconds.
Challenge two. Deduplication.
The same filing might be downloaded multiple times.
If your ingestion job runs daily, you'll re-download the same 10-K over and over.
We need a way to detect if a filing has already been ingested.
SHA-256 hashing of the content gives us a unique fingerprint.
Even if the filing is re-filed with a different date, the content hash changes.
We can detect duplicates reliably.
Challenge three. Transient errors.
The EDGAR API occasionally returns 5xx errors or times out.
We need automatic retries with exponential backoff.
If a request fails, wait 2 seconds, try again. Wait 4 seconds, try again. Wait 8 seconds, then give up.
Let me show you how we solve all three challenges.
We'll build a token bucket rate limiter using asyncio Semaphore.
We'll use tenacity for retries with exponential backoff.
And we'll compute SHA-256 hashes for deduplication.
We'll also cache raw HTML to disk.
So if your ingestion job fails halfway, you don't re-download everything.
Let's create the file.
src/financial_rag/ingestion/sec_ingestor.py
[## [FILE: src/financial_rag/ingestion/sec_ingestor.py — Async SEC EDGAR Client with Rate Limiting, Retries, and Deduplication]]
First, imports. We need asyncio, hashlib, logging, and datetime.
From typing, we import TYPE_CHECKING for conditional imports.
We use httpx for async HTTP requests.
And tenacity for retries with exponential backoff.
From our application, we import get_settings
and SECFetchError from exceptions.
Now define the EDGAR base URLs and supported filing types.
We only support 10-K, 10-Q, 8-K, 20-F, DEF 14A, and S-1.
Component one. The rate limiter.
EDGAR enforces 10 requests per second per IP address.
Our token bucket rate limiter uses an asyncio semaphore.
It allows at most RPS concurrent requests.
Then it sleeps for the interval between releases.
For 10 requests per second, that's 100 milliseconds.
When you enter the rate limiter using async with, it acquires the semaphore.
When you exit, it sleeps and then releases.
The result is exactly 10 requests per second, evenly spaced.
Never burst, never throttled.
Now the FilingMetadata class.
This is a lightweight value object returned by list_filings.
It uses __slots__ for memory efficiency.
Each instance stores ticker, filing type, fiscal year and quarter,
filed date, accession number, and source URL.
The __repr__ method gives us a readable string for debugging.
We pass this metadata to download_filing to fetch the actual content.
Now the SECIngestor class itself.
This is the main entry point for all EDGAR operations.
In __init__, we load settings, create the rate limiter,
and initialize the HTTP client as None.
We use async context managers for proper cleanup.
__aenter__ creates the httpx client with our User-Agent header.
EDGAR requires a descriptive User-Agent identifying your application.
Without this, your requests may be blocked.
__aexit__ closes the client and releases resources.
Now the public API methods.
Method one. list_filings.
This returns metadata for the most recent N years of filings.
First, we validate the filing type is supported.
If not, we raise SECFetchError with helpful message.
We resolve the ticker to a CIK number.
CIK stands for Central Index Key, EDGAR's unique identifier for companies.
Then we fetch the submissions JSON and parse it.
The result is a list of FilingMetadata objects, newest first.
Method two. download_filing.
This downloads the primary document for a filing.
First, we check if a cached version exists in raw_dir.
If yes, we return the cached content and its hash.
If not, we fetch the document from the source URL.
We compute the SHA-256 hash of the content.
A SHA-256 hash is a 64-character fingerprint.
If the content changes by even one character, the hash changes completely.
We then cache the content if raw_dir was provided.
And return the content and hash as a tuple.
Method three. check_duplicate.
This is a utility that checks if a filing already exists in our database.
We get the database client, create a session,
and use the FilingsRepository to check by hash.
Now the internal EDGAR API calls.
Each one is decorated with tenacity's retry.
Let me explain the retry decorator carefully.
retry_if_exception_type means only retry on SECFetchError.
stop_after_attempt of 3 means maximum 3 total attempts.
wait_exponential means wait 2 seconds, then 4, then 8.
reraise True means after exhaustion, re-raise the original error.
Any other exception type bypasses the retry entirely.
_resolve_cik fetches the company_tickers.json file from EDGAR.
This maps ticker symbols to CIK numbers.
We iterate through the entries looking for a matching ticker.
If found, we return the CIK padded to 10 digits.
If not found, we raise SECFetchError.
_fetch_submissions fetches the full submissions JSON for a CIK.
_fetch_document downloads the raw content of a filing.
We set the Host header to www.sec.gov explicitly.
Notice that every HTTP call is wrapped with the rate limiter.
async with self._rate_limiter ensures we never exceed 10 requests per second.
Now _parse_submissions.
This extracts the relevant filings from the JSON response.
We look at the recent filings array.
We filter to the requested filing type and collect up to years many results.
We skip duplicates by tracking seen fiscal years.
We construct the source URL by combining the CIK, accession number, and primary document.
Finally, cache helpers for raw filing storage.
_cache_path builds a path like ticker slash filing type slash FYyear.html.
_check_cache reads from disk if the file exists.
_write_cache writes the content to disk, creating parent directories as needed.
Let me summarize the flow for ingesting a filing.
First, call list_filings to get metadata.
This resolves the ticker to a CIK and parses the submissions.
Second, call download_filing with the metadata.
This fetches the raw HTML and returns the content plus SHA-256 hash.
Third, check if the hash already exists in the database.
If it does, skip to avoid duplicates.
If not, proceed to parsing, chunking, embedding, and storage.
All with automatic retries and rate limiting.
Our SEC ingestor is complete.
It respects EDGAR's limits, handles failures gracefully, and prevents duplicates.
[## [SECTION: HTML Parser — Cleaning Messy SEC Filings]]
Now that we can download SEC filings, we need to parse them.
SEC filings are messy documents. Very messy.
They contain SGML headers before the HTML starts.
XBRL inline tags for machine-readable data.
Exhibit sections that are just boilerplate.
And inconsistent heading formats for sections.
Our job is to strip all of that away.
We want clean, section-tagged text ready for chunking.
Let me explain the strategy.
Step one. Strip the SGML header.
SEC filings begin with SGML metadata before the first HTML tag.
We search for the first HTML tag and discard everything before it.
Step two. Remove noise tags.
Script tags, style tags, meta tags, SVG tags.
XBRL inline tags like ix:nonfraction and ix:nonumeric.
These contain no human-readable text.
We remove them entirely from the document tree.
Step three. Extract clean text.
We use BeautifulSoup's get_text with newline separators.
Then we normalize whitespace. Collapse runs of spaces into single spaces.
Collapse excessive blank lines to at most two in a row.
Step four. Remove boilerplate patterns.
Page numbers like dash space 42 space dash. Table of contents markers.
EDGAR header fields. Long separator lines of equals signs or dashes.
These add no value to the content.
Step five. Detect sections.
We split the text into lines and look for heading patterns.
Regular expressions match phrases like "management discussion and analysis".
Or "risk factors". Or "financial statements".
When we find a heading, we group all lines until the next heading.
That becomes a section.
Sections shorter than 200 characters are discarded as false positives.
If no sections are found, we return the full text as a "General" section.
Let's implement this.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/ingestion/parsers/html_parser.py
[## [FILE: src/financial_rag/ingestion/parsers/html_parser.py — HTML Parser for SEC Filings with Section Detection]]
First, imports. We need logging, re for regular expressions, and dataclasses.
From bs4, we import BeautifulSoup and Tag.
From our application, we import DocumentParseError from exceptions.
Now define our section detection patterns.
This is a list of regular expression patterns mapped to canonical section names.
For example, patterns matching "management discussion and analysis"
map to the canonical name "MD&A".
Order matters. First match wins.
We have patterns for Risk Factors, Market Risk, Business, Financial Statements,
Balance Sheet, Income Statement, Cash Flow, and more.
Next, define tags that never contain useful text.
Script, style, meta, link, head, noscript, SVG, and image tags.
We also discard XBRL inline tags like ix:nonfraction and ix:nonumeric.
These are machine-readable tags, not human text.
Now the ParsedSection dataclass.
This represents a single identified section from a filing.
It has a name, the section text, and a computed character count.
The __repr__ method gives us readable output for debugging.
Next, the ParsedFiling dataclass.
This is the complete result of parsing a filing.
It contains ticker, filing type, fiscal year,
the full cleaned text, and a list of sections.
The get_section method lets you retrieve a specific section by name.
If not found, it returns None.
Now the main HTMLParser class.
This is where the parsing logic lives.
The parse method is the public entry point.
It takes raw HTML, ticker, filing type, and optional fiscal year.
It returns a ParsedFiling object with all extracted content.
Inside parse, we perform five steps.
Let me walk through each one.
Step one. strip the SGML header.
SEC filings begin with SGML metadata before the HTML starts.
We search for the first HTML tag.
Everything before that is discarded.
Step two. parse with BeautifulSoup using the lxml parser.
Step three. remove noise tags entirely.
The _remove_noise_tags method finds every tag in our discard list
and calls decompose to remove them from the tree.
Then it removes any tag that has no visible text content.
Empty tags just add noise.
Step four. extract clean text.
We use soup.get_text with a newline separator to preserve line structure.
Then we normalize whitespace.
Collapse runs of spaces, but preserve newlines.
We collapse excessive blank lines to at most two in a row.
This keeps the text readable without giant gaps.
Then we run boilerplate removal.
We strip out page numbers, table of contents markers, and EDGAR header fields.
We also remove long separator lines of equals signs or dashes.
These add no value to the content.
Step five. detect sections.
This is where we identify the major sections within the filing.
We split the text into lines.
Then we look for lines that match our section heading patterns.
Section headings are typically short — less than 200 characters.
If a line is too long, it's probably not a heading.
When we find a heading, we record its line index and section name.
We build a list of heading positions.
If no sections are detected at all,
we return the full text under a "General" section.
If we have headings, we iterate through them.
For each heading, we take all lines from its position to the next heading.
We skip duplicate section names.
We also skip sections shorter than 200 characters as false positives.
The result is a list of ParsedSection objects.
Each contains a section name and its cleaned text.
Let me summarize what the parser does from start to finish.
Input. raw SEC filing HTML with SGML headers and XBRL tags.
Output. a ParsedFiling with full clean text and per-section breakdown.
We strip the SGML header, parse with BeautifulSoup,
remove noise tags, extract and clean the text.
Then we detect sections using regex patterns.
Sections shorter than 200 characters are discarded as false positives.
The result is structured text ready for chunking and embedding.
Our HTML parser is complete.
[## [SECTION: Text Parser — Cleaning and Normalizing Financial Text]]
Now we have clean HTML text, but it still needs more processing.
The text parser runs after the HTML parser and before chunking.
What problems does it solve?
First, Unicode normalization.
SEC filings contain all sorts of special characters.
Ligatures like the fi character that looks like one symbol but is actually two letters.
Accented characters, non-breaking spaces, em dashes.
We normalize everything to a standard form called NFKC.
Second, removing noise.
URLs, email addresses, control characters that aren't visible.
Four or more consecutive newlines.
Third, normalizing financial number formatting.
Dollar signs and commas fragment tokenization.
For example, the string "1,234" becomes two tokens. "1" and "234".
After normalization, "1234" is a single token.
Fourth, extracting financial metrics.
We use regex patterns to find revenue figures, net income, earnings per share.
"Revenue of X billion" becomes a key-value pair.
revenue equals the numeric value scaled to full dollars.
These metrics get stored in the JSONB column of financial_chunks.
This allows fast filtering and aggregation without re-parsing the text.
Let me show you the implementation.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/ingestion/parsers/text_parser.py
[## [FILE: src/financial_rag/ingestion/parsers/text_parser.py — Text Cleaner and Financial Metric Extractor]]
First, imports. We need logging, re for regular expressions,
and unicodedata for Unicode normalisation.
From our application, we import DocumentParseError from exceptions.
Now define noise patterns.
These are regular expressions that match content we want to remove.
We remove URLs starting with http or https.
We remove email addresses, control characters, and four or more consecutive newlines.
Next, number normalisation patterns.
These preserve the semantic meaning while cleaning formatting.
We remove dollar signs before numbers.
So dollar sign 1 comma 234 becomes just 1234.
We remove commas in numbers.
So 1 comma 234 comma 567 becomes 1234567.
And we normalise percentages.
12.5 space percent becomes 12.5 percent with no space.
Now the TextParser class.
It has three public methods. clean, normalise_numbers, and extract_metrics.
Let's start with the clean method.
This is the full cleaning pipeline.
Step one. Unicode normalisation using NFKC.
NFKC converts ligatures and normalises accented characters.
For example, the ligature character for "fi" becomes two separate letters.
And an accented e becomes a plain e.
Step two. remove noise patterns.
We loop through each pattern and replace matches with a space.
Step three. normalise whitespace within lines.
We collapse runs of spaces and tabs into a single space.
Step four. collapse excessive blank lines.
We allow at most two consecutive blank lines.
Then we join the lines back together and strip the result.
This gives us clean, readable text.
Now the normalise_numbers method.
This applies our number normalisation patterns to the text.
It removes dollar signs and commas from numbers.
And fixes spacing around percentage signs.
This is important for chunking.
If we leave dollar signs and commas, they fragment tokenisation.
For example, "1,234" becomes two tokens. "1" and "234".
After normalisation, "1234" is a single token.
Now the extract_metrics method.
This extracts numerical financial metrics using regex patterns.
It returns a dictionary of metric names to numeric values.
This will be stored in the metrics JSONB column of the financial_chunks table.
First, we define a helper called _safe_float.
It removes commas from a string and attempts to convert to float.
If conversion fails, it returns None.
This prevents exceptions from malformed numbers.
Now revenue extraction.
We look for patterns like revenue of X billion or total revenue of X million.
When we find a match, we extract the number and the scale.
Then we pass both to _apply_scale to get the full value.
Next, net income extraction.
Similar pattern but looking for net income, net earnings, or net loss.
EPS extraction for earnings per share.
We look for EPS or earnings per diluted share followed by a dollar figure.
And margin extraction for operating, gross, or net margin.
We look for a number followed by a percent sign.
Finally, the _apply_scale helper.
It converts a scaled value to its full numeric form.
If the scale is billion, multiply by 1 billion.
If million, multiply by 1 million. If thousand, multiply by 1 thousand.
If no scale is provided, return the value unchanged.
Let me summarize the text parser's role in the pipeline.
The HTML parser gives us raw cleaned text.
But that text still has URLs, emails, and messy number formatting.
The text parser cleans all of that.
It normalises Unicode, strips noise, and standardises number formats.
It also extracts key financial metrics.
Revenue, net income, EPS, and margins go into a dictionary.
This dictionary will be stored in the metrics JSONB column.
That column is indexed with GIN for efficient querying.
The cleaned text then goes to the chunking processor.
The metrics go to the database alongside the embeddings.
Our text parser is complete.
Text is now clean, normalised, and enriched with metrics.
[
## [FILE: tests/integration/test_phase2_ingestion.py — Integration Test for Ingestion Pipeline]]
Now let's write the actual integration test file.
We'll put it in tests/integration/test_phase2_ingestion.py
First, imports. We need pytest, pathlib, and uuid.
From our application, we import SECIngestor, HTMLParser, and TextParser.
We also import get_settings to get the raw data directory.
And we import the database client for deduplication.
We mark the whole module with pytestmark to skip in regular test runs.
integration = pytest.mark.integration
Now define the async test function.
test_ingest_aapl_10k
First, create a temporary directory for raw files.
Using the settings RAW_DATA_DIR.
Use SECIngestor as an async context manager.
inside the with block, call list_filings.
ticker equals AAPL, filing_type equals 10-K, years equals 1.
This gives us the most recent 10-K metadata.
Assert that at least one filing was found.
If none found, the test fails.
Take the first filing metadata.
Call download_filing with the raw_dir.
This returns raw_html and file_hash.
Print the file hash for debugging.
Now create an HTMLParser instance.
Call parse with the raw HTML, ticker, filing type, and fiscal year.
Assert that the parsed filing has sections.
Print the number of sections and each section name.
Create a TextParser instance.
Take the first section from the parsed filing.
Clean the section text using text_parser.clean.
Assert that the cleaned text is not empty.
Extract metrics from the cleaned text using extract_metrics.
Assert that metrics is a dictionary.
Print the metrics for inspection.
This might include revenue, net income, or EPS.
The test passes if all assertions succeed.
No exceptions were raised during download or parsing.
Run the test with the integration flag.
pytest tests/integration/test_phase2_ingestion.py -v -m integration
Expected output will show the file hash.
The number of sections detected, and the extracted metrics.
If the test fails, check your internet connection.
EDGAR may be blocking your requests.
You may need to set a valid User-Agent in settings.
EDGAR requires a descriptive User-Agent with a contact email.
Our integration test is complete.
Phase 2 is now fully verified.
**End of Phase 2. I have Phases 3 through 12 ready. Shall I continue with Phase 3?**