Now let's move to Phase 5. API, monitoring, and metrics.
This is where we expose our RAG system as a web service.
Here are the new files we'll create in Phase 5.
src/financial_rag/monitoring/metrics.py
Prometheus metrics for query latency, error rates, and ingestion.
src/financial_rag/monitoring/__init__.py
Exports the metric recording functions.
src/financial_rag/api/models.py
Pydantic request and response models for FastAPI.
src/financial_rag/api/dependencies.py
Dependency injection for database, cache, and query engine.
src/financial_rag/api/middleware.py
Request logging, API key auth, and rate limiting.
src/financial_rag/api/routes.py
All HTTP endpoints. health, query, ingest, stats, metrics.
src/financial_rag/api/server.py
FastAPI application factory with lifespan and middleware.
tests/unit/test_api.py
Unit tests for API endpoints with mocked dependencies.
tests/integration/test_phase5_api.py
Integration tests for the running API server.
[## [SECTION: Step 8 — Prometheus Metrics (Components #46–48)]]
Now let's build our Prometheus metrics module.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/monitoring/metrics.py
Prometheus is an open-source monitoring system.
It collects time-series metrics from your application.
These metrics tell you how your system is performing.
How many queries per minute, how fast they are, and how many errors occur.
First, imports. From prometheus_client, we import four metric types.
CONTENT_TYPE_LATEST for HTTP headers, Counter, Gauge, and Histogram.
We also import generate_latest to produce the metrics output.
Now let's define our metrics.
First, QUERY_TOTAL. This is a Counter, which only goes up.
Counters are for monotonically increasing counts.
Total queries, total errors, total requests.
QUERY_TOTAL has four labels. Analysis style, search type, agent type, and status.
Labels allow you to slice the data by different dimensions.
Next, QUERY_LATENCY. This is a Histogram.
Histograms measure the distribution of values.
We define buckets for latency. Point one seconds, point two five, point five, one, two point five, five, ten, and thirty seconds.
QUERY_ERRORS is another Counter. It has a single label for error type.
This helps you see which errors are most common.
Now Gauges. Gauges measure values that go up and down.
Unlike Counters which only increase.
CHUNKS_TOTAL measures the number of chunks in the vector store.
It has a ticker label to track per-company counts.
FILINGS_TOTAL measures the number of filings ingested.
With labels for ticker and filing type.
INGESTION_TOTAL is a Counter for ingestion jobs.
With labels for ticker, filing type, and status.
INGESTION_LATENCY is a Histogram for ingestion duration.
With longer buckets because ingestion takes more time than queries.
Finally, cache metrics. CACHE_HITS and CACHE_MISSES are Counters.
These tell you how effective your Redis cache is.
Now the helper functions.
record_query records metrics for a completed query.
It increments the query total counter with the appropriate labels.
It observes the latency in the histogram.
If the query failed, it also increments the error counter.
With the specific error type.
record_ingestion does the same for ingestion jobs.
Increments the ingestion counter and observes latency.
update_store_stats updates the gauge metrics.
Chunks total and filings total.
These are gauges because they can go up or down.
As you delete filings or add new ones.
Let me explain label cardinality. This is critical for production.
Each unique combination of labels creates a new time series.
With three analysis styles, three search types, two agent types, and two statuses.
That's three times three times two times two equals thirty-six series.
That's fine.
But if you added a ticker label to QUERY_TOTAL, that would be dangerous.
If you queried ten thousand different tickers, you'd have ten thousand times thirty-six.
That's three hundred sixty thousand time series.
Prometheus does not handle that well.
That's why CHUNKS_TOTAL uses ticker as a label.
The number of tickers you ingest is bounded, maybe a few thousand.
But QUERY_TOTAL does not use ticker.
Because queries could come for any ticker, unbounded.
Now let's create the monitoring package __init__.py.
Open src/financial_rag/monitoring/__init__.py.
We import get_metrics_output, record_ingestion,
record_query, and update_store_stats.
Then we expose all four in __all__.
Now anywhere in the application, you can import.
from financial_rag.monitoring import record_query, get_metrics_output
Let me summarize the metric types and their use cases.
Counters are for things that only increase.
Total queries, total errors, total cache hits.
Gauges are for things that go up and down.
Number of chunks in the store, number of active connections.
Histograms are for distributions.
Query latency, ingestion duration.
The metrics module is complete.
Prometheus can now scrape your application for monitoring.
[## [SECTION: Step 9 — API Models (api/models.py)]]
Now let's build our API models.
We'll put them in src/financial_rag/api/models.py
These are Pydantic request and response models for the FastAPI layer.
They define the shape of data going in and out of the API.
First, let's understand the two patterns worth highlighting.
StrEnum for API enumerations, and required fields with ellipsis.
First, imports. From enum, we import StrEnum.
From typing, we import Any.
From pydantic, we import BaseModel and Field.
Now define our enums using StrEnum.
First, AnalysisStyle with three values. Analyst, executive, and risk.
Second, SearchType with three values.
Similarity, MMR, and hybrid.
Let me explain why we use StrEnum instead of regular Enum.
With StrEnum, the enum value IS the string.
You don't need to use dot value in comparisons.
And it serialises to the plain string in JSON automatically.
This makes API responses cleaner.
Now the QueryRequest model.
This is the request body for the query endpoint.
Question is a required string field.
Notice the ellipsis as the first argument to Field.
The ellipsis means the field is required with no default.
Pydantic raises a validation error immediately if the request omits it.
Ticker, filing type, and fiscal year are optional.
Analysis style defaults to analyst, search type defaults to similarity.
Limit is optional but must be between 1 and 20 if provided.
Now DocumentResponse.
This represents a single source chunk returned with a query response.
It contains chunk ID, content, ticker, filing type,
fiscal year, section, similarity score, and extracted metrics.
QueryResponse is the complete response from the query endpoint.
It includes the original question, the answer, analysis style, and search type.
Agent type tells you whether the response came from the agent or query engine.
Latency in seconds, source documents, and any error.
Now the ingestion models.
IngestionRequest is the request body for the ingest endpoint.
It requires a ticker symbol.
Filing type defaults to 10-K, years defaults to 2 with a maximum of 5.
IngestionResponse returns the results.
Ticker, filing type, filings found, chunks stored, success flag, skipped duplicates, and any error.
Now the health models.
ServiceStatus represents the status of a single backing service.
It has a boolean healthy flag and a details dictionary.
Details can contain version numbers, connection pool stats, or error messages.
HealthResponse is the complete health check response.
It has an overall status string, version, and a services dictionary.
Services can include database, cache, and embeddings.
Each with its own ServiceStatus.
Finally, StatsResponse.
This is for the statistics endpoint.
It contains ticker if filtered, total chunks, total filings,
embedding provider name, and embedding dimensions.
Let me summarize the key patterns.
First, StrEnum gives you string-based enums without dot value.
This is cleaner for API serialization.
Second, Field with ellipsis makes fields required.
Pydantic validates this automatically before your handler runs.
Third, optional fields use None as default.
This gives the API flexibility while keeping the contract clear.
Our API models are complete.
The FastAPI routes can now use these for request validation and response formatting.
[## [SECTION: Step 10 — Dependency Injection (api/dependencies.py)]]
Now let's build our FastAPI dependencies.
We'll put them in src/financial_rag/api/dependencies.py
These are dependency injection functions used across route handlers.
All expensive objects are instantiated once at startup and reused.
Dependency injection in FastAPI is a pattern where you declare what your route needs.
FastAPI automatically provides it from the dependency tree.
First, imports. We need logging, and Annotated from typing.
From fastapi, we import Depends.
From our application, we import QueryEngine, CacheClient,
get_cache_client, DatabaseClient, get_db_client, and VectorStore.
Now we define module-level singletons.
_query_engine and _vector_store start as None.
The get_vector_store function returns the singleton.
If it doesn't exist, it creates a new VectorStore instance.
The get_query_engine function does the same for QueryEngine.
It first gets the vector store, then creates the engine.
Why singletons? VectorStore and QueryEngine are expensive to create.
They load models, create embedding clients, and set up connections.
Creating them once per request would be very slow.
So we create them once at startup and reuse them for every request.
Now the FastAPI dependency functions.
These are used with Depends in route handlers.
db_client yields the database client.
It simply calls get_db_client and returns it.
cache_client yields the cache client.
Same pattern.
query_engine yields the query engine singleton.
vector_store yields the vector store singleton.
Now Annotated type aliases.
These make route signatures cleaner.
DBClient is Annotated of DatabaseClient with Depends db_client.
CacheClient_ is Annotated of CacheClient with Depends cache_client.
Engine is Annotated of QueryEngine with Depends query_engine.
Store is Annotated of VectorStore with Depends vector_store.
Now a route signature can look like this.
async def query, then db colon DBClient.
FastAPI automatically provides the database client.
No need to call get_db_client in every route.
Now the startup and shutdown helpers.
These are called from the FastAPI lifespan context manager.
initialise_dependencies runs once when the server starts.
First, we get the database client and call connect.
Then we verify pgvector is installed.
If the extension is missing, we fail fast at startup.
Next, we get the cache client and call connect.
Then we pre-warm the singletons.
Calling get_vector_store and get_query_engine creates them now.
This makes the first request faster.
shutdown_dependencies runs when the server shuts down.
It disconnects the database and cache clients gracefully.
This ensures no connections are left hanging.
And all resources are properly cleaned up.
Let me summarize the dependency injection flow.
At startup, initialise_dependencies creates all connections.
It also creates the query engine and vector store singletons.
During each request, the route handler declares its dependencies.
FastAPI calls the dependency functions and provides the instances.
At shutdown, shutdown_dependencies closes everything gracefully.
No resources are leaked.
Our dependencies module is complete.
FastAPI routes can now use these for clean, testable code.
[## [SECTION: Step 11 — Middleware (Components #42–45)]]
Now let's build our API middleware.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/api/middleware.py
Middleware sits between the incoming request and your route handler.
It can modify requests, log information, enforce authentication, or rate limit.
We have three middleware components.
Request logging, API key authentication, and rate limiting.
First, imports. We need logging, time, uuid, and FastAPI components.
From slowapi, we import Limiter, the rate limit exceeded handler, and get_remote_address.
From starlette middleware, we import BaseHTTPMiddleware.
And from our application, we import get_settings.
First, create the rate limiter singleton.
It uses the client's IP address as the key, with a default limit of 100 requests per minute.
The configure_limiter function attaches the limiter to the FastAPI app.
In development, it uses in-memory storage.
In production with Redis available, it uses Redis as the backend.
This ensures rate limits are shared across multiple API replicas.
Let me explain rate limiting in more detail.
Rate limiting prevents a single client from overwhelming your API.
100 requests per minute is a sensible default.
You can override this per route with a different limit.
For example, you might allow only 10 queries per minute for the expensive endpoint.
Now the RequestLoggingMiddleware.
This logs every request coming into the API.
It generates a unique request ID as a UUID.
This ID is stored in request.state so other middleware and handlers can access it.
We log the start of the request with method, path, and client IP.
Then we measure the processing time.
After the response is generated, we add two headers.
X-Request-ID so clients can trace their request through logs.
And X-Process-Time with the duration in milliseconds.
Then we log the completion with status code and duration.
This structured logging is critical for debugging.
You can grep your logs for a single request ID and see exactly what happened.
Now the APIKeyMiddleware.
This provides optional API key authentication.
It has an exempt paths set. Health, docs, redoc, and openapi.json are always allowed.
Load balancer health probes would fail without this.
If API_KEY_ENABLED is False, the middleware does nothing.
If it's True, it checks the X-API-Key header.
If the key matches the expected value from settings, the request continues.
If not, it returns a 401 Unauthorized response.
Notice the response uses RFC 7807 format.
Type, title, status, detail, and instance fields.
This is the standard error format for production APIs.
Clients can handle errors programmatically rather than parsing error strings.
Now the exception handlers.
register_exception_handlers attaches handlers to the FastAPI app.
The unhandled exception handler catches any unexpected error.
It logs the error with the request ID, then returns a 500 response.
This prevents raw Python exceptions from reaching the client.
Which could leak sensitive information.
The value error handler catches validation errors.
It returns a 422 Unprocessable Entity response.
Both handlers use the same RFC 7807 format.
This gives clients a consistent error structure.
Let me summarize the middleware order.
Middleware order matters. FastAPI applies middleware in reverse registration order.
The first registered runs last.
Typically you want authentication to run first, then logging, then rate limiting.
Check your server.py registration to ensure the intended order.
Let me also highlight the request ID pattern.
Every request gets a unique UUID injected into request.state.
All log lines in the lifecycle can include this ID.
This enables end-to-end tracing across your logs.
You can trace a request from the moment it enters the API to the final response.
Our middleware module is complete.
The API now has logging, authentication, rate limiting, and structured error responses.
[## [SECTION: Step 12 — Fix routes.py (Duplicate Write Bug)]]
Now let's fix the routes.py file.
There was a duplicate write bug in the original implementation.
When you added the analysis history recording, you may have left a second block.
Remove the duplicate and keep only one call to repo.record.
Let's build the complete routes.py.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/api/routes.py
This file contains all the HTTP endpoints for the application.
Health check, query, ingestion, stats, and metrics.
First, imports. We need logging, time, and UUID.
From fastapi, we import APIRouter, BackgroundTasks, HTTPException, and status.
From our application, we import dependencies, models, and all the core components.
HTMLParser, TextParser, TextProcessor, SECIngestor, VectorStore, and more.
Create the router instance.
router = APIRouter
First, the health endpoint at GET slash health.
This returns the status of all backing services.
We check the database by calling health_check.
If it succeeds, we mark it healthy and include details like PostgreSQL version.
We check the cache by calling health_check on Redis.
If it succeeds, we mark it healthy with Redis version and memory usage.
Then we determine the overall status.
Unhealthy if database is down, degraded if only cache is down, healthy if both are up.
Now the query endpoint at POST slash query.
This is the main RAG endpoint for financial questions.
We call engine.query with all the parameters from the request.
Analysis style and search type come from the enum values.
After getting the result, we write to the audit trail.
We create an AnalysisRepository and call record.
This stores the question, answer, latency, and source chunks.
If this fails, we log a warning but do not fail the request.
We also record Prometheus metrics.
Total queries, latency, and success or failure.
If the result has an error and no answer, we raise an HTTP exception.
Otherwise, we return the QueryResponse.
Now the ingestion endpoint at POST slash ingest slash sec.
This triggers background ingestion of SEC filings.
We use FastAPI's BackgroundTasks to run ingestion in the background.
The endpoint returns immediately with a 202 Accepted status.
This is important because ingestion can take a long time.
Minutes for multiple years of filings.
The background task downloads filings, parses HTML, chunks text, creates embeddings, and stores everything.
The _ingest_background function does the actual work.
First, we create the HTML parser, text parser, and text processor.
We use SECIngestor to list and download filings.
We save raw HTML to disk in case we need to re-process later.
For each filing, we parse the HTML, clean the text, and create chunks.
Then we call store.ingest to embed and store everything.
If a filing is a duplicate, we catch DuplicateFilingError and skip it.
We log progress and any errors.
Now the stats endpoint at GET slash stats.
This returns global vector store statistics.
Total chunks, total filings, embedding provider, and dimensions.
We also have a per-ticker version at GET slash stats slash ticker.
Finally, the metrics endpoint at GET slash metrics.
This returns Prometheus metrics in text format.
This endpoint is not included in the OpenAPI schema.
It's for Prometheus to scrape automatically.
Let me summarize the key patterns in these routes.
First, background tasks for long-running operations.
Ingestion returns immediately and runs in the background.
Second, audit trail recording is non-fatal.
If the database is up but writing to analysis_history fails, we log and continue.
Third, health checks for all dependencies.
The health endpoint lets load balancers know if the service is ready.
Fourth, Prometheus metrics for monitoring.
Every query is tracked with labels for style, search type, and agent.
Our API routes are complete.
The application now has a full REST API for financial RAG queries.
[## [SECTION: Step 13 — Application Server (Component #40)]]
Now let's build the FastAPI application server.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/api/server.py
This is the entry point for the API.
It wires together all the components into a runnable application.
The server handles startup and shutdown, CORS, middleware, exception handlers, and routes.
First, imports. We need logging and contextlib.asynccontextmanager.
From typing, we import TYPE_CHECKING and AsyncGenerator.
We import uvicorn as the ASGI server.
From fastapi, we import FastAPI and CORSMiddleware.
From our application, we import dependencies, middleware, routes, and get_settings.
Now the lifespan context manager.
This is the modern FastAPI pattern for startup and shutdown.
It replaces the deprecated on_event startup and shutdown decorators.
Everything before the yield runs at startup.
At startup, we log the application name, version, and environment.
Then we call initialise_dependencies.
This connects the database, verifies pgvector, connects Redis, and pre-warms the singletons.
If any of this fails, the app fails to start. Fail fast.
The yield keyword is the boundary.
After yield, the application runs.
At shutdown, we log and call shutdown_dependencies.
This disconnects database and Redis gracefully.
Now the create_app factory function.
This builds and configures the FastAPI application.
We load settings and create the FastAPI instance.
Title, description, version, and OpenAPI URLs.
Notice that docs_url, redoc_url, and openapi_url are only enabled when DEBUG is True.
In production with APP_ENV production, DEBUG is False.
This disables Swagger UI, ReDoc, and the OpenAPI schema in production.
Prevents attackers from enumerating your API surface.
We attach the lifespan to the app.
Now the startup and shutdown logic will run automatically.
Now we configure middleware.
First, CORS middleware with allowed origins from settings.
CORS stands for Cross-Origin Resource Sharing.
It controls which web domains can call your API.
We add RequestLoggingMiddleware for request tracing.
We register exception handlers for consistent error responses.
We configure rate limiting with configure_limiter.
In production, this uses Redis as a shared backend.
Finally, we add APIKeyMiddleware for optional authentication.
And we include the router with all the endpoints.
We add a root endpoint at slash.
It returns the service name, version, and docs URL if enabled.
Then we create the module-level app instance.
This is what uvicorn imports and runs.
Finally, the dev entrypoint.
This runs uvicorn with reload enabled when DEBUG is True.
In production, you would run uvicorn directly.
Without the reload flag for better performance.
Let me summarize the middleware order.
Middleware order matters. FastAPI applies middleware in reverse registration order.
The first registered runs last.
Our order is. CORS first, then request logging, then rate limiting, then API key auth.
This means auth runs first on each request.
Let me also highlight the lifespan pattern.
The yield keyword is the key. Everything before yield is startup.
Everything after yield is shutdown.
If startup fails, the app never starts.
This is correct behavior. Fail fast, don't run with missing dependencies.
And docs are disabled in production.
Your OpenAPI schema is an attack surface. Disable it when not needed.
Our application server is complete.
The entire system is now ready to run.
[## [SECTION: Step 14 — Start the API Server]]
Now that we've built everything, let's start the API server.
This is the moment of truth.
We'll use uvicorn to run the FastAPI application.
Uvicorn is an ASGI server built for high-performance async Python.
From the project root, run this command.
uvicorn financial_rag.api.server:app with the reload flag and port 8000.
The reload flag automatically restarts the server when code changes.
This is great for development.
Let me explain what you should see in the startup output.
First, the application logs its name, version, and environment.
Starting financial rag agent version 0.1.0 in development.
Then the database client connects and verifies pgvector is installed.
Cache client connects to Redis.
QueryEngine and VectorStore are initialised.
This pre-warms the singletons so the first request is fast.
Finally, the application announces it's ready.
Listening on 0.0.0.0 port 8000.
Now let's test the health endpoint.
This is the first check to ensure everything is working.
Run curl to localhost:8000 slash health.
Pipe it to python minus m json.tool for pretty printing.
The response should show status healthy.
And both database and cache services should be healthy.
If database is healthy, you'll see PostgreSQL version and pool stats.
If cache is healthy, you'll see Redis version and memory usage.
If either is down, the overall status will be degraded or unhealthy.
This is what your load balancer checks.
Now let's test a query.
This requires that you've already ingested some data.
We post to the query endpoint with a question about Apple's revenue segments.
We set ticker to AAPL, analysis style to analyst, and search type to hybrid.
The response will include the answer, source documents, and latency.
Notice the question uses escaped single quotes for valid JSON.
Now let's test ingestion.
We post to the ingest slash sec endpoint.
The request body includes ticker AAPL, filing type 10-K, and years 2.
The response returns 202 Accepted immediately.
Ingestion runs in the background.
This could take several minutes depending on your network and the number of filings.
To check ingestion progress, look at the stats endpoint.
Get to stats slash AAPL.
This returns total chunks and total filings for Apple.
You'll also see which embedding provider is being used.
Finally, the metrics endpoint.
This returns Prometheus metrics in text format.
You'll see counters for total queries, query latency histograms, and gauge values for chunks.
Prometheus scrapes this endpoint automatically.
Let me summarize the test flow.
First, start the server with uvicorn.
Verify startup logs show all green.
Second, test health. Should return healthy.
Third, test ingestion. Returns 202 immediately.
Fourth, check stats to see ingestion progress.
Fifth, test query once data is ingested.
Sixth, check metrics for monitoring.
The system is now fully operational.
[## [SECTION: Step 15 — Phase 5 Verification Test]]
Now let's write unit tests for our API endpoints.
We'll put them in tests/unit/test_api.py
These tests use httpx AsyncClient with mocked dependencies.
No database, Redis, or LLM calls are made.
We test that the endpoints respond correctly.
And that request validation works as expected.
First, we set up our testing environment.
VALID_SECRETS provides the required passwords.
The _testing_env fixture patches environment variables.
And clears the settings cache for each test.
Now we create mock fixtures for external dependencies.
mock_db simulates the database client with health_check.
mock_cache simulates the Redis client with health_check.
mock_query_engine simulates the query engine returning a QueryResult.
mock_vector_store simulates the vector store with stats.
The test_client fixture creates an AsyncClient against the FastAPI app.
It patches all dependencies to use our mocks.
This creates a completely isolated test environment.
The app runs in memory without any external services.
Now the endpoint tests.
First, TestRootEndpoint verifies the root endpoint.
It should return 200 OK.
And the response should contain service name and version.
Now TestHealthEndpoint.
This verifies the health check endpoint.
It should return 200 OK.
The response should have status, version, and services fields.
Each service should have a healthy boolean flag.
Database and cache services must both be present.
Now TestQueryEndpoint.
This is the most important set of tests.
We verify that a valid query returns 200 OK.
And the response contains answer, source documents, and latency.
We test that missing question returns a 422 validation error.
And invalid analysis style also returns 422.
We test that all three analysis styles are accepted.
Analyst, executive, and risk should all work.
And all three search types are accepted.
Similarity, MMR, and hybrid.
Now TestIngestEndpoint.
Ingestion returns 202 Accepted immediately.
We mock the background task to avoid actual ingestion.
The response should include the ticker.
Missing ticker returns a 422 validation error.
Years out of range, greater than 5, also returns 422.
Finally, TestStatsEndpoint.
Global stats returns 200 with total chunks, total filings, provider, and dimensions.
Ticker stats returns 200 for a specific ticker.
The response should include the ticker field.
Let me summarize the test strategy.
We test each endpoint in isolation using mocked dependencies.
This ensures the tests are fast and reliable.
We test success cases with valid inputs.
And failure cases with missing or invalid inputs.
We test that all enum values are accepted.
Analysis styles and search types.
Our API unit tests are complete.
They will catch regressions as the API evolves.
[## [SECTION: Common Errors and Fixes — Phases 4 & 5]]
Let me walk through common errors in Phases 4 and 5.
And how to fix them.
Error one. AttributeError saying repo.create.
The cause is a duplicate write block still in routes.py.
When you added the analysis history recording, you may have left a second block.
Remove the duplicate and keep only one call to repo.record.
Error two. RuntimeError saying pgvector not found at startup.
The pgvector extension is missing from your database.
The fix is to run CREATE EXTENSION IF NOT EXISTS vector in psql.
Connect to your database and run that command.
Error three. connect already called.
This means initialise_dependencies is calling connect twice.
The cause is both your lifespan and something else calling connect.
Check your dependencies file and make sure connect is called only once.
Error four. RateLimitExceeded in tests.
SlowAPI is counting test requests and hitting the rate limit.
The fix is to use TestClient from FastAPI.
TestClient bypasses real rate limiting in the test environment.
Error five. 401 Unauthorized on the health endpoint.
Your load balancer or test can't reach /health.
The cause is that health path is not in the exempt paths list.
APIKeyMiddleware.EXEMPT_PATHS must include slash health.
Error six. LLM_BASE_URL mismatch.
You have Groq URL set but you're using an OpenAI API key.
Groq API keys start with gsk underscore.
OpenAI API keys start with sk dash project or sk dash.
Match your key type to your base URL.
If using Groq, use a Groq key. If using OpenAI, use an OpenAI key.
Error seven. max_tool_calls hit immediately on the first request.
The agent is calling tools but not getting results.
The cause is that your LLM model does not support function calling.
Not all models support tools.
For OpenAI, use gpt-3.5-turbo or newer.
For Groq, use llama3 or newer.
Error eight. CORS error in your browser.
Your frontend cannot call the API because of cross-origin restrictions.
The cause is that your frontend origin is not in CORS_ORIGINS.
CORS_ORIGINS controls which web domains can call your API.
The fix is to add your frontend URL to CORS_ORIGINS in .env.
For example, comma-separated list of allowed domains.
[## [SECTION: End-to-End Smoke Test]]
Now let's run an end-to-end smoke test.
This verifies that the entire system works together.
First, start the server.
uvicorn financial_rag.api.server:app --reload --port 8000
Second, check health.
curl http://localhost:8000/health | python -m json.tool
Expected output shows status healthy.
Database and cache both healthy.
Third, ingest some data.
curl -X POST http://localhost:8000/ingest/sec \
-H "Content-Type: application/json" \
-d ''
Expected output shows 202 Accepted.
Ingestion runs in the background.
Fourth, wait a few minutes for ingestion to complete.
Then check stats.
curl http://localhost:8000/stats/AAPL | python -m json.tool
Expected output shows total_chunks greater than zero.
Fifth, run a query.
curl -X POST http://localhost:8000/query \
-H "Content-Type: application/json" \
-d '' \
| python -m json.tool
Expected output shows an answer, source documents, and latency.
Sixth, check metrics.
curl http://localhost:8000/metrics
Expected output shows Prometheus metrics.
QUERY_TOTAL, QUERY_LATENCY, and more.
If all six steps pass, your system is fully operational.
The API, query engine, agent, and monitoring all work.
[## [SECTION: What's Next — Phase 6]]
Now let me preview Phase 6.
In Phase 6, we implement zero-trust secrets management with HashiCorp Vault.
This is how production systems handle secrets safely.
You will learn how Vault solves three production problems.
Static credentials, shared credentials, and environment variable exposure.
We'll install Vault on Kubernetes and bootstrap it.
With database secrets engine, PKI engine, and Kubernetes auth.
We'll create three Vault policies.
One for API, one for agent, and one for ingestion.
Each gets different database credentials with different privileges.
Least privilege per workload.
We'll configure the Vault Agent sidecar.
It injects secrets as files, never in environment variables.
And we'll build a Python Vault client that reads those files.
With fallbacks for development.
The file tree for Phase 6 will include.
infrastructure/vault/vault-bootstrap.sh.
infrastructure/vault/policies/api-policy.hcl.
infrastructure/vault/policies/agent-policy.hcl.
infrastructure/vault/policies/ingestion-policy.hcl.
infrastructure/vault/vault-agent-config.hcl.
infrastructure/k8s/service-accounts.yaml.
src/financial_rag/security/vault.py.
Phase 5 is complete.
Your API is now live with full monitoring and metrics.
In Phase 6, we secure all the secrets.
Database passwords, API keys, and certificates.
Ready to proceed to Phase 6?
---
**End of Phase 5. Phase 6 covers Vault secrets management. Shall I continue?**