Now let's move to Phase 6. Zero-trust secrets management with HashiCorp Vault.
This is how production systems handle secrets safely.
In Phases 1 through 5, secrets live in .env and are injected as environment variables.
This has three problems at production scale.
First, static credentials. If POSTGRES_PASSWORD leaks, it works forever.
Until someone manually rotates it, the attacker has access.
Second, shared credentials. Every pod uses the same password.
If the ingestion service is compromised, the attacker has database access identical to the API service.
Third, environment variable exposure. Any process in the container can read os.environ.
Secrets in files with restricted permissions are harder to exfiltrate.
Vault solves all three.
Dynamic credentials rotate automatically every hour.
Per-role credentials. API, agent, and ingestion each get different database users.
With different privileges for each workload.
File-based injection. Vault Agent writes secrets to files that only the application process can read.
Imagine you have a big, yummy box of cookies. Those are your secrets.
Right now, you have one giant jar of cookies that stays on the counter all day.
That's your .env file with all your secrets in one place.
If a naughty monkey comes into your kitchen, he can just walk up.
Grab the whole jar, and eat all the cookies at once.
That's the problem with static credentials in environment variables.
One leak exposes everything, and the credentials work forever.
Vault is like having a special cookie guard.
It completely changes how secrets are managed.
First, the guard has a magic key. Only you get to wear the magic key.
That's your Kubernetes service account.
Second, no more jar. Instead of leaving the big jar out,
the guard keeps it locked away in a tall, tall cupboard.
Third, one tiny cookie at a time. When you are hungry, you show the guard your magic key.
He nods and says okay. He goes to the cupboard.
Takes out just one tiny cookie, and puts it on your plate.
That's the Vault Agent. It puts the secret in a file.
Not in an environment variable where any process can read it.
Fourth, the cookie disappears. After a little while, that cookie vanishes.
If you want another, you show the magic key again.
That's dynamic credentials. They rotate automatically.
If a secret leaks, it only works for a short time.
So, if that naughty monkey comes into the kitchen,
he can't find any cookies. The jar is locked away.
Even if he does find one tiny cookie on your plate,
it disappears so fast he can't steal the whole jar.
That's the zero-trust model. No standing privileges.
Every request re-authenticates. Every secret has a short lifespan.
[## [SECTION: New Files in This Phase]]
Here are the new files we'll create in Phase 6.
infrastructure/vault/vault-bootstrap.sh
Automates the entire Vault configuration.
infrastructure/vault/policies/api-policy.hcl
Least-privilege policy for the API service.
infrastructure/vault/policies/agent-policy.hcl
Policy for the agent service.
infrastructure/vault/policies/ingestion-policy.hcl
Policy for the ingestion service.
infrastructure/k8s/service-accounts.yaml
Kubernetes service accounts for each workload.
infrastructure/vault/vault-agent-config.hcl
Vault Agent sidecar configuration.
src/financial_rag/security/vault.py
Python Vault client for runtime secret retrieval.
src/financial_rag/security/__init__.py
Exports the Vault client.
policies/rego/vault_policy.rego
OPA Rego policy for validating Vault policies.
[## [SECTION: Step 1 — Understand the Vault Architecture]]
Before writing any code, understand how the components connect.
At the center is HashiCorp Vault.
It runs three engines. The database engine for PostgreSQL credentials.
The PKI engine for short-lived TLS certificates.
And the Kubernetes auth method for pod authentication.
Next is the Vault Agent sidecar.
It runs in the same pod as your application container.
The sidecar reads the Kubernetes service account JWT token.
It authenticates to Vault using that token.
Then it writes secrets to a shared volume.
The volume is mounted at slash vault slash secrets.
Your application container reads from that file.
It never talks to Vault directly in normal operation.
Here is the key insight.
The application never talks to Vault directly in normal operation.
Vault Agent handles all authentication and secret renewal.
The app just reads files from disk.
This is much simpler and more secure.
No Vault client code in your application at all.
[## [SECTION: Step 2 — Install Vault on Kubernetes (Component #52)]]
Now let's install Vault on Kubernetes.
We'll use the official HashiCorp Helm chart.
First, add the HashiCorp Helm repository and update it.
Then install Vault in dev mode.
Dev mode starts a single Vault pod with no high availability.
It uses in-memory storage, which loses all data on restart.
This is only for learning the workflow.
Production requires HA mode with Raft storage and auto-unseal.
Wait for Vault to be ready with kubectl wait.
Then verify the status with vault status.
Expected output shows Seal Type shamir, Initialized true, Sealed false.
If it says Sealed true, something went wrong.
[## [SECTION: Step 3 — Vault Bootstrap Script (Components #53–63)]]
Now let's create the Vault bootstrap script.
This script automates the entire Vault configuration.
It's idempotent, meaning you can run it multiple times safely.
Each command checks for existing configuration before creating it.
Create infrastructure slash vault slash vault-bootstrap.sh.
Make it executable with chmod plus x.
The script does ten things in order.
Let me walk through each component.
First, it enables the database secrets engine.
This tells Vault to manage PostgreSQL credentials.
Second, it configures the PostgreSQL connection.
Vault needs admin credentials to create and revoke database users.
Third, it creates three database roles.
One for each service. API, agent, and ingestion.
The API role gets read-only access to filings and financial chunks.
Plus insert on analysis_history for the audit trail.
The agent role gets read access to filings and financial chunks.
And read-write on analysis_history.
The ingestion role gets select, insert, and update on filings and financial chunks.
And usage on all sequences in the public schema.
Fourth, it enables the PKI secrets engine.
PKI stands for Public Key Infrastructure. It handles certificates.
Fifth, it generates a root certificate for the internal certificate authority.
This root CA signs all service certificates.
Sixth, it creates a PKI role for financial rag.
This role defines which domains are allowed and the certificate lifespan.
Seventh, it enables the Kubernetes auth method.
This allows pods to authenticate using their service account.
Eighth, it configures Kubernetes auth.
It reads the cluster's API server address and CA certificate.
Ninth, it writes three Vault policies.
One for each service with least-privilege access.
The API policy can read LLM keys, Redis password, and database credentials.
It can also issue PKI certificates.
The agent policy can read LLM keys, Redis password, and database credentials.
But no PKI access.
The ingestion policy can read Edgar credentials, Redis password, and database credentials.
No LLM or PKI access.
Tenth, it creates Kubernetes auth roles.
Each role binds a service account to a Vault policy.
The API service account gets the API policy.
The agent service account gets the agent policy.
The ingestion service account gets the ingestion policy.
Each with different TTLs.
Finally, the script seeds static secrets.
These are the secrets that aren't dynamically generated.
LLM API keys, Redis password, Edgar user agent, and config values.
You must replace the placeholders before production use.
To run the script, set your PostgreSQL admin password.
Then execute vault-bootstrap.sh from within the Vault pod.
kubectl exec dash it vault dash 0 dash n vault
Then bash dash c, then the script path.
After it completes, verify with vault read database slash creds slash api dash role.
You should see dynamic credentials generated.
Let me summarize the bootstrap workflow.
Enable database engine. Configure PostgreSQL. Create database roles.
Enable PKI. Generate root CA. Create PKI role.
Enable Kubernetes auth. Configure Kubernetes. Create policies.
Create auth roles. Seed static secrets.
Our Vault bootstrap is complete.
Now Vault is ready to provide dynamic credentials to our services.
[## [SECTION: Step 4 — Vault Policies (Component #62)]]
Now let's create the Vault policies as separate files.
For audit and GitOps tracking, we store them in infrastructure/vault/policies.
First, api-policy.hcl.
This is the least-privilege policy for the API service.
It can read LLM secrets, Redis secrets, and config secrets.
It can read dynamic database credentials for the API role.
And it can create and update PKI certificates.
For mTLS between services.
Second, agent-policy.hcl.
The agent service needs LLM access and Redis.
It can read database credentials for the agent role.
But it cannot issue PKI certificates.
Third, ingestion-policy.hcl.
The ingestion service only needs EDGAR config and Redis.
Notice what's missing. No LLM API key access.
Ingestion does not call the LLM.
Why three separate policies?
This is the principle of least privilege per workload.
If the ingestion service is compromised, the attacker cannot call the LLM.
The API service does not need EDGAR credentials.
Compartmentalisation limits the blast radius.
Each service gets exactly what it needs, nothing more.
[## [SECTION: Step 5 — Kubernetes Service Accounts (Component #64)]]
Now let's create the Kubernetes service accounts.
One per workload.
Create infrastructure slash k8s slash service-accounts.yaml.
We define three service accounts.
financial-rag-agent-api for the API service.
financial-rag-agent-agent for the agent service.
And financial-rag-agent-ingestion for the ingestion service.
Each in the financial-rag namespace.
Apply them with kubectl create namespace if it doesn't exist.
Then kubectl apply dash f.
These service accounts will be used by the Vault Agent sidecar.
Each maps to a different Vault policy.
[## [SECTION: Step 6 — Vault Agent Sidecar Config (Component #65)]]
Now let's configure the Vault Agent sidecar.
This runs as a second container in each pod.
Create infrastructure slash vault slash vault-agent-config.hcl.
Let me explain what this configuration does.
First, the vault block sets the Vault address.
http colon slash slash vault dot vault dot svc dot cluster dot local colon 8200.
This is the Kubernetes internal DNS name for Vault.
All pods in the cluster can reach it.
Next, auto_auth tells Vault how to authenticate.
We use the Kubernetes auth method.
The sidecar reads the pod's service account JWT.
It presents this token to Vault.
The role must match the service account.
We set it via an environment variable on the sidecar.
Now the template blocks.
These render secrets into files.
The first template renders database credentials.
It calls the secret command to get dynamic credentials.
The output goes to slash vault slash secrets slash database.env.
The format is environment variables.
When credentials rotate, the command runs kill dash HUP.
This sends a signal to the application to reload.
The annotation approach uses Vault's mutating admission webhook.
It automatically injects the sidecar without changing the deployment spec.
Here are the annotations for a deployment.
vault.hashicorp.com slash agent-inject set to true.
vault.hashicorp.com slash role specifies which Vault role to use.
And agent-inject-secret plus agent-inject-template define each secret.
This is the recommended production pattern.
No manual sidecar configuration needed.
[## [SECTION: Step 7 — Deploy and Test the Sidecar (Component #66)]]
Now let's test the Vault Agent sidecar.
We'll deploy a test pod with the API service account.
This pod has the Vault Agent annotations.
It will automatically inject the sidecar and fetch secrets.
We create a simple pod with the busybox image.
It just sleeps for 3600 seconds so we can inspect it.
The annotations tell Vault to inject the sidecar.
And to fetch the database secret from the API role.
Wait for the pod to be ready with kubectl wait.
Then inspect the injected secret file.
The expected output shows POSTGRES_USER and POSTGRES_PASSWORD.
Notice the username starts with v dash k8s dash api dash role.
This is a dynamically generated credential.
Unique per pod, rotated automatically after one hour.
If you run the test multiple times, you'll get different usernames.
Each time, Vault creates a new database user.
Clean up the test pod when done.
kubectl delete pod vault-test in the financial-rag namespace.
[## [SECTION: Step 8 — Python Vault Client (Component #67)]]
Now let's build the Python Vault client.
We'll put it in src/financial_rag/security/vault.py
This client handles reading secrets from Vault.
But with an important design decision.
The client has a three-tier priority order.
First, try file-based injection from the Vault Agent sidecar.
This is the production path. Secrets are written to slash vault slash secrets.
As dot env files that the app can read.
Second, if no file exists, try direct Vault API using hvac.
This is for development when running Vault locally.
Third, fall back to environment variables.
This is for local development without Vault at all.
The VaultSecretReader class has a read method.
It takes a secret name like database or llm.
In production, it looks for slash vault slash secrets slash database.env.
It parses the KEY=VALUE pairs and returns them as a dictionary.
The _parse_env_file method handles the file parsing.
It skips comments and blank lines.
If the file doesn't exist, we try direct Vault API.
We need VAULT_ADDR and VAULT_TOKEN environment variables.
For static secrets like LLM keys, we use the KV v2 engine.
For dynamic database credentials, we use the database engine.
The read_database_credentials method is a convenience wrapper.
It specifically reads the database secret.
We use a module-level singleton for the Vault reader.
get_vault_reader returns the same instance every time.
Update the security package __init__.py.
Export VaultSecretReader and get_vault_reader.
Install the hvac library first.
pip install hvac.
Let me summarize the Vault client design.
The key insight is that the application never talks to Vault directly.
In production, the sidecar handles everything.
The app just reads files from slash vault slash secrets.
This is much simpler and more secure.
The direct Vault API path is only for development.
And for testing when you don't have the sidecar.
In production, VAULT_ADDR and VAULT_TOKEN are not set.
So the client only uses the file path.
Our Python Vault client is complete.
Now our application can read secrets from Vault seamlessly.
[## [SECTION: Step 9 — OPA Rego Policy for Vault (Component #74 preview)]]
Now let's look at OPA Rego policy validation for Vault.
This ensures our Vault policies are secure before they are applied.
OPA stands for Open Policy Agent. It's a general-purpose policy engine.
We use it to validate Vault policy files.
Install conftest first. pip install conftest.
This tool evaluates policies against your policy files.
We create a test input with a bad policy.
It grants write on a wildcard secret path.
And delete capability on that same path.
These are dangerous permissions.
We run conftest test against this input.
Using the vault_policy.rego file from our repo.
The output shows two failures.
One for wildcard write, one for delete capability.
The Rego policy enforces three rules.
No wildcard write on secret paths.
No delete capability on secret paths.
Application roles should never delete secrets.
No sudo capability except for admin policies.
And no sys slash access from non-admin workloads.
[## [SECTION: Step 10 — Production Vault HA (Component #68)]]
Now let's deploy Vault in production HA mode.
We upgrade the Helm chart with different settings.
Dev mode is disabled. HA mode is enabled.
We use three replicas for high availability.
Raft storage is enabled. This is Vault's built-in consensus algorithm.
It replaces Consul storage.
Data storage is enabled with 10 gigabytes per replica.
And the web UI is enabled for management.
In production, Vault must be unsealed after every restart.
Manual unsealing is operationally painful.
You need 3 out of 5 key shares to unseal.
That means someone must type three different keys.
AWS KMS auto-unseal solves this.
Vault unseals itself using a KMS key you control.
The seal block goes in your Helm values as extraConfig.
Region, and the KMS key ARN.
When Vault starts, it calls the KMS service.
The KMS key decrypts Vault's master key automatically.
No human intervention needed. Vault just works after restarts.
Now let's set up Raft snapshot backups.
A manual snapshot command saves the Vault state.
Use this before upgrades or major changes.
For automated backups, we use a Kubernetes CronJob.
It runs daily at 2 AM.
The job calls vault operator raft snapshot save.
Then uploads the snapshot to S3.
[## [SECTION: Step 11 — Phase 6 Verification]]
Now let's verify everything works.
First, read dynamic database credentials from Vault.
vault read database slash creds slash api-role.
You get a lease ID, lease duration of one hour, username, and password.
The username starts with v dash k8s dash api dash role.
The password is a secure random string.
Next, verify the credential actually works in PostgreSQL.
Use PGPASSWORD with the password, then run a SELECT query.
If the query succeeds, your dynamic credentials are working.
Finally, verify the policy denies what it should.
Create a token with the api-policy.
Then try to access the EDGAR secret path.
vault kv get secret slash financial-rag slash prod slash edgar.
Expected output is permission denied.
The API service should not have access to EDGAR secrets.
Let me summarize Phase six.
We installed Vault on Kubernetes.
We bootstrapped the database and PKI engines.
We created least-privilege policies per service.
We configured the Vault Agent sidecar for file injection.
We built a Python client that reads secrets from files.
With fallbacks for development.
And we set up production HA with AWS KMS auto-unseal.
Plus Raft snapshot backups for disaster recovery.
Phase six is complete.
Secrets are now managed securely at production scale.
---
**End of Phase 6. Phase 7 covers CI/CD Pipeline. Shall I continue?**