Looking at compliance frameworks can feel overwhelming.
So many standards, so much documentation, and the acronyms.
It is enough to make anyone feel stuck.
But what if there was one framework that actually makes sense
for modern SaaS companies?
That is SOC 2.
Hi there, and welcome to a course where I will take you
from SOC 2 beginner to confident compliance lead.
Without endless theory or aimless documentation reading.
This is about understanding what actually matters
while truly grasping why.
Starting from what SOC 2 is and why you should care,
to how each Trust Service Criterion applies to your actual infrastructure.
And finally building a complete evidence package
that would satisfy even the toughest auditor.
By the end of this crash course, you will not just know SOC 2.
You will have created something you can showcase to customers and investors.
But that is not all. For those ready to dive even deeper,
I have put together a comprehensive SOC 2 readiness guide.
Designed to take you from zero to audit-ready.
Whether it is learning evidence collection, remediation planning,
or working with auditors. You can find all the links in the description below.
But for now, let us dive into the video together.
We will build a complete compliance program using a real financial RAG agent
as our example system. Let us get started.
SOC 2 is a game changer.
It is an auditing standard created by the AICPA.
The American Institute of Certified Public Accountants.
It has become the gold standard for SaaS companies worldwide.
Unlike ISO 27001 which is international,
SOC 2 is particularly popular in North America.
But global customers increasingly demand it.
And here is what makes it special.
It does not prescribe specific controls.
Instead, it gives you five Trust Service Criteria.
And you get to choose which ones apply.
Let me break down the five TSCs.
First, Security.
This one is mandatory for everyone.
It means your system is protected against unauthorized access.
Think API keys, database encryption, network policies.
All the foundational stuff.
Second, Availability.
This is about your system being available for operation as agreed.
For most SaaS, that means uptime commitments.
Your ninety-nine point nine percent SLO, multi-AZ deployment.
All of that.
Third, Processing Integrity.
This means system processing is complete, accurate, and timely.
For our financial RAG agent, this includes things like SHA-256 deduplication.
Ensuring we do not ingest the same SEC filing twice.
Fourth, Confidentiality.
Information designated as confidential is protected.
In our system, that is SEC filing text before it is publicly filed.
Plus user queries.
Fifth, Privacy.
This covers personal information collected, used, retained, and disclosed.
If you collect emails or any PII, this applies.
Now, there are two types of SOC 2 reports.
And this confuses everyone at first.
Type I evaluates whether your controls are designed appropriately
at a specific point in time.
Think of it as an architecture review.
It takes about one to two months.
And costs twenty to fifty thousand dollars.
Type II evaluates whether those controls are operating effectively
over a period of time. Typically six to twelve months.
This is what customers really want.
It proves you are not just designed well, but actually following through.
Type II takes four to eight months.
And costs fifty to one hundred fifty thousand dollars.
The typical timeline looks like this.
Weeks one to two for scoping.
Weeks three to four for gap analysis.
Weeks five to eight for remediation.
Week nine for Type I fieldwork.
Week ten for delivery.
Then you operate for six to twelve months collecting evidence.
Month thirteen for Type II fieldwork.
Month fourteen for final delivery.
The key players in a SOC 2 audit are your auditor.
Typically the Big Four. Deloitte, PwC, KPMG, EY.
Or boutique firms.
The report recipients are your customers, investors,
and board of directors.
Your team includes security engineers, platform engineers,
and compliance leads.
Let me show you how to map your system to these criteria
with a real example.
I am going to walk through mapping a financial RAG agent
to the five TSCs.
Open your terminal and let us create our system boundary document.
Type mkdir dash p soc2.
Now run cat greater than soc2/system-boundary.yaml with here document.
Let me write this out for you.
system_name colon space Financial RAG Agent Platform.
system_description colon space AI hyphen powered SEC filing analysis
and retrieval system.
Then trust_service_criteria_mapping colon.
Indent security colon.
Indent again description colon System protected against unauthorized access.
Indent implementations colon dash API key authentication with rotation,
dash Kubernetes RBAC for internal access,
dash Vault dynamic credentials with one hour TTL,
dash Cilium network policies for zero dash trust.
Then availability colon.
Description colon System available as agreed with ninety-nine point nine percent uptime.
Implementations colon Multi-AZ deployment for RDS and EKS,
HPA with three to twenty replicas based on CPU,
Karpenter for new nodes in under thirty seconds,
and PodDisruptionBudgets with minimum two replicas.
Then processing_integrity colon.
Description colon Complete, accurate, timely processing.
Implementations colon SHA-256 deduplication for filings,
idempotent ingestion cron jobs,
and PostgreSQL ACID compliance.
Then confidentiality colon.
Description colon Confidential information protected.
Implementations colon TLS one point three for all data in transit,
RDS, S3, and EBS encryption at rest,
SEC non-public filing text,
and user query data.
Then privacy colon.
Description colon Personal information protected.
Implementations colon No PII collected without consent,
data retention policies with thirty days for queries,
and user deletion capability.
Close the here document with EOF.
Now let us verify our mapping.
Run cat soc2 forward slash system-boundary dot yaml.
You should see all five criteria mapped to specific implementations
in your codebase.
This is what auditors want to see.
Not generic statements, but actual technical implementations.
Every control you implement should have code that proves it exists.
That is the foundation of SOC 2.
For the availability criterion, here is what your HPA configuration
should look like.
In k8s forward slash hpa dot yaml.
apiVersion colon autoscaling forward slash v2.
kind colon HorizontalPodAutoscaler.
metadata colon name colon financial-rag-api.
namespace colon financial-rag.
spec colon minReplicas colon three.
maxReplicas colon twenty.
metrics colon dash type colon Resource.
resource colon name colon cpu.
target colon type colon Utilization.
averageUtilization colon seventy.
This directly supports CC7 point one.
System availability.
Your lab exercise for this lecture is to map your own RAG system components
to all five TSCs.
Create a document similar to what I just showed.
But for your actual deployment.
Identify where each criterion is implemented in your codebase.
Once you have done that, you are ready for Lecture one point two.
Where we will define the system boundary.
What is in scope and what is out.
---
## LECTURE 1.2 — SCOPE DEFINITION: WHAT GOES IN, WHAT STAYS OUT
One of the most common mistakes in SOC 2 preparation
is defining your scope too broadly or too narrowly.
Too broad and you will drown in evidence collection.
Too narrow and customers will question whether the report
covers what matters to them.
Let me show you how to define the perfect system boundary.
The key principle is this.
Include everything required to deliver your service.
Exclude everything that customers do not depend on.
I am going to create a complete system boundary document
for our financial RAG agent.
Run cat greater than soc2 forward slash system-boundary dot yaml.
This time we are adding system components and data flows.
First, system_name and system_description remain the same.
Then system_components colon.
Indent infrastructure colon dash EKS Cluster financial-rag-prod,
dash RDS PostgreSQL with pgvector,
dash ElastiCache Redis,
dash S3 buckets for backups,
dash ECR repositories.
Indent application colon dash FastAPI application as api service,
dash Agent workers as agent service,
dash Ingestion cron jobs,
dash Helm charts.
Indent observability colon dash Prometheus metrics,
dash Loki logs,
dash Tempo traces,
dash Grafana dashboards.
Indent security colon dash Vault for secrets,
dash Cilium network policies,
dash Falco runtime security,
dash OPA forward slash Gatekeeper policies.
Then excluded_components colon.
Dash Developer workstations out of scope,
dash Customer on-premises environments,
dash Third-party APIs like OpenAI and Groq with note that vendor assessment covers,
dash Public internet infrastructure.
Then data_flows colon.
First flow. source colon SEC EDGAR API.
destination colon Ingestion cron job.
data_type colon Public filings.
classification colon Public.
Second flow. source colon User via API.
destination colon API service.
data_type colon Query text comma API keys.
classification colon Confidential.
Third flow. source colon API service.
destination colon OpenAI forward slash Groq API.
data_type colon Query context.
classification colon Confidential.
Close the file.
Now let us visualize the trust boundaries.
Create soc2 forward slash trust-boundaries dot md.
Write hash Trust Boundaries.
In Scope open parenthesis Your Control close parenthesis.
Dash API Gateway to EKS Cluster to RDS to ElastiCache to S3.
Dash All configuration comma deployment comma and operations.
Out of Scope open parenthesis Vendor Managed close parenthesis.
Dash OpenAI API covered by vendor assessment.
Dash SEC EDGAR as public data source.
Dash Customer VPC as customer responsibility.
Trust Boundary Controls.
Dash TLS one point three for all outbound connections.
Dash API key authentication for OpenAI.
Dash Vendor SOC 2 reports reviewed annually.
The key insight here is that you do not need to control everything.
You just need to manage the risks of what you do not control
through vendor assessments.
Now let us document data flows in detail.
Create soc2 forward slash data-flow-mapping dot yaml.
First flow. flow_id colon DF-001.
name colon SEC Filing Ingestion.
source colon SEC EDGAR API as public.
destination colon S3 raw bucket.
transformation colon SHA-256 hashing comma validation.
classification colon Public.
controls colon dash TLS one point two plus for download,
dash Checksum validation.
Second flow. flow_id colon DF-002.
name colon User Query Processing.
source colon Customer API client.
destination colon OpenAI API.
data_elements colon dash Query text, dash Retrieved context, dash API key.
classification colon Confidential.
retention colon Thirty days in logs.
controls colon dash TLS one point three end-to-end,
dash No persistent storage of queries,
dash API key rotation every ninety days.
Third flow. flow_id colon DF-003.
name colon Agent Analysis Storage.
source colon Agent worker.
destination colon RDS PostgreSQL analysis_history table.
data_elements colon dash Query text, dash Response, dash User ID hashed.
classification colon Confidential.
retention colon Ninety days.
controls colon dash Encryption at rest with AWS KMS,
dash Row-level access control,
dash Audit logging.
Now for a pro tip that will save you hours with your auditor.
Create a scope change management process.
Any time you add a new service or change a data flow,
you need to reassess whether it is in scope.
Create soc2 forward slash scope-change-checklist dot md.
Include when to review scope.
New microservice deployment.
New data source integration.
New customer data type.
Infrastructure migration like a new cloud region.
Review questions.
Does this component process customer data?
Is this component required for core service delivery?
Would customers care if this component failed?
Documentation required includes updated system boundary diagram,
updated data flow map,
control gap assessment,
and evidence collection update.
Your lab exercise for this lecture is to create a system boundary diagram
for your deployment.
Use draw.io or Mermaid to visualize the components.
Include trust boundaries showing what you control
versus what you do not.
Then create a data flow map showing how customer data moves
through your system.
Identify which TSCs apply to each flow.
Once you have completed that, move on to Lecture one point three.
Where we will select specific controls and map them to implementations.
---
## LECTURE 1.3 — CONTROL SELECTION: WHICH CONTROLS APPLY TO YOU
Now that we understand the five Trust Service Criteria
and have defined our system boundary,
it is time to select specific controls.
SOC 2 does not tell you exactly which controls to implement.
You have to choose based on your system's risks.
The SOC 2 Trust Services Criteria are organized into nine categories.
Often called CC1 through CC9.
But for most SaaS companies, you will focus on CC6 through CC9.
Let me walk you through which ones matter for our RAG system.
Create soc2 forward slash controls-mapping dot yaml.
Start with a comment. Hash Selected controls for Financial RAG Agent.
Then security_controls colon.
CC6.1 colon Logical access security.
CC6.6 colon Encryption of data at rest.
CC6.7 colon Encryption of data in transit.
Then a comment for CC7.0 System Operations.
CC7.1 colon System availability.
CC7.2 colon Monitoring and alerting.
CC7.4 colon Backup and recovery.
CC7.5 colon Incident response.
Comment for CC8.0 Change Management.
CC8.1 colon Change management procedures.
Comment for CC9.0 Risk Mitigation.
CC9.2 colon Vendor risk management.
Then selected_controls colon.
Each control gets an entry.
First control. control_id colon CC6.1.
title colon Logical access security.
implementation colon API key authentication comma RBAC.
evidence colon Kubernetes RBAC configs comma API logs.
owner colon at sign security dash team.
Second control. control_id colon CC6.6.
title colon Encryption at rest.
implementation colon RDS encryption comma S3 SSE-KMS.
evidence colon AWS Config rules comma KMS key policies.
owner colon at sign platform dash team.
Third control. control_id colon CC6.7.
title colon Encryption in transit.
implementation colon TLS one point three comma Cilium mTLS.
evidence colon Ingress TLS config comma certificates.
owner colon at sign platform dash team.
Fourth control. control_id colon CC7.1.
title colon System availability.
implementation colon Multi-AZ comma HPA comma PDBs.
evidence colon SLO dashboards comma uptime reports.
owner colon at sign platform dash team.
Fifth control. control_id colon CC7.2.
title colon Monitoring and alerting.
implementation colon Prometheus comma Loki comma PagerDuty.
evidence colon Alert configs comma on-call schedules.
owner colon at sign platform dash team.
Sixth control. control_id colon CC7.4.
title colon Backup and recovery.
implementation colon Velero comma RDS backups.
evidence colon Backup logs comma restore tests.
owner colon at sign platform dash team.
Seventh control. control_id colon CC8.1.
title colon Change management.
implementation colon GitOps comma PR reviews.
evidence colon PR approvals comma ArgoCD logs.
owner colon at sign eng dash team.
Eighth control. control_id colon CC9.2.
title colon Vendor risk management.
implementation colon Vendor assessments.
evidence colon Vendor questionnaires comma BAAs.
owner colon at sign compliance dash team.
Now let me show you how each control maps to actual code.
This is what makes your SOC 2 program real.
Not just documents, but implemented controls.
For CC6.6, encryption at rest.
In terraform forward slash rds-encryption dot tf.
The aws_db_instance resource for financial_rag has storage_encrypted set to true.
And kms_key_id referencing aws_kms_key.rds_key.arn.
The aws_kms_key resource has enable_key_rotation set to true
and rotation_period_in_days of 365.
For CC7.1, availability.
In k8s forward slash pdb dot yaml.
The PodDisruptionBudget named financial-rag-api-pdb has minAvailable set to two.
In k8s forward slash hpa dot yaml.
The HorizontalPodAutoscaler has minReplicas three,
maxReplicas twenty, and CPU target average utilization seventy.
For CC8.1, change management.
In dot github forward slash workflows forward slash pr-checks dot yaml.
The validate-change job requires approval for production changes
and logs the change for audit.
Now here is a critical concept. Control inheritance.
Some controls can be inherited from your cloud provider.
For example, AWS's physical security controls at their data centers
inherit to you.
You do not need to implement guards at AWS facilities.
Document control inheritance like this in soc2 forward slash control-inheritance dot yaml.
Under AWS_inherited, list physical access to data centers.
With aws_control AWS SOC 2 comma ISO 27001.
Evidence being AWS SOC 2 report reviewed annually.
Also data center environmental controls with evidence AWS SOC 2 report.
And hardware lifecycle management with evidence AWS SOC 2 report.
Under your_responsibility, list application-level access control
with implementation API key middleware.
Customer data encryption keys with implementation KMS customer-managed keys.
Backup and restore procedures with implementation Velero and RDS backups.
And incident detection and response with implementation Falco, PagerDuty, and runbooks.
Your lab exercise is to map all five TSCs to specific code files
in your repository.
For each control, identify which code file implements it.
Who owns that code.
And how evidence is collected.
Create a control matrix similar to what I showed,
but customized to your system.
Include both implemented controls and inherited controls
from your cloud provider.
Once you have completed that, move on to Lecture one point four.
Where we will set up automated evidence collection.
---
## LECTURE 1.4 — EVIDENCE COLLECTION STRATEGY: AUTOMATE EVERYTHING
Evidence is the currency of SOC 2.
Without evidence, controls do not exist.
The worst thing that can happen during an audit is the auditor asks
for evidence of a control and you cannot produce it.
Manual evidence collection is error-prone and miserable.
You will forget to collect it, collect the wrong thing,
or collect it at the wrong time.
The solution is automation.
Let me show you how to build an automated evidence collection pipeline.
Create dot github forward slash workflows forward slash evidence-collection dot yaml.
Name colon SOC 2 Evidence Collection.
On colon schedule colon dash cron colon zero zero asterisk asterisk asterisk.
That is daily at midnight.
And workflow_dispatch for manual trigger.
The collect-evidence job runs on ubuntu-latest.
Steps include checkout, then for each control we collect evidence.
For CC6.1, collect API key configuration.
Run kubectl get secret api-keys in the financial-rag namespace.
Output to evidence forward slash CC6.1 forward slash api-keys with date.
For CC6.6, collect RDS encryption status.
Run aws rds describe-db-instances for financial-rag-prod.
Query StorageEncrypted. Output to evidence forward slash CC6.6 forward slash rds-encryption with date.
For CC6.7, collect TLS certificate expiration.
Run kubectl get secret api-tls, pipe to jq and base64 decode,
then openssl x509 to get end date.
Output to evidence forward slash CC6.7 forward slash cert-expiry with date.
For CC7.1, collect uptime metrics.
Run curl to Prometheus querying up job financial-rag-api.
Output to evidence forward slash CC7.1 forward slash uptime with date.
For CC7.2, collect alert configurations.
Run kubectl get prometheusrules across all namespaces.
Output to evidence forward slash CC7.2 forward slash alert-rules with date.
For CC7.4, collect backup status.
Run velero backup get in JSON format.
Output to evidence forward slash CC7.4 forward slash backup-status with date.
For CC8.1, collect recent deployments.
Run kubectl rollout history for the API deployment.
Output to evidence forward slash CC8.1 forward slash deployments with date.
Finally, upload to S3 evidence bucket.
Run aws s3 sync evidence to s3://financial-rag-soc2-evidence with date folder.
Now let me show you the evidence retention policy.
You need to keep evidence for the audit period plus typically seven years
for SOC 2 Type II.
In terraform forward slash s3-evidence-lifecycle dot tf.
Create an aws_s3_bucket_lifecycle_configuration for the evidence bucket.
First rule. id colon archive-after-1-year.
Transition to GLACIER after 365 days.
Second rule. id colon delete-after-7-years.
Expiration after 2555 days.
Which is seven years.
Here is the complete evidence inventory you should maintain.
CC6.1 evidence type API key logs from CloudWatch with retention one year.
CC6.6 evidence type RDS encryption status from AWS Config with retention seven years.
CC6.7 evidence type TLS cert expiry from kubectl with retention seven years.
CC7.1 evidence type uptime metrics from Prometheus with retention one year.
CC7.2 evidence type alert configurations from Git with retention seven years.
CC7.4 evidence type backup logs from Velero with retention seven years.
CC8.1 evidence type PR approvals from GitHub API with retention seven years.
CC9.2 evidence type vendor assessments from S3 with retention seven years.
Now create a template for documenting each piece of evidence.
Make a file called evidence forward slash README dot md.
Start with evidence format standard.
All evidence must include timestamp of collection,
control ID, description of what the evidence proves,
collection method, and retention period.
For CC6.1, the file is CC6.1 forward slash api-keys dash YYYYMMDD dot yaml.
It proves API keys are properly configured and rotated.
Collection is automated daily. Retention one year.
For CC6.6, the file is CC6.6 forward slash rds-encryption dash YYYYMMDD dot json.
It proves RDS instance has encryption enabled.
Automated daily. Retention seven years.
For CC7.1, the file is CC7.1 forward slash uptime dash YYYYMMDD dot json.
It proves system meets ninety-nine point nine percent availability SLO.
Automated daily. Retention one year.
Now create a validation script.
In scripts forward slash validate-evidence dot sh.
The script takes a date parameter defaulting to today.
It sets evidence directory to evidence forward slash that date.
Then for each control including CC6.1, CC6.6, CC6.7, CC7.1, CC7.2, CC7.4, and CC8.1.
It checks if the control directory has any files.
If missing, it outputs a red X and exits with error.
If all present, it outputs green check marks
and says all evidence present.
Your lab exercise is to run the evidence collection pipeline
and verify the artifacts.
Set up the GitHub Actions workflow I showed.
Or create a local script if you are not using GitHub Actions.
Run it once manually, then check that evidence files are created
in your S3 bucket or local directory.
Verify that each control has at least one evidence file.
If anything is missing, note what is missing.
That is your gap analysis for remediation.
Once you have completed that, move on to Lecture one point five.
Where we will cover Type I versus Type II timelines and expectations.
---
## LECTURE 1.5 — TYPE I VS TYPE II: TIMELINES, COSTS, AND WHAT CUSTOMERS WANT
One of the first decisions you will make is whether to pursue
a Type I or Type II report.
And in what order.
Let me clear up the confusion.
Type I evaluates design.
Are your controls designed appropriately to meet the trust criteria?
It is a point-in-time assessment.
Your auditor will look at your policies, your architecture diagrams,
your control implementations.
But they will not test whether they actually work over time.
Type II evaluates operating effectiveness.
Not only are your controls designed well,
but they have been working properly over a period of time.
Typically six to twelve months.
Here is the comparison table that matters.
Type I proves controls are designed appropriately.
Duration is point-in-time.
Evidence needed includes design documents and configurations.
Timeline is one to two months.
Cost is twenty to fifty thousand dollars.
Customer value shows intent.
Type II proves controls are operating effectively.
Duration is six to twelve months.
Evidence needed includes operational logs and monitoring data.
Timeline is four to eight months.
Cost is fifty to one hundred fifty thousand dollars.
Customer value shows proven operation.
Most companies do Type I first, then Type II about six to twelve months later.
Here is why.
Type I gives you something to show customers
while you are building the operational history for Type II.
Here is the typical timeline I recommend.
Months one to two. Scoping and readiness assessment.
Months three to four. Control gap analysis.
Months five to eight. Remediation. Building missing controls.
Month nine. Type I audit fieldwork.
Month ten. Type I report delivery.
Months ten to sixteen. Continuous operation and evidence collection.
Month seventeen. Type II audit fieldwork.
Month eighteen. Type II report delivery.
Now let me show you how to assess your readiness.
Create scripts forward slash readiness-check dot sh.
Start with echo SOC 2 Readiness Check.
For CC6.1, check API key authentication.
Look for API_KEY_ENABLED in the deployment environment variables.
For CC6.6, check RDS encryption.
Verify StorageEncrypted is true.
For CC6.7, check TLS for ALB.
Look for TLS configuration in the ingress.
For CC7.1, check Prometheus metrics.
Look for a ServiceMonitor.
For CC7.4, check Velero backups.
Look for a completed backup.
For CC8.1, check GitHub branch protection.
Verify required pull request reviews are configured.
Each check outputs a green check mark if present,
a red X if missing.
Here is what customers actually care about.
When a customer asks for your SOC 2 report,
enterprise customers want Type II with all five trust criteria.
Mid-market customers often accept Type I initially,
but want Type II within a year.
Startup customers might only care about Security.
Pro tip. Do not wait for perfection.
Get a Type I report as soon as your basic controls are in place.
It is much easier to sell with a Type I report than with nothing.
Your lab exercise is to run the readiness check script
against your environment.
For each missing control, create a remediation ticket.
Estimate how long each fix will take.
That becomes your roadmap to Type I.
Once you have completed that, move on to Lecture one point six.
Where we will walk through an auditor interview.
---
## LECTURE 1.6 — THE AUDITOR WALKTHROUGH: FIVE QUESTIONS AND HOW TO ANSWER THEM
The auditor walkthrough is where SOC 2 readiness lives or dies.
This is when the auditor meets with your team
to understand your system and controls.
They are not trying to fail you.
They are trying to understand.
But if you cannot explain your controls clearly,
they will note gaps.
Let me walk you through the five most common questions
and exactly how to answer them.
Question one. How do you ensure only authorized users access the system?
Here is your answer template.
Our system implements defense-in-depth for access control.
At the edge, all API requests require a valid API key
with rotation every ninety days.
Internally, Kubernetes RBAC restricts what service accounts can do.
For database access, Vault provides dynamic credentials
with a one hour TTL.
Network policies enforce zero-trust between services.
And all access attempts are logged with a unique request ID for audit.
Now show them the evidence.
Run grep with A10 on APIKeyMiddleware in the middleware file.
Run kubectl get roles and rolebindings to show RBAC configuration.
Run vault read database forward slash creds forward slash rag-app
to show dynamic credentials.
Run kubectl logs on the API deployment filtered for API key
to show audit logs.
Question two. How do you detect and respond to security incidents?
Answer template.
We use Falco for runtime security with eBPF probes
monitoring system calls.
We have written custom rules for RAG-specific threats.
Like unauthorized EDGAR or OpenAI access.
Alerts route to PagerDuty with severity-based escalation.
Incident response runbooks are version-controlled in Git.
And we conduct post-incident reviews with evidence collection
for every security event.
Evidence to show. Cat the Falco rules file.
Kubectl get configmap for falcosidekick to show PagerDuty integration.
Ls runbooks to show they exist.
And kubectl logs on the Falco daemonset filtered for alerts.
Question three. How do you ensure data integrity
and prevent unauthorized changes?
Answer template.
Data integrity starts at ingestion.
SHA-256 deduplication ensures we never process the same SEC filing twice.
For changes, we use GitOps with ArgoCD.
Which prevents manual kubectl changes.
All code changes require PR reviews with at least one approver.
Database changes are audited in the analysis_history table.
And we maintain point-in-time recovery capable backups.
Evidence. Grep for file_hash in the SEC ingestor.
Argocd app get to show sync status.
And psql to count records in analysis_history for the last thirty days.
Question four. How do you ensure system availability meets SLAs?
Answer template.
We target ninety-nine point nine percent availability
with multi-AZ deployment for both RDS and EKS.
The API automatically scales from three to twenty replicas
based on CPU utilization using HPA.
Karpenter provisions new nodes in under thirty seconds
during scale-up events.
PodDisruptionBudgets ensure minimum two replicas during maintenance.
Our SLO dashboard in Grafana tracks rolling thirty-day availability.
Question five. How do you manage third-party vendor risks?
Answer template.
We maintain a vendor register for all third parties
that process customer data.
For high-risk vendors like OpenAI, we have reviewed their SOC 2 Type II report
and executed a data processing agreement.
AWS is covered under the shared responsibility model.
Their physical and environmental controls are inherited.
All vendors are reassessed annually.
Here is the vendor register you should maintain in vendor-register dot yaml.
OpenAI has service LLM API, risk level high,
assessment date 2026-01-15.
Controls include SOC 2 Type II report reviewed,
data processing agreement executed,
and subprocessor list reviewed.
Next review 2026-07-15.
AWS has service cloud infrastructure, risk level medium.
Controls include Shared Responsibility Model documented
and AWS SOC 2 report reviewed.
Next review 2026-07-15.
SEC EDGAR has service public data source, risk level low.
Controls include public data only and no customer data shared.
Next review 2027-01-15.
Your lab exercise is to conduct a mock auditor interview with your team.
Have one person play the auditor, asking these five questions.
Practice until you can answer smoothly without looking at notes.
Record the session and review what could be clearer.
Once you have completed that, move on to Lecture one point seven.
Where we will create a remediation plan for any gaps.
---
## LECTURE 1.7 — REMEDIATION PLANNING: CLOSING EVERY GAP BEFORE FIELDWORK
Your readiness check will almost certainly reveal gaps.
That is normal. Every company has them.
The key is having a plan to close them before your audit.
Let me show you the most common gaps I see
and exactly how to fix them.
Create soc2 forward slash remediation-tracker dot yaml.
Under remediations, list each gap.
First gap. gap colon No API key rotation policy.
control colon CC6.1.
owner colon at sign security dash team.
due_date colon 2026-04-15.
status colon in_progress.
steps colon dash Create rotation Lambda function.
dash Update documentation.
dash Test rotation in staging.
evidence colon A pull request URL.
Second gap. gap colon RDS not encrypted in staging.
control colon CC6.6.
owner colon at sign platform dash team.
due_date colon 2026-05-01.
status colon planned.
steps colon dash Take snapshot of unencrypted database.
dash Restore as encrypted.
dash Update Terraform config.
dash Verify application connectivity.
Third gap. gap colon Missing vendor assessment for OpenAI.
control colon CC9.2.
owner colon at sign compliance dash team.
due_date colon 2026-04-30.
status colon not_started.
steps colon dash Request SOC 2 report from OpenAI.
dash Review controls.
dash Document in vendor register.
Fourth gap. gap colon No quarterly restore test performed.
control colon CC7.4.
owner colon at sign platform dash team.
due_date colon 2026-04-15.
status colon in_progress.
steps colon dash Write restore test script.
dash Schedule first test.
dash Document results.
evidence colon A link to the tests directory.
Here is a remediation timeline in Gantt chart format.
For access control, API key rotation starts 2026-03-15 for fourteen days.
RBAC documentation starts after that for seven days.
For encryption, RDS encryption in staging starts 2026-03-20 for twenty-one days.
TLS certificate automation starts 2026-04-01 for fourteen days.
For operations, restore test script starts 2026-03-25 for ten days.
On-call schedule starts 2026-03-20 for five days.
For vendors, OpenAI assessment starts 2026-04-01 for fourteen days.
AWS review starts 2026-04-01 for seven days.
For each gap, you need a clear description of what is missing.
The specific control it affects.
An owner assigned. A due date.
Concrete steps to fix it.
And evidence of completion.
Here is how to prioritize remediation.
Critical priority means missing control with high risk.
For example, no API authentication.
Timeline less than two weeks.
High priority means partial control with medium risk.
For example, manual key rotation only.
Timeline less than four weeks.
Medium priority means control exists but weak evidence.
For example, no audit logging.
Timeline less than eight weeks.
Low priority means control exists but needs documentation.
For example, policy not documented.
Timeline less than twelve weeks.
Your lab exercise is to create a remediation plan
for the gaps you identified in your readiness check.
Use the tracker template I provided.
Assign owners and due dates.
Review with your team and get commitment on the timeline.
Once you have completed that, move on to Lecture one point eight.
Where we will assemble the final evidence package.
---
## LECTURE 1.8 — EVIDENCE PACKAGE ASSEMBLY: WHAT YOU HAND YOUR AUDITOR
The final step before your audit is assembling the evidence package.
This is what you will upload to your auditor's portal.
It needs to be complete, organized, and clearly labeled.
Let me show you the exact structure.
soc2-evidence forward slash YYYY-MM-DD.
Inside that, a controls folder.
With files CC6.1-api-keys dot json.
CC6.6-encryption dot json.
CC6.7-tls-cert dot json.
CC7.1-uptime dot json.
CC7.2-alerts dot json.
CC7.4-backups dot json.
CC8.1-changes dot json.
And CC9.2-vendors dot json.
A policies folder with security-policy dot pdf.
incident-response dot pdf.
change-management dot pdf.
and vendor-management dot pdf.
A runbooks folder with incident-response dot md.
backup-restore dot md.
and on-call dot md.
And a README dot md.
Now create the assembly script.
In scripts forward slash assemble-evidence dot sh.
Set DATE to today's date.
Set EVIDENCE_DIR to soc2-evidence forward slash DATE.
Create the directory structure with mkdir dash p.
Then collect all control evidence.
Kubectl get secrets in the financial-rag namespace to YAML.
Output to controls forward slash CC6.1-secrets dot yaml.
Aws rds describe-db-instances for financial-rag-prod.
Output to controls forward slash CC6.6-rds dot json.
Kubectl get ingress in the financial-rag namespace to YAML.
Output to controls forward slash CC6.7-ingress dot yaml.
Curl to Prometheus query for up metric.
Output to controls forward slash CC7.1-metrics dot json.
Kubectl get prometheusrules across all namespaces to YAML.
Output to controls forward slash CC7.2-alerts dot yaml.
Velero backup get in JSON format.
Output to controls forward slash CC7.4-backups dot json.
Gh api to get pull requests.
Output to controls forward slash CC8.1-prs dot json.
Then generate a summary README dot md.
Include a table with each control and its status.
Then run a validation check.
For each control, verify the file exists and is non-empty.
If any control missing evidence, print a red X and exit with error.
If all present, print green check marks
and say evidence package assembled.
Your final lab exercise is to assemble a complete evidence package
using the script I provided.
Run it, then review each file to ensure it contains valid evidence.
Create a README summarizing what is included and any gaps.
Once you have your evidence package, you are ready to engage an auditor
for your Type I audit.
Key takeaways for Phase one.
The five Trust Service Criteria and how they apply to RAG systems.
Security, Availability, Processing Integrity, Confidentiality, Privacy.
System boundary definition.
What to include, what to exclude, and how to document trust boundaries.
Control selection and mapping.
Choosing the right controls and mapping them to code.
Automated evidence collection.
Daily pipelines that prove controls are working.
Type I versus Type II.
Design versus operating effectiveness, timelines, and costs.
Auditor walkthrough preparation.
The five questions you will be asked and how to answer them.
Remediation planning. Closing gaps before the audit.
Evidence package assembly.
The final deliverable your auditor will review.
This is the foundation.
Everything in the remaining eight phases builds on this.
In Phase two, we will dive deep into cryptographic controls.
You will learn to implement AWS KMS, RDS encryption, S3 SSE-KMS,
TLS one point three, certificate management with cert-manager.
And encryption for pgvector embeddings.
Plus how to collect evidence that satisfies CC6.6 and CC6.7.
Continue to Phase two when you are ready.
---
**End of Phase 1 SRT**
**Total lines:** 255
**Duration:** ~2 hours (14 minutes per line average)
Shall I continue with **Phase 2**?