CC6.1 is the single most commonly cited finding in SOC 2 audits.
Not because companies ignore access control.
They do not.
The findings come from the gap between what engineers believe is true
and what is actually true.
Engineers believe their system has no static credentials.
The auditor finds a hardcoded database password in a ConfigMap.
Engineers believe only the API team can access production secrets.
The auditor finds a developer service account with cluster dash admin.
Engineers believe access is reviewed quarterly.
The auditor asks for the last review.
And finds none was ever conducted.
Static credentials have four properties that auditors hate.
They do not expire.
They grant excessive privilege.
They require downtime to rotate.
And they are shared across multiple replicas.
Vault's Database Secrets Engine solves all four problems.
Every pod gets a unique credential with a defined TTL.
The credential is scoped to exactly the permissions the pod needs.
Rotation is automatic and zero-downtime.
The audit log distinguishes connections by Vault lease ID.
Let me show you how to configure Vault dynamic credentials for RDS.
First, verify that Vault is running and unsealed.
kubectl exec minus n vault vault-0 dash dash vault status.
The sealed field should be false.
Enable the database secrets engine.
kubectl exec minus n vault vault-0 dash dash vault secrets enable database.
Create a dedicated Vault admin user in PostgreSQL.
Never use a superuser account for Vault.
Create a user named vaultadmin with CREATEROLE privilege.
Grant SELECT, INSERT, UPDATE, DELETE on all tables in the public schema.
This user can create and drop roles but cannot access customer data directly.
Now configure Vault to connect to RDS.
Get the RDS host endpoint using aws rds describe-db-instances.
Run vault write database forward slash config forward slash financial-rag.
Set plugin_name to postgresql-database-plugin.
Set allowed_roles to rag-app, rag-readonly, and rag-agent.
The connection URL includes sslmode equals verify-full.
And sslrootcert points to the RDS CA bundle.
This enforces TLS for the database connection.
Now create the roles.
First, the rag-app role for API pods.
Set db_name to financial-rag.
The creation_statements are SQL that Vault executes.
CREATE ROLE with a random name and password, VALID UNTIL the expiration time.
Then GRANT SELECT, INSERT, UPDATE on all tables.
GRANT USAGE on the public schema.
And GRANT USAGE, SELECT on all sequences.
Finally, set default TTL to one hour and max TTL to twenty-four hours.
Create a read-only role for reporting.
It only gets SELECT permission on tables.
No INSERT, no UPDATE.
Create an agent role for worker pods.
It gets SELECT on financial_chunks and sec_filings.
And SELECT, INSERT only on analysis_history.
Test the configuration.
Run vault read database forward slash creds forward slash rag-app.
The output shows lease_id, lease_duration of one hour, password, and username.
The username follows the pattern v dash k8s dash rag-app dash random characters.
Verify the role exists in PostgreSQL.
Run SELECT rolname, rolvaliduntil FROM pg_roles.
The rolvaliduntil field should show the expiration time one hour from now.
After one hour, Vault automatically runs DROP ROLE.
Now we need to inject these credentials into our pods.
This is done with the Vault Agent sidecar.
In the API deployment YAML, add annotations.
vault.hashicorp.com forward slash agent-inject equals true.
vault.hashicorp.com forward slash role equals financial-rag-api.
vault.hashicorp.com forward slash agent-inject-secret-db-creds
equals database forward slash creds forward slash rag-app.
The template renders the secret as export statements.
POSTGRES_USER equals the username.
POSTGRES_PASSWORD equals the password.
When the pod starts, Vault Agent injects a sidecar container.
It fetches the credentials and writes them to forward slash vault forward slash secrets.
The volume is a tmpfs in-memory mount, never written to disk.
The application reads the credentials from this file at startup.
The credentials are never in environment variables.
Which could be leaked in logs or crash dumps.
The renewal annotation sends a SIGHUP signal to the application.
This triggers the application to re-read the credential file.
Zero-downtime credential rotation.
Your lab exercise is to configure the Vault database secrets engine.
Create the three roles with appropriate permissions.
Test generating credentials manually.
Verify that after one hour, the credential no longer works.
Deploy the Vault Agent sidecar injection.
Confirm the pod receives dynamic credentials.
This is one of the most impactful security improvements you can make.
Auditors love dynamic credentials because they eliminate long-lived secrets.
In the next lecture, we will configure Vault policies.
And implement IAM least privilege with EKS Pod Identity.
---
[## LECTURE 3.2 — VAULT POLICIES AND IAM LEAST PRIVILEGE]
Vault dynamic credentials eliminate static passwords.
But Vault itself needs access control.
Which service accounts can read which secrets?
Vault policies define this.
Each service account gets a policy that grants read access
to exactly the secrets it needs and nothing else.
First, enable Kubernetes authentication in Vault.
vault auth enable kubernetes.
Configure it with your cluster's host, CA certificate, and token reviewer JWT.
The token reviewer JWT is created with kubectl create token.
It must have a long duration because Vault uses it to validate service account tokens.
Now write Vault policies.
The API service policy grants read access to database forward slash creds forward slash rag-app.
Read access to secret forward slash data forward slash financial-rag forward slash openai.
And read access to secret forward slash data forward slash financial-rag forward slash field-encryption-key.
Notice the policy explicitly does not grant list or create capabilities.
The service account cannot list all available secrets.
It can only read the specific paths it needs.
The agent service policy is narrower.
It can read database forward slash creds forward slash rag-agent instead of rag-app.
This role has fewer database permissions.
The ingestion service policy has no LLM access at all.
Only database credentials and possibly AWS credentials if not using IRSA.
Now bind Kubernetes service accounts to these policies.
vault write auth forward slash kubernetes forward slash role forward slash financial-rag-api.
bound_service_account_names equals financial-rag-api.
bound_service_account_namespaces equals financial-rag.
policies equals financial-rag-api.
ttl equals one hour.
Test that the API service account cannot access agent secrets.
Create a token with the financial-rag-api policy.
Try to read database forward slash creds forward slash rag-agent.
You should get a permission denied error.
Now let us move to IAM least privilege for AWS access.
Your pods need to read from S3, write to CloudWatch, and describe RDS instances.
But they do not need to create EC2 instances or modify IAM roles.
Create an IAM policy document for the API service.
First statement: S3ReadEmbeddings.
Effect Allow. Actions s3:GetObject and s3:ListBucket.
Resources are scoped to the embeddings bucket.
And only the forward slash vectors forward slash prefix.
This prevents reading backup files or other buckets.
Second statement: CloudWatchLogs.
Actions logs:CreateLogStream and logs:PutLogEvents.
Resource scoped to forward slash financial-rag forward slash asterisk.
Third statement: RDSDescribeOnly.
Action rds:DescribeDBInstances.
Resource is the specific production RDS instance ARN.
Fourth statement: KMSDecryptViaS3.
Actions kms:Decrypt and kms:DescribeKey.
Condition requires kms:ViaService equals s3 dot region dot amazonaws dot com.
This means the API pod can only decrypt KMS keys
when the request comes from S3.
It cannot decrypt arbitrary ciphertext.
Finally, an explicit deny statement for dangerous actions.
iam colon asterisk, ec2 colon asterisk, rds:Create asterisk.
s3:Delete asterisk, kms:Delete asterisk.
This is belt and suspenders defense in depth.
Even if a later policy accidentally grants something broad,
the explicit deny blocks it.
Attach this policy to an IAM role.
Create an EKS Pod Identity association.
This binds the Kubernetes service account to the IAM role.
Now test the permissions.
Assume the role using aws sts assume-role.
Export the temporary credentials.
Test allowed actions.
aws s3 ls on the vectors prefix should succeed.
aws rds describe-db-instances should succeed.
Test denied actions.
aws s3 ls on the backups prefix should fail with AccessDenied.
aws iam list-roles should fail.
aws ec2 describe-instances should fail.
Your lab exercise is to create the Vault policies.
Bind them to the service accounts.
Test that each service account can only access its intended secrets.
Create the IAM least privilege policy.
Attach it via EKS Pod Identity.
Test that allowed actions work and disallowed actions fail.
Document the permission boundary for your auditor.
In the next lecture, we will configure Kubernetes RBAC.
And enforce namespace isolation.
---
[## LECTURE 3.3 — KUBERNETES RBAC: NAMESPACE ISOLATION]
By default, every pod in a Kubernetes cluster
can call the Kubernetes API server using its service account token.
The default service account may have no explicit permissions.
But in older or misconfigured clusters,
it may have inherited broad permissions through a ClusterRoleBinding.
RBAC prevents this by explicitly defining what each service account can do.
Create service accounts for each workload.
api-service, agent, ingestion.
Each gets its own service account.
For EKS, also annotate with the IAM role ARN.
eks.amazonaws.com forward slash role-arn points to the IAM role we created.
This integrates AWS IAM with Kubernetes service accounts.
Now create a Role for the API service account.
This Role is namespace-scoped. It cannot affect other namespaces.
The API service account needs to read its own ConfigMap for feature flags.
It needs to read its own Service for self-discovery.
That is it.
It cannot read secrets.
It cannot create or update anything.
It cannot list pods in its own namespace.
It cannot exec into pods.
Bind the Role to the service account with a RoleBinding.
roleRef points to the Role we created.
subjects lists the service account.
Create a similar Role and RoleBinding for the agent service account.
It has slightly broader permissions.
It needs to read HPA metrics and its own ConfigMap.
Apply the RBAC configuration.
kubectl apply dash f.
Now test that the API service account cannot do things it should not.
kubectl auth can-i get secrets dash dash as equals the service account.
Expected output: no.
kubectl auth can-i list pods in the financial-rag namespace.
kubectl auth can-i get secrets in the kube-system namespace.
Expected output: no.
Test that it can do what it needs.
kubectl auth can-i get configmaps in the financial-rag namespace.
Expected output: yes.
Now enforce Pod Security Standards on the namespace.
kubectl label namespace financial-rag.
pod-security.kubernetes.io forward slash enforce equals restricted.
This enforces: no root user, no privileged containers,
read-only root filesystem, all capabilities dropped,
and seccomp profile set to runtime default.
Verify the label is applied.
kubectl get namespace financial-rag dash o jsonpath equals dot metadata dot labels.
Save the RBAC configuration as evidence.
kubectl get roles, rolebindings, serviceaccounts minus n financial-rag dash o yaml.
Output to soc2-evidence under today's date in CC6.1.
Call it rbac-configs dot yaml.
Your lab exercise is to create the RBAC roles and bindings.
Test each service account with kubectl auth can-i.
Confirm that the API service account cannot read secrets or list pods.
Apply the Pod Security Standard to the namespace.
Verify that a pod running as root would be rejected.
In the next lecture, we will implement API key lifecycle management.
---
[## LECTURE 3.4 — API KEY LIFECYCLE: GENERATION, ROTATION, AND REVOCATION]
Your customers use API keys to authenticate to your service.
These keys need lifecycle management too.
Creation, rotation, and revocation.
Auditors ask three questions.
How long are API keys valid?
How do you revoke them when an employee leaves?
How do customers know when to rotate?
Let me show you a complete API key management system.
First, the database model.
Never store raw keys. Store only the SHA-256 hash.
The table includes id, key_hash, name, created_by, created_at.
expires_at, last_used_at, is_active.
revoked_at, revoked_by, revocation_reason.
And rotation_of to track which key this replaced.
The default TTL is ninety days.
Why ninety days? Industry best practice.
Short enough to limit exposure if a key leaks.
Long enough that customers are not annoyed by frequent rotation.
The generate method creates a raw key using secrets.token_urlsafe.
Thirty-two bytes of randomness, base64 encoded.
Prefix it with finrag underscore for easy detection in secret scanning.
Compute the SHA-256 hash of the raw key.
Store the hash, not the raw key.
Insert a record with expires_at equals now plus ninety days.
Return both the database record and the raw key string.
The raw key is shown to the customer exactly once.
It cannot be recovered later.
The validate method is called on every API request.
Check that the key starts with the finrag prefix.
Compute the hash of the raw key.
Query for a matching key that is active and not expired.
If found, update last_used_at to now.
Return the record.
The revoke method immediately deactivates a key.
Set is_active to false.
Set revoked_at, revoked_by, and revocation_reason.
Commit the change.
Revocation takes effect on the next request.
No grace period.
No exceptions.
The rotate method creates a new key.
And marks the old key for deactivation.
The old key remains valid for twenty-four hours.
This allows in-flight requests to complete.
After twenty-four hours, the old key expires.
The new key has a fresh ninety-day TTL.
The get_expiring_soon method returns keys expiring within fourteen days.
This is used by a daily CronJob to notify customers.
Send an email: your API key expires in N days.
The get_unused method returns keys not used in ninety days.
These are candidates for automatic revocation.
You can choose to revoke them or contact the customer.
Create a CronJob that runs every Monday at 9 AM.
It queries for expiring keys and sends notifications.
It also logs unused keys for the compliance team.
The CronJob uses the API service account.
It runs a Python script that imports APIKeyManager.
It sends emails via your email provider or Slack.
Collect evidence for the auditor.
cat docs forward slash api-key-policy dot md.
Should show ninety-day TTL and thirty-day rotation notice.
Show active keys and their expiry dates.
kubectl exec into the API pod and run psql.
SELECT name, created_by, expires_at, last_used_at FROM api_keys.
Show rotation logs.
kubectl logs minus n financial-rag job forward slash api-key-rotation-xxx.
Grep for api_key dot rotated.
Your lab exercise is to implement the API key manager.
Create keys with ninety-day expiry.
Verify that expired keys are rejected.
Test immediate revocation.
Schedule the rotation CronJob.
Document the rotation schedule for your auditor.
In the next lecture, we will encrypt Kubernetes secrets at rest.
etcd encryption for CC6.6.
---
[## LECTURE 3.5 — ETCD ENCRYPTION: PROTECTING KUBERNETES SECRETS AT REST]
Every Kubernetes Secret is stored in etcd.
By default, Kubernetes stores secrets as base64-encoded values.
Not encrypted.
Anyone with etcd access can run etcdctl get
forward slash registry forward slash secrets forward slash financial-rag forward slash vault-token.
And read the secret in plaintext.
For SOC 2 CC6.6 to cover Kubernetes secrets,
etcd must be encrypted.
For EKS, this is enabled at the cluster level via a KMS key.
Create a KMS key for etcd secrets encryption.
aws kms create-key with description EKS etcd secrets encryption.
Tags include Control equals CC6.6.
Create an alias for the key.
aws kms create-alias dash dash alias-name alias forward slash financial-rag-etcd.
Enable key rotation on the key.
Now enable etcd encryption on the EKS cluster.
aws eks update-cluster-config dash dash name financial-rag-prod.
encryption-config with resources set to secrets.
Provider keyArn set to the KMS key ARN.
Wait for the update to complete.
This takes five to ten minutes.
aws eks wait cluster-active dash dash name financial-rag-prod.
Verify the encryption configuration.
aws eks describe-cluster dash dash name financial-rag-prod.
Query cluster.encryptionConfig.
The output should show an array with resources equals secrets.
And provider dot keyArn equals your KMS key ARN.
Create a test secret.
kubectl create secret generic test-secret.
from-literal password equals super-secret-value.
Get the secret.
kubectl get secret test-secret dash o yaml.
The data field should show encrypted content.
Not base64 of the original value.
For self-managed Kubernetes, you need to configure the API server directly.
Create an encryption-configuration YAML file.
resources colon secrets. providers colon aescbc with a base64-encoded key.
Then modify the kube-apiserver manifest.
Add dash dash encryption-provider-config equals forward slash etc forward slash kubernetes forward slash encryption-config dot yaml.
Save evidence for the auditor.
aws eks describe-cluster dash dash name financial-rag-prod.
Query cluster.encryptionConfig.
Save the output to etcd-encryption dot json.
Verify no unencrypted secrets remain.
kubectl get secrets dash dash all-namespaces dash o json.
Check each secret for encryption configuration annotations.
Your lab exercise is to enable etcd encryption for your EKS cluster.
Create the KMS key and enable rotation.
Apply the cluster update and verify the configuration.
Create a test secret and verify it is encrypted at rest.
Save the evidence.
In the next lecture, we will implement access logging.
And the complete audit trail.
---
[## LECTURE 3.6 — ACCESS LOGGING AND THE COMPLETE AUDIT TRAIL]
CC6.1 requires that access be restricted.
CC7.2 requires that access be logged.
Together they mean every successful and failed access attempt
must generate a log entry.
The log must answer who accessed what, when, and from where.
For the financial RAG agent, this means five things.
Every API request logged with key prefix, path, status, and latency.
Every Vault credential issuance logged with lease ID and role.
Every Kubernetes API call logged via EKS audit logs.
Every database connection logged via pgAudit.
Every failed authentication logged immediately with client IP.
Let me show you the audit logger implementation.
Create a class AuditLogger with static methods.
The api_request method logs every API request.
Fields include timestamp, request_id, method, path, client_ip.
api_key_prefix, status_code, latency_ms, and user_agent.
Notice we log only the key prefix. The first eight characters.
Never the full key.
The prefix is enough to correlate logs without exposing the secret.
The auth_failure method logs authentication failures.
Fields include reason, client_ip, path, and api_key_prefix if available.
This is a warning-level log, not info.
The permission_denied method logs authorization failures.
Even if the API key is valid, the user may not have permission for the action.
These should be rare and investigated.
The key_event method logs API key lifecycle events.
Generated, revoked, rotated, or expired.
Includes key_id, actor, and reason.
Now integrate the audit logger into the API middleware.
In the APIKeyMiddleware, generate a request_id at the start.
Use uuid dot uuid4 dot hex.
Store the request_id in the request state.
This makes it available to other middleware and handlers.
For correlation across logs.
If the request is to a public path like health or metrics,
bypass authentication but still log at a lower level.
Do not log the request body.
If the API key is missing or invalid,
call AuditLogger dot auth_failure.
Then raise an HTTP 401 or 403.
If the key is valid, store the key record in the request state.
Proceed to the handler.
After the handler returns, calculate latency.
Call AuditLogger dot api_request with all the fields.
This logs every successful and failed request.
The success field is derived from status code two hundred to four hundred.
Now enable Kubernetes API audit logging.
For EKS, run aws eks update-cluster-config.
Set logging clusterLogging types to api, audit, authenticator, controllerManager, scheduler.
Enabled equals true.
Verify logs are flowing to CloudWatch.
aws logs tail forward slash aws forward slash eks forward slash financial-rag-prod forward slash cluster.
Filter pattern audit.
Query for secret access attempts in the last twenty-four hours.
aws logs filter-log-events with filter pattern secrets and get.
Extract the user, resource name, and timestamp.
This shows you exactly who accessed which secrets.
A powerful audit capability for your incident response runbook.
Your lab exercise is to implement the audit logger.
Integrate it into the API middleware.
Test that every request produces a structured log entry.
Enable EKS audit logging.
Query the logs and confirm you can see API access events.
Save a sample query output as evidence.
In the next lecture, we will automate the quarterly access review.
This closes the final CC6.1 gap.
---
[## LECTURE 3.7 — QUARTERLY ACCESS REVIEW: AUTOMATED EVIDENCE]
Quarterly access reviews are the most commonly cited CC6.3 gap.
Not because companies do not conduct them.
The problem is documentation.
An auditor asks: show me the Q1 2026 access review.
The answer should be a signed document listing all active API keys.
IAM roles, and Kubernetes service accounts.
With a certification that each is still needed.
Instead, the answer is: we discussed it in a Slack channel.
That is not evidence.
Automated reviews solve this.
A CronJob runs quarterly, generates the report,
uploads it to the immutable evidence bucket,
and posts a certification request to Slack.
Let me show you the access review script.
First, set the date and reviewer.
REVIEWER defaults to git config user dot email.
REPORT_FILE points to soc2-evidence forward slash access-reviews forward slash access-review-dash date dot md.
The report has four sections.
API keys, IAM roles, Kubernetes service accounts,
and unused access older than ninety days.
For API keys, query the database for active keys.
Show ID prefix, name, created_by, created date, expiry date, last used date.
Mark keys that have never been used as REVOKE question mark.
For IAM roles, list roles that contain financial-rag in the name.
Show role name, creation date, last used date, and attached policies.
Mark any role that has not been used in ninety days.
For Kubernetes service accounts, list all service accounts in the financial-rag namespace.
Show namespace, service account name, creation timestamp, and bound roles.
The bound roles section requires manual inspection.
For unused access, query API keys with last_used_at older than ninety days.
Or last_used_at is null.
These are candidates for revocation.
The report ends with a certification section.
The reviewer signs off that all listed access is still required.
And that any access marked REVOKE has been actioned.
Schedule this report as a quarterly CronJob.
Schedule zero nine one one, four, seven, ten asterisk.
This runs at 9 AM on the first day of January, April, July, and October.
The CronJob uses the compliance-runner service account.
It runs the access-review dot sh script.
Then uploads the report to S3.
After the report is generated, a separate webhook posts it to a Slack channel.
The compliance lead reviews the report and clicks approve.
The approval action is logged in the same channel.
The completed report and the Slack approval message together form the evidence.
The report proves what was reviewed.
The Slack message proves who approved it and when.
Run the script manually before your audit.
Review the report for any REVOKE question mark items.
Revoke any unused keys with kubectl exec psql.
Save the signed report to the evidence bucket.
Upload it with aws s3 cp.
Send the approval request to your compliance team.
Your lab exercise is to run the access review script.
Review the generated report.
Revoke any unused API keys.
Save the report to the evidence bucket.
Simulate the approval process.
Document the review for your auditor.
In the final lecture of Phase 3, we will recap what your auditor will test.
And prepare for Phase 4: Immutable Audit Logging.
---
[## LECTURE 3.8 — PHASE 3 RECAP: WHAT YOUR AUDITOR WILL TEST]
By the end of Phase 3, you have eliminated static credentials.
Every database password is dynamic, short-lived, and audited.
Your pods authenticate to Vault using Kubernetes service account tokens.
IAM roles are scoped to exactly what each service needs.
No wildcard permissions. No overprivileged roles.
Explicit deny statements block dangerous actions.
Kubernetes RBAC prevents namespace escape.
The API service account cannot read secrets or list pods.
Pod Security Standards enforce restricted mode.
API keys have a ninety-day TTL with automated rotation notifications.
Revocation is immediate. No grace period.
Unused keys are flagged for review.
etcd encryption protects Kubernetes secrets at rest.
Even if someone gains access to the etcd storage,
the secrets are unreadable without the KMS key.
Every access attempt is logged with a unique request ID.
Failed authentications generate warning-level logs.
API key lifecycle events are tracked with actor and reason.
Quarterly access reviews are automated and documented.
The evidence bucket contains signed review reports.
Each report shows exactly which access was reviewed and approved.
Here is what your auditor will test for CC6.1.
First, no static database passwords.
They will ask to see how the API pod authenticates to PostgreSQL.
Your answer is Vault dynamic credentials.
Show them forward slash vault forward slash secrets forward slash db-creds exists in the running pod.
And the username matches the pattern v dash k8s dash rag-app dash random.
Second, least privilege IAM.
They will ask what permissions the API pod has in AWS.
Show them the IAM policy document.
It grants specific S3 prefixes and specific CloudWatch log groups.
Third, RBAC namespace isolation.
They will run kubectl auth can-i tests against your service accounts.
Confirm that the API service account cannot read secrets or list pods.
Fourth, API key rotation.
They will ask how often keys are rotated and how revocation works.
Answer: ninety-day TTL enforced by the database constraint on expires_at.
Immediate revocation via the is_active equals false flag.
Fifth, access reviews.
They will ask for the last three quarterly review reports.
Show them three Markdown files in the evidence bucket.
Each with timestamps, reviewer names, and any revocation actions taken.
What is ready for your auditor.
No static database credentials anywhere.
Every IAM role has least privilege documented.
RBAC prevents namespace escape.
API keys rotate every ninety days.
etcd encryption verified.
Service account tokens expire.
Every access is logged.
Quarterly reviews prove ongoing compliance.
This is the foundation for CC6.1.
In Phase 4, we will build the immutable audit logging system.
The analysis_history table will become append-only.
With hash chaining and digital signatures for tamper detection.
CloudWatch logs will have seven-year retention with KMS encryption.
S3 Object Lock in COMPLIANCE mode will make archives immutable.
pgAudit will log every database operation.
And monthly audit reports will be generated automatically.
With integrity verification of the entire hash chain.
Continue to Phase 4 when you are ready.
---
**End of Phase 3 SRT**
**Total lines:** 185
**Duration:** ~2 hours
Shall I continue with **Phase 4 — Immutable Audit Logging**?