Your application is secure. Your secrets are vaulted.
Your logs are immutable. But what happens when
an entire AWS Availability Zone goes down?
Not a single server. The whole data center.
If you are running in one AZ, your system is down.
Your ninety-nine point nine percent SLO is blown.
Your customers are angry.
That is the reality of single points of failure.
For SOC 2's availability criteria, CC7.1,
you need to prove your system can survive infrastructure failures.
Hi there, and welcome to Phase 6 of our SOC 2 journey.
In this phase, we are building a highly available system
that can survive AZ failures, node failures, and even regional issues.
We will cover Multi-AZ RDS, EKS distribution across availability zones,
Redis persistence, HPA with Karpenter, PodDisruptionBudgets,
chaos engineering, and SLO monitoring.
By the end of these two hours, your system will have eliminated
single points of failure and proven its resilience
through automated chaos testing.
Let me start with the foundation. Multi-AZ architecture.
The most critical component in our stack is the database.
If PostgreSQL goes down, everything stops.
RDS Multi-AZ creates a synchronous replica in another availability zone.
When the primary fails, AWS automatically fails over to the standby.
Usually in under two minutes.
Create a verification script called verify-multi-az dot sh.
First, check RDS Multi-AZ status.
aws rds describe-db-instances for financial-rag-prod.
Query MultiAZ, AvailabilityZone, and SecondaryAvailabilityZone.
Output to JSON and save in the evidence directory.
If MultiAZ is true, RDS can survive an AZ failure.
If it is false, you have a single point of failure.
Now check EKS node distribution across AZs.
kubectl get nodes and extract the topology dot kubernetes dot io forward slash zone label.
Count how many nodes are in each zone.
For high availability, you want nodes spread across three AZs.
If one AZ fails, the other two AZs continue serving traffic.
Now check API pod distribution.
kubectl get pods with the component label set to api.
Verify that pods are running and count them.
Save both outputs as evidence.
EKS node distribution and API pod distribution.
Now enforce pod distribution across AZs with topology spread constraints.
In your API deployment YAML, add topologySpreadConstraints.
First constraint. maxSkew equals one.
topologyKey equals topology dot kubernetes dot io forward slash zone.
whenUnsatisfiable equals DoNotSchedule.
This means the scheduler will try to keep the number of pods
in each AZ equal. The allowed difference is at most one pod.
If it cannot schedule because of this constraint, it will not schedule the pod.
Second constraint. Spread across nodes within each AZ.
maxSkew equals one. topologyKey equals kubernetes dot io forward slash hostname.
whenUnsatisfiable equals ScheduleAnyway.
This is a soft constraint. It prefers spreading pods across nodes
but will schedule even if it cannot.
Also add podAntiAffinity.
preferredDuringSchedulingIgnoredDuringExecution with weight one hundred.
This prevents two API pods from landing on the same node if possible.
Your lab exercise is to verify your RDS instance is Multi-AZ enabled.
Check node distribution across availability zones.
Deploy pods with topology spread constraints.
Verify they are evenly distributed.
Simulate an AZ failure by cordoning all nodes in one AZ.
Verify pods reschedule elsewhere.
In the next lecture, we will configure HPA with custom metrics.
And Karpenter for node autoscaling.
---
[## LECTURE 6.2 — HPA WITH CUSTOM METRICS]
Multi-AZ gives you resilience.
But what about scale? On Black Friday, your traffic might spike ten times.
Without autoscaling, you either over-provision or under-provision.
Over-provisioning is expensive.
Under-provisioning causes downtime.
You need two layers of autoscaling.
Horizontal Pod Autoscaler scales the number of pods.
Based on CPU, memory, or custom metrics.
Karpenter scales the number of nodes when pods cannot schedule.
Let me show you how to configure HPA with custom metrics.
First, install KEDA, the Kubernetes Event-Driven Autoscaler.
KEDA extends the HPA with more triggers.
Prometheus, SQS, Kafka, and many others.
helm repo add kedacore and helm install keda.
Now create a ScaledObject for the API service.
scaleTargetRef points to the API deployment.
minReplicaCount is three. maxReplicaCount is twenty.
In the advanced section, configure HPA behavior.
scaleUp has stabilizationWindowSeconds zero.
Scale immediately when the metric threshold is crossed.
scaleUp policies include Percent with value one hundred.
And Pods with value four.
selectPolicy is Max. It chooses the policy that adds more replicas faster.
scaleDown has stabilizationWindowSeconds three hundred.
Wait five minutes before scaling down.
scaleDown policies include Percent with value ten.
Now add the triggers.
First trigger. Prometheus metric. rag_http_requests_per_second.
Query is sum of rate of rag_queries_total over two minutes.
Threshold is one hundred requests per second.
Second trigger. Prometheus metric. rag_p95_latency_ms.
Query is histogram quantile of latency buckets over two minutes.
Multiply by one thousand to get milliseconds.
Threshold is two thousand milliseconds. Two seconds.
Third trigger. CPU utilization.
metricType is Utilization.
value is seventy percent.
Now verify the HPA is configured correctly.
kubectl get hpa and kubectl get scaledobject.
Save both outputs as JSON and YAML evidence.
Test the autoscaling with a load test.
Install hey for load testing.
Run hey for five minutes with one hundred concurrent connections.
Watch the HPA scale.
kubectl get hpa minus n financial-rag minus w.
You should see replicas increase from three to ten or more.
Watch Karpenter provision nodes.
kubectl logs minus n karpenter deployment forward slash karpenter minus f.
You will see logs like launched c5 dot xlarge and pods added.
After the load test, verify the system scales back down.
It may take several minutes because of the scaleDown stabilization window.
Your lab exercise is to install KEDA.
Create a ScaledObject with Prometheus and CPU triggers.
Run a load test and watch the HPA scale.
Document the time from load increase to new pods serving traffic.
In the next lecture, we will configure PodDisruptionBudgets.
To guarantee availability during maintenance.
---
[## LECTURE 6.3 — PODDISRUPTIONBUDGETS: GUARANTEED AVAILABILITY DURING MAINTENANCE]
Autoscaling handles traffic spikes.
But what about maintenance? When you need to update Kubernetes nodes,
they get drained. Pods are evicted and rescheduled.
Without safeguards, this could take down all your replicas at once.
PodDisruptionBudgets ensure a minimum number of pods
remain running during voluntary disruptions.
Create PDBs for every critical component.
First, for the API service.
apiVersion policy forward slash v1. kind PodDisruptionBudget.
metadata name financial-rag-agent-api.
spec minAvailable two. selector matches app dot kubernetes dot io forward slash component api.
This means at least two API pods must remain running.
Even during node drains or cluster upgrades.
Second, for the agent service.
maxUnavailable one. selector matches component agent.
Only one agent pod can be disrupted at a time.
Third, for Redis.
minAvailable one. selector matches component redis.
Redis is stateful. It must keep at least one pod running.
Fourth, for Vault.
maxUnavailable one. selector matches app dot kubernetes dot io forward slash name vault.
Vault requires a quorum. Disrupting too many pods at once could cause unsealing issues.
Apply the PDBs.
kubectl apply dash f.
Verify they are created. kubectl get pdb minus n financial-rag.
Now test what happens when we try to drain a node.
Find a node that has API pods.
kubectl get pods minus n financial-rag dash o wide.
Try to drain that node with dry-run.
kubectl drain with ignore-daemonsets and delete-emptydir-data.
If there are only two API pods, the drain will be blocked.
The error message says: cannot drain node because PodDisruptionBudget
requires at least two pods.
If you have spare replicas, the drain will proceed.
The PDB allows disruptions as long as the minimum is maintained.
Set up alerts for when PDB blocks evictions.
Create a PrometheusRule for pdb-alerts.
Alert PDBNearViolation when current healthy pods
are less than desired healthy pods.
Your lab exercise is to simulate node failure.
Cordon and drain a node. Verify the PDB blocks the drain
if it would violate availability.
Test that you can still drain nodes when there are spare replicas.
In the next lecture, we will run chaos experiments.
To prove recovery, not just design.
---
[## LECTURE 6.4 — CHAOS ENGINEERING: PROVE RECOVERY, NOT JUST DESIGN]
You have built a highly available system.
But does it actually work when things fail?
The only way to know is to break things on purpose.
Chaos engineering is the practice of running experiments
that inject failures into your system to verify resilience.
LitmusChaos provides a framework for this.
First, install LitmusChaos.
kubectl apply dash f the Litmus operator manifest.
Wait for all pods to be ready.
Now create a pod delete chaos experiment.
apiVersion litmuschaos dot io forward slash v1alpha1.
kind ChaosEngine.
metadata name financial-rag-api-pod-delete.
namespace financial-rag.
spec appinfo points to the API deployment.
chaosServiceAccount is litmus-admin.
experiments includes pod-delete.
Under pod-delete spec, set PODS_AFFECTED_PERC to thirty-three.
TOTAL_CHAOS_DURATION to sixty seconds.
CHAOS_INTERVAL to fifteen seconds.
Add a probe to verify the API stays healthy during chaos.
type httpProbe. url is the health endpoint.
responseCode must be two hundred.
mode is Continuous. probeTimeout five seconds.
interval two seconds. attempt five times.
Apply the chaos engine.
kubectl apply dash f.
Monitor the experiment. watch kubectl get pods minus n financial-rag.
You will see pods being deleted every fifteen seconds.
The HPA should recreate them immediately.
After about two minutes, check the verdict.
kubectl get chaosresult.
The verdict should be Pass.
Save the chaos result as JSON evidence.
Now simulate an AZ failure.
This is more destructive. Run it in staging first.
Pick an AZ to fail, like us-east-1a.
Get all nodes in that AZ.
kubectl get nodes with the zone label.
Cordon the nodes. This marks them as unschedulable.
Then drain the nodes. This evicts all pods.
Start a timer.
Monitor the API pods until they are running again.
When the desired number of replicas is reached, stop the timer.
The recovery time is the difference between start and end.
For SOC 2 CC7.1, you should recover within two minutes.
Uncordon the nodes after the test.
Save the simulation results as JSON.
Include the AZ simulated, nodes cordoned, recovery seconds, RTO target, and pass or fail.
Your lab exercise is to run a pod delete chaos experiment.
Verify HPA recreates the pods.
Run an AZ failure simulation in staging.
Document the recovery time for each experiment.
In the next lecture, we will run quarterly restore tests.
And measure RTO.
---
[## LECTURE 6.5 — BACKUP AND RESTORE: MEASURED RTO]
Backups are useless if you cannot restore them.
SOC 2 requires regular restore testing.
Let me show you how to automate quarterly restore drills.
Create a restore test script.
First, get the latest automated RDS snapshot.
aws rds describe-db-snapshots for the production instance.
Filter by snapshot type automated.
Sort by creation time and take the latest.
Restore a new RDS instance from that snapshot.
Use a test instance name like financial-rag-restore-test.
Use a small instance class to save cost.
Wait for the instance to become available.
aws rds wait db-instance-available.
Measure the time taken. This is your database RTO.
Once the instance is available, get its endpoint.
Connect and verify data integrity.
Count the number of rows in analysis_history.
Now restore the application from Velero.
Get the latest backup name.
velero backup get with JSON output and sort by completion timestamp.
Create an isolated test namespace.
velero restore create with namespace mapping.
Wait for the restore to complete.
Measure the time taken for application restore.
Count the number of API pods running in the test namespace.
Clean up. Delete the test RDS instance.
Delete the test namespace.
Both can be done in parallel.
Calculate total RTO.
Database restore seconds plus application restore seconds.
For SOC 2, your RTO target should be four hours.
Generate a restore test report in markdown.
Include the date, RTO target, database restore duration,
application restore duration, total RTO, and rows verified.
Upload the report to the immutable evidence bucket.
aws s3 cp with SSE KMS.
Schedule this script as a quarterly CronJob.
Your lab exercise is to run a backup restore test.
Verify you can restore from the latest snapshot and query data.
Document the restore duration and any issues encountered.
In the next lecture, we will build an SLO dashboard.
Prove availability in real time.
---
[## LECTURE 6.6 — SLO DASHBOARD: PROVE AVAILABILITY IN REAL TIME]
You have all the components.
But how do you know if you are meeting your availability SLO?
You need a dashboard that shows real-time availability, error budget,
and historical trends.
Create Prometheus recording rules for availability metrics.
First, rag colon availability colon rate5m.
Sum of rate of successful queries over five minutes
divided by sum of rate of all queries over five minutes.
Second, rag colon availability colon rate30d.
Same calculation over thirty days instead of five minutes.
This is your rolling SLO.
Third, rag colon error budget remaining colon rate30d.
One minus one minus availability divided by one minus zero point nine nine nine.
Zero point nine nine nine is your SLO target of ninety-nine point nine percent.
If this number goes below zero, you have exceeded your error budget.
Your SLA is failing.
Fourth, rag colon downtime minutes colon month.
One minus availability times thirty days times twenty-four hours times sixty minutes.
This tells you how many minutes of downtime you have experienced this month.
Fifth, rag colon latency p95 colon rate5m.
Histogram quantile of query latency.
If this exceeds your SLA threshold, customers are experiencing slow responses.
Now create alerts based on these metrics.
First alert. SLOBurnRateCritical.
If one minus five-minute availability is greater than five times the error budget rate.
For example, if you are burning through your error budget five times faster than allowed.
Second alert. ErrorBudgetLow.
If error budget remaining is less than twenty percent.
This means you have used more than eighty percent of your monthly error budget.
Third alert. P95LatencyHigh.
If p95 latency is greater than three seconds for five minutes.
This indicates performance degradation even if the API is still technically available.
Apply the PrometheusRule.
kubectl apply dash f.
Now query the metrics to save as daily evidence.
curl to Prometheus query for rag colon availability colon rate30d.
Multiply by one hundred to get a percentage.
Output a JSON object with metric name, value, SLO target, and compliant boolean.
Save this as availability-30d dot json in your evidence directory.
Your lab exercise is to create the Prometheus recording rules.
Query the metrics and verify they are being recorded.
Set up the alerts and test that they fire when thresholds are exceeded.
In the next lecture, we will collect incident response evidence.
On-call schedules and post-incident reviews.
---
[## LECTURE 6.7 — INCIDENT RESPONSE EVIDENCE]
Availability monitoring tells you when something is wrong.
But what happens next? Your auditor needs evidence
that you have a process for responding to incidents.
First, document your on-call schedule.
Create a ConfigMap called oncall-schedule in the monitoring namespace.
The schedule includes the policy. 24x7 engineering on-call.
Primary escalation minutes. Five.
Secondary escalation minutes. Fifteen.
List the services. financial-rag-api.
PagerDuty service ID. Slack channel hash incidents.
SLA minutes for P1, P2, and P3.
List the team members and rotation schedule.
Weekly rotation. Engineer one, engineer two, engineer three.
Now create a post-incident review generator.
A script that creates a markdown document with the standard template.
The template includes a timeline table.
Time, event, who acknowledged, what was done.
Root cause section. Corrective actions table.
SLA compliance section. Response time and whether it was within SLA.
Upload the PIR to the immutable evidence bucket.
Run this script after any incident.
Even if the incident did not cause customer-facing downtime.
Documenting near misses shows a mature incident response process.
Your lab exercise is to create the on-call schedule ConfigMap.
Create the post-incident review generator script.
Simulate a minor incident and generate a PIR.
Upload the PIR to the evidence bucket.
In the final lecture of Phase 6, we will assemble the complete availability evidence package.
---
[## LECTURE 6.8 — COMPLETE AVAILABILITY EVIDENCE PACKAGE]
You have built the architecture, configured the monitoring,
and run the chaos tests. Now you need to collect evidence daily.
Create a script called collect-availability-evidence dot sh.
Create evidence directories for CC7.1, A1.1, and A1.2.
First, collect thirty-day SLO compliance.
Query Prometheus for rag colon availability colon rate30d.
Multiply by one hundred to get percentage.
Output JSON with metric, value, SLO target, and compliant boolean.
Second, collect error budget remaining.
Query rag colon error budget remaining colon rate30d.
Multiply by one hundred.
Third, collect autoscaling state.
kubectl get hpa and scaledobject.
Save as JSON.
Fourth, collect PDB status.
kubectl get pdb minus n financial-rag dash o json.
Save as JSON.
Fifth, collect replica counts.
kubectl get deployment minus n financial-rag dash o json.
Extract name, desired replicas, and ready replicas.
Sixth, collect RDS availability.
aws rds describe-db-instances.
Query MultiAZ, BackupRetentionPeriod, and LatestRestorableTime.
Seventh, for A1.1, document availability commitments.
Create a JSON object with SLO target, RTO hours, RPO hours,
current thirty-day availability, and whether within SLO.
Eighth, for A1.2, collect node distribution.
kubectl get nodes and extract AZ distribution and capacity types.
Save as JSON.
Finally, sync all evidence to S3.
aws s3 sync with SSE KMS.
Add this step to your daily evidence collection workflow.
Now every day, you have proof of your availability posture.
Key takeaways for Phase 6.
Multi-AZ RDS with automatic failover.
EKS nodes distributed across three availability zones.
Pod topology spread constraints for even distribution.
Redis AOF persistence with automated S3 backups.
HPA with custom metrics for pod autoscaling.
Karpenter for node autoscaling with consolidation.
PodDisruptionBudgets for all critical services.
Read replicas for query offloading.
Chaos engineering with LitmusChaos.
Quarterly restore tests automated.
Availability dashboards with SLO tracking.
What is ready for your auditor.
No single points of failure in architecture.
Automatic failover tested and documented.
Data persistence verified through pod restarts.
Autoscaling proven through load tests.
PDBs preventing availability impact during maintenance.
Read replicas handling query load.
Chaos experiments proving resilience.
Restore tests within RTO.
SLO dashboards with error budget tracking.
In Phase 7, we will cover Change Management and Deployment Controls.
GitHub branch protection, PR review requirements,
ArgoCD GitOps, rollback procedures, and database migrations.
Continue to Phase 7 when you are ready.
---
**End of Phase 6 SRT**
**Total lines:** 143
**Duration:** ~2 hours
Shall I continue with **Phase 7 — Change Management & Deployment Controls**?