Imagine this. Six months after a security incident,
an auditor asks you to prove exactly what data was accessed.
You pull up your logs.
But wait. Someone with database access could have deleted those logs.
Or updated them. How would you know?
That is the problem with mutable audit logs.
For SOC 2, especially for processing integrity and incident response,
you need logs that cannot be changed.
Not by accident. Not by admin. Not by anyone.
Hi there, and welcome to Phase 4 of our SOC 2 journey.
In this phase, we are building an immutable audit logging system
that would satisfy the most demanding auditor.
We will cover append-only table design, hash chaining,
digital signatures, immutable cloud storage,
and automated compliance reporting.
By the end of these two hours, every user interaction
with your RAG system will be permanently recorded,
cryptographically verifiable, and tamper-evident.
Let me start with the foundation. The analysis_history table.
Every time a user asks a question, we create a record.
The record captures everything. The question, the answer,
which agent handled it, how long it took, and any errors.
But here is the key. This table is append-only.
No updates. No deletes. Only inserts.
Let me show you the schema.
In the migration file, we create the analysis_history table.
The table has columns for identity, query content, performance,
session context, privacy-safe user identification,
immutability chain fields, and timestamps.
Notice there is no updated_at column.
This table never updates. Only inserts.
The user_email_hash and ip_hash columns store SHA-256 hashes.
Not raw emails or IP addresses.
This is for privacy. We can identify patterns without exposing PII.
The previous_hash and current_hash columns are for the cryptographic chain.
We will cover those in the next lecture.
The signature and signed_at columns are for digital signatures.
Now let us create indexes for audit queries.
Index on ticker and created_at.
Index on session_id.
Index on agent_type and created_at.
Index on user_email_hash and created_at.
Now the critical part. Enforcing immutability at the database level.
Create a function called enforce_append_only.
This function raises an exception with a clear error message.
It says: operation not permitted on analysis_history.
This table is an immutable audit log. Only INSERT is allowed.
Now create triggers that call this function.
First, a BEFORE UPDATE trigger.
Second, a BEFORE DELETE trigger.
Third, a BEFORE TRUNCATE trigger.
Each trigger executes the enforce_append_only function.
This means no one can update, delete, or truncate the table.
Not your application. Not a database administrator. Not even the table owner.
Let me show you what happens when someone tries to cheat.
If you try to update a record, PostgreSQL returns an error.
Operation UPDATE not permitted on analysis_history.
If you try to delete records older than ninety days,
same error. No deletion allowed.
If you try to truncate the entire table, same error.
Now, how do you handle data retention if you cannot delete?
Two options. Partition by date and drop entire partitions.
Or export to cold storage and drop partitions after seven years.
Here is the partition approach.
Create a partitioned table by month.
Create monthly partitions.
To archive old data, detach the partition, export to S3, then drop it.
Verify that the triggers exist.
Query the information schema for triggers on analysis_history.
You should see three triggers. One for UPDATE, one for DELETE, one for TRUNCATE.
Save the trigger evidence to your evidence bucket.
Run the query and output to analysis-history-triggers dot txt.
Your lab exercise is to create the analysis_history table.
Apply the triggers. Test that INSERT works.
Test that UPDATE, DELETE, and TRUNCATE all fail with clear error messages.
Document the error messages as evidence for your auditor.
In the next lecture, we will add hash chaining and digital signatures.
---
[## LECTURE 4.2 — HASH CHAINING: CRYPTOGRAPHIC TAMPER DETECTION]
Append-only triggers prevent changes through SQL.
But what about a database administrator with direct access to the storage?
Or someone who restores an old backup?
The records could be changed outside the database.
That is where cryptographic tamper detection comes in.
We will implement two layers. Hash chaining and digital signatures.
Hash chaining means each record contains the hash of the previous record.
If anyone changes a record, the chain breaks.
Digital signatures prove the record came from your application, not an attacker.
First, add the columns for tamper detection to the analysis_history table.
previous_hash, current_hash, signature, and signed_at.
Now let me show you the Python code that creates these hashes and signatures.
Create a class AuditChainSigner.
In the init method, load the private key from a PEM file.
If no private key is provided, try to load from Vault.
Add a method compute_record_hash.
This takes a dictionary of record data and returns a SHA-256 hash.
Sort the keys to ensure consistent hash regardless of insertion order.
Use json dot dumps with sort_keys equals true.
Then compute hashlib dot sha256 of the encoded JSON.
Return the hex digest.
Add a method sign_hash.
This takes a record hash and signs it with the private key.
Use RSA-PSS padding with MGF1 and SHA-256.
Return the signature as bytes.
Add a method verify_signature.
This takes a record hash and a signature.
It returns true if the signature is valid, false otherwise.
Now create the AuditChainRepository class.
This manages the hash chain integrity.
Add a method get_last_hash.
Query the most recent record in analysis_history.
Return its current_hash, or None if no records exist.
Add a method prepare_chain_fields.
This is called before inserting a new record.
Get the previous hash from the last record.
Compute the current hash by calling signer dot compute_record_hash.
Add previous_hash and current_hash to the record data.
If a private key is available, sign the current hash and add the signature.
Now add the verification method. verify_chain_integrity.
This method iterates through all records in order.
For each record, verify that previous_hash matches the previous record's current_hash.
If not, log an error and return false.
Recompute the current hash from the record data.
If it does not match the stored current_hash, log an error and return false.
Verify the signature using the public key.
If any signature is invalid, log an error.
Continue verification but note the failure.
Return a report dict with total_records, chain_valid, signatures_valid,
first_broken_at if any, and verification_seconds.
Now generate the signing keys and store them in Vault.
OpenSSL genrsa with 4096 bits for the private key.
Then extract the public key.
Store the private key in Vault at secret forward slash financial-rag forward slash audit-signing-key.
Never store the private key in Git.
Store the public key in Git at security forward slash audit-signing-key-pub dot pem.
The public key is safe to share.
Auditors need it to verify signatures.
Delete the private key from your local disk after storing in Vault.
Now integrate the chain repository into your analysis repository.
When inserting a new record, call prepare_chain_fields first.
Then insert the record with the chain fields populated.
After inserting ten thousand records, here is what the hash chain looks like.
Record one current_hash equals a1b2c3.
Record two previous_hash equals a1b2c3, current_hash equals d4e5f6.
Record three previous_hash equals d4e5f6, current_hash equals g7h8i9.
If someone modifies record two, its current_hash changes.
Then when verifying record three, previous_hash does not match. The chain breaks.
If someone modifies record two and also updates record three's previous_hash to match,
the signature on record two would be invalid.
Because the private key is not available to re-sign.
The private key lives in Vault with strict access controls.
Only the application pod can access it, and only in memory.
Your lab exercise is to insert several audit records.
Verify the hash chain integrity.
Then try to manually modify a record in the database.
Re-run verification. It should fail.
Document the tamper detection as evidence for SOC 2.
In the next lecture, we will configure CloudWatch log groups.
With seven-year retention and deletion protection.
---
[## LECTURE 4.3 — CLOUDWATCH LOG GROUPS WITH 7-YEAR RETENTION]
Your database audit log is one piece.
But what about application logs? API access logs?
Kubernetes audit logs?
They all need to be stored immutably with appropriate retention.
For SOC 2, audit logs typically need seven-year retention.
CloudWatch can do this, but you need to configure it correctly.
First, define your log groups in Terraform.
Create a local map of log group names and retention days.
Audit logs get 2555 days retention. That is seven years.
This includes forward slash financial-rag forward slash audit.
Forward slash financial-rag forward slash api-access.
Forward slash financial-rag forward slash auth.
And forward slash financial-rag forward slash db-audit.
Operational logs get 365 days retention.
This includes forward slash financial-rag forward slash api.
Forward slash financial-rag forward slash agent.
And forward slash financial-rag forward slash ingestion.
The EKS cluster audit log also gets 365 days retention.
Its name is forward slash aws forward slash eks forward slash financial-rag-prod forward slash cluster.
Create each log group using for_each over the local map.
Set retention_in_days and kms_key_id.
Tag the groups with Control equals CC7.5.
Now create an IAM policy that denies log group deletion.
This is critical. A user with logs colon DeleteLogGroup can wipe your audit trail.
The policy explicitly denies DeleteLogGroup, DeleteLogStream, DeleteRetentionPolicy.
Also deny PutRetentionPolicy for groups that already have seven-year retention.
This prevents someone from shortening the retention period.
For the strongest protection, apply this as a Service Control Policy in AWS Organizations.
An SCP applies to all IAM users and roles in the account, including the root user.
Even AWS support cannot override an SCP.
Create the SCP with the same deny statements.
Attach it to your production account.
Now audit log deletion is impossible.
Now configure Fluent Bit to send logs to the right groups.
Create a ConfigMap in the logging namespace.
For API access logs, tail the container logs for the API pod.
Filter for logs containing event_type equals api_request or auth_failure.
Output to the forward slash financial-rag forward slash audit log group.
For agent logs, output to the forward slash financial-rag forward slash agent log group.
One-year retention.
For ingestion logs, output to the forward slash financial-rag forward slash ingestion log group.
Verify the logs are flowing and retention is set correctly.
aws logs describe-log-groups for the forward slash financial-rag prefix.
Query logGroupName and retentionInDays.
Verify KMS encryption on the audit group.
aws logs describe-log-groups for forward slash financial-rag forward slash audit.
Query kmsKeyId. It should return your KMS key ARN.
Test that logs are being written.
aws logs tail forward slash financial-rag forward slash audit dash dash since five minutes.
You should see API request logs appearing.
Save the log group configuration as evidence.
Run the describe command and output to cloudwatch-log-groups dot json.
Your lab exercise is to create the CloudWatch log groups.
Configure retention and KMS encryption.
Apply the SCP to prevent deletion.
Verify that logs are flowing and retention is set correctly.
In the next lecture, we will configure S3 Object Lock.
For truly immutable archive storage.
---
[## LECTURE 4.4 — S3 OBJECT LOCK: TRULY IMMUTABLE ARCHIVE STORAGE]
CloudWatch logs can be protected with SCPs.
But very hard is not the same as mathematically impossible.
S3 Object Lock in COMPLIANCE mode is the gold standard.
Even AWS support, with the account root credentials,
cannot delete or modify a COMPLIANCE-locked object before its retention date.
For SOC 2 Type II, where the auditor is verifying six to twelve months
of operating history, having that history in COMPLIANCE-locked S3
means the evidence can never be disputed.
Let me show you the immutable export pipeline.
Create a class ImmutableAuditExporter.
In the export_daily method, query analysis_history
for all records from the previous day.
If no records exist, log and return.
Write the records to a temporary JSON Lines file.
One record per line. Each line is a JSON object.
This format is easy for auditors to inspect.
Exclude the question_encrypted and answer fields from the archive.
The archive proves what happened, not the content.
Which may contain confidential information.
Auditors verify chain integrity from hash fields.
Generate an S3 key with the date path.
audit-archive forward slash year forward slash month forward slash day forward slash.
analysis-history dash date dot jsonl.
Calculate the retention date as target date plus seven years.
Then upload the file with extra arguments.
ObjectLockMode equals COMPLIANCE.
ObjectLockRetainUntilDate equals the retention date.
ServerSideEncryption equals aws:kms.
Metadata includes record-count and export-date.
After upload, verify the lock was applied.
Call head_object and check the ObjectLockMode.
If mode is not COMPLIANCE, raise an error.
Return a manifest with the S3 key, record count, lock mode, and retain until date.
Deploy this as a nightly CronJob.
Schedule at 1 AM UTC.
After the daily evidence collection, before the morning business hours.
The CronJob uses the financial-rag-api service account.
It calls the export_daily method for yesterday's date.
Now test immutability.
Get the S3 key of yesterday's export.
Run aws s3api get-object-retention.
The output should show Mode equals COMPLIANCE.
And RetainUntilDate equals a date seven years in the future.
Try to delete the object.
aws s3 rm on that key.
It should fail with AccessDenied.
Object is locked in COMPLIANCE mode and cannot be deleted.
Try to overwrite the object.
Echo tampered and pipe to aws s3 cp.
It should also fail with AccessDenied.
Try to shorten the retention period.
aws s3 put-object-retention with a date earlier than the current retention.
It should fail. Cannot shorten retention period for COMPLIANCE mode objects.
Your lab exercise is to create the immutable exporter.
Deploy the nightly CronJob.
Verify that objects are uploaded with COMPLIANCE lock.
Test that deletion, overwrite, and retention shortening all fail.
In the next lecture, we will configure pgAudit.
Database-level SQL audit logging.
---
[## LECTURE 4.5 — PGAUDIT: DATABASE-LEVEL SQL AUDIT LOGGING]
Your application logs are one thing.
But what about direct database access?
A DBA connecting with psql. A compromised pod that finds database credentials.
A developer running a one-off query in production.
None of these appear in your application logs.
PostgreSQL has an extension called pgAudit that solves this.
pgAudit captures every SQL statement executed against the database.
Regardless of who ran it, from what client, or through what connection.
For RDS, enable pgAudit through the parameter group.
Update the parameter group with shared_preload_libraries equals pgaudit comma pg_stat_statements.
Set pgaudit.log equals ddl, role, read, write.
This logs data definition language, role statements, reads, and writes.
Set pgaudit.log_parameter equals one to log query parameters.
Set pgaudit.log_relation equals one to log table names.
Apply the parameter group and reboot the RDS instance.
The reboot is required to load the shared library.
After reboot, connect to the database and enable the extension.
CREATE EXTENSION IF NOT EXISTS pgaudit.
Verify the configuration with SHOW pgaudit.log.
Now run a test query. SELECT COUNT asterisk FROM analysis_history.
Then check the logs.
Here is what pgAudit emits.
A log line with AUDIT colon SESSION.
Then the statement ID, substatement, class, command, and the full SQL text.
Every SELECT, INSERT, CREATE, GRANT is logged.
With timestamp, database user, and the exact SQL.
Configure RDS to publish these logs to CloudWatch.
In the Terraform for the RDS instance, set enabled_cloudwatch_logs_exports.
Include postgresql and upgrade.
Now verify that pgAudit logs are in CloudWatch.
aws logs tail forward slash aws forward slash rds forward slash instance forward slash financial-rag-prod forward slash postgresql.
Filter pattern AUDIT.
Query for specific access to analysis_history.
aws logs filter-log-events with filter pattern analysis_history.
The output shows every query that touched that table.
Save the log group configuration as evidence.
aws logs describe-log-groups for the RDS log group.
Output to pgaudit-log-groups dot json.
Your lab exercise is to enable pgAudit on your RDS instance.
Run various SQL operations and verify they appear in the logs.
Configure log export to CloudWatch.
In the next lecture, we will run monthly integrity verification.
And generate an audit report for your evidence package.
---
[## LECTURE 4.6 — MONTHLY INTEGRITY VERIFICATION AND AUDIT REPORT]
A SOC 2 Type II auditor will test whether your audit logs have been tampered with.
If you wait for the audit to run this verification,
you are operating blind for six to twelve months.
Any tampering during the observation period could invalidate your entire Type II report.
Run verification monthly.
Detect tampering as soon as it occurs.
Generate a report that proves continuous integrity throughout the observation period.
Create a function generate_monthly_integrity_report.
It takes a session, signer, report year, report month, and evidence bucket.
First, verify the hash chain integrity for the month.
Call chain_repo dot verify_chain_integrity with start_date and end_date.
Second, count records by agent_type and analysis_style.
Include average latency and error count.
This gives you usage metrics for the month.
Third, check S3 archive completeness.
For each day in the month, check if the daily export exists.
If any day is missing, note it in the report.
Fourth, assemble the report.
Include total records, error count, error rate, chain integrity status,
signature validity, records verified, and missing days.
Fifth, upload the report to the immutable evidence bucket.
Use Object Lock in COMPLIANCE mode with seven-year retention.
Schedule this to run on the first day of each month at 2 AM UTC.
The monthly integrity report becomes part of your Type II evidence.
Your lab exercise is to generate a monthly integrity report.
Verify that all checks pass.
Store the report in your immutable S3 bucket.
In the next lecture, we will run the tamper detection demonstration.
To prove the system works to your auditor.
---
[## LECTURE 4.7 — THE TAMPER-DETECTION DEMONSTRATION]
Before submitting to your auditor, run the tamper-detection test.
Prove that any modification to analysis_history is detected.
This demonstration should be part of your auditor walkthrough.
First, insert a legitimate record.
Call the API or insert directly through the repository.
Capture the record ID.
Second, record the current hash.
Query the current_hash for the record.
Note the value.
Third, attempt a direct UPDATE.
Update the answer column on the record.
The trigger should block it with an error message.
If the UPDATE fails with a clear error, the trigger is working.
If it succeeds, your trigger is missing or disabled.
Fix that before proceeding.
Fourth, simulate a DBA bypassing the trigger.
Set session_replication_role to replica.
This temporarily disables triggers.
Then run the UPDATE again.
This time it will succeed because triggers are disabled.
This simulates a malicious superuser.
Set session_replication_role back to default.
Now run hash chain verification.
The verification should detect that the chain is broken.
chain_valid should be false.
first_broken_at should be the ID of the tampered record.
This proves that even if a superuser bypasses the trigger,
the hash chain detects the modification immediately.
The signing key lives in Vault. Without it, an attacker cannot recompute valid hashes or forge signatures.
Run this demonstration in your staging environment.
Document the steps and outputs.
Include the demonstration in your audit evidence package.
Your lab exercise is to run the tamper detection demonstration.
Document that the trigger blocks UPDATE.
Document that hash chain verification detects tampering.
In the final lecture of Phase 4, we will generate the monthly audit report.
This is the document you will hand to your auditor.
---
[## LECTURE 4.8 — AUTOMATED MONTHLY AUDIT REPORT FOR THE EVIDENCE PACKAGE]
Your auditor will want a human-readable monthly audit report.
Not just raw logs.
But a summary showing total queries processed, error rates,
any anomalies detected, and integrity verification status.
Let me show you how to generate this report automatically.
Create a script called generate-audit-report dot sh.
It takes year and month as arguments.
Defaults to the current year and month.
First, pull the integrity report from S3.
aws s3 cp from the integrity-reports path.
If it exists, extract the status, total records, error count, error rate.
Extract chain_valid, signatures_valid, and missing days.
Format these into a summary table.
Second, list the S3 archive files for the month.
aws s3 ls on the audit-archive path.
Show each file with its size and last modified date.
Third, query CloudWatch for authentication failures in the month.
Use aws logs filter-log-events with filter pattern auth dot failure.
Count the events.
Fourth, query the database for API key events.
Number of revocations in the month.
Number of new keys issued.
Fifth, assemble the report in Markdown format.
Start with an executive summary table.
Include overall status, total queries, error rate, chain integrity, and S3 completeness.
Add a section on hash chain integrity.
Describe the verification method.
Report the number of records verified and any broken chain.
Add a section on S3 archive status.
List all files with their sizes.
Show that every day of the month has an export.
Add a section on access events.
Authentication failures, key revocations, and new keys issued.
Add a compliance controls status table.
CC7.5 for incident identification and response.
PI1.1 for processing integrity.
C1.1 for confidentiality.
Finally, add a certification section.
The report was generated automatically.
All data is cryptographically verified.
Include the report ID and S3 archive location.
Save the report to soc2-evidence forward slash audit-reports.
Upload the report to the immutable evidence bucket with Object Lock.
Run this script monthly, after the integrity verification is complete.
The report becomes part of your Type II evidence package.
Your lab exercise is to generate a monthly audit report.
Verify that all integrity checks pass.
Store the report in your immutable S3 bucket.
Key takeaways for Phase 4.
Every user interaction is permanently recorded.
Cryptographic proof of no tampering.
Seven-year immutable log retention.
Complete audit trail of database and Kubernetes access.
Automated monthly compliance reports.
Anomaly detection and alerting.
What is ready for your auditor.
Every user interaction permanently recorded.
Cryptographic proof of no tampering.
Seven-year immutable log retention.
Complete audit trail of database and Kubernetes access.
Automated monthly compliance reports.
Anomaly detection and alerting.
In Phase 5, we will cover Vulnerability Management in CI/CD.
Trivy container scanning, Gitleaks secret detection,
dependency scanning, SBOM generation, and CVE remediation SLAs.
Continue to Phase 5 when you are ready.
---
**End of Phase 4 SRT**
**Total lines:** 161
**Duration:** ~2 hours
Shall I continue with **Phase 5 — Vulnerability Management in CI/CD**?