You have the most secure, available, perfectly logged system in the world.
But what happens when a developer pushes directly to main?
Or merges a PR without review?
One bad merge and your compliance is gone.
Change management, CC8.1, requires that all changes follow a controlled process.
No exceptions. Not for emergencies. Not for small fixes.
Hi there, and welcome to Phase 7 of our SOC 2 journey.
In this phase, we are building a complete change management system
that auditors love.
GitHub branch protection, PR requirements, pre-merge validation,
ArgoCD GitOps, rollback procedures, database migrations,
canary deployments, and complete change audit trails.
By the end of these two hours, every change to your system
will be reviewed, tested, approved, and traceable.
From commit to production.
Let me start with the foundation. Branch protection.
Apply branch protection via the GitHub CLI.
Required status checks must be strict.
The branch must be up to date with main before merging.
The required status checks include secret scan, Trivy filesystem scan,
dependency scan, Ruff, MyPy, unit tests, and Conftest validation.
All must pass before a PR can merge.
Required pull request reviews. Set required approving review count to two.
Two people must approve. One can miss something. Two is harder.
Dismiss stale reviews. If you push new code after approval,
approvals are dismissed. No sneaking in changes.
Require code owner reviews. If you change security code,
the security team must approve.
Require last push approval. The reviewer who approved
must have approved the most recent commit.
Enforce admins. Even administrators cannot bypass branch protection.
Require linear history. No merge commits. Only rebase or squash.
Clean audit trail.
Allow force pushes false. Force pushing overwrites history.
That is not allowed.
Allow deletions false. Branches cannot be deleted through the API.
Now verify the protection.
gh api to get the branch protection settings.
Extract required reviews count, dismiss stale, code owners required,
force push allowed, and admin enforced.
Save the branch protection configuration as evidence.
Save it to soc2-evidence under today's date in CC8.1.
Call it branch-protection dot json.
Test that protection works.
Attempt a direct push to main. It should fail.
The error says protected branch update failed.
At least two approving reviews are required.
Attempt a force push to main. It should also fail.
The error says cannot force push to a protected branch.
Your lab exercise is to configure branch protection on your main branch.
Verify you cannot push directly.
Create a PR and verify it requires approval.
Test that force pushes are blocked.
In the next lecture, we will configure CODEOWNERS.
To automatically request review from the right teams.
---
[## LECTURE 7.2 — CODEOWNERS: AUTOMATIC REVIEW ASSIGNMENT]
Branch protection enforces the process.
But what about the quality of reviews?
CODEOWNERS ensures the right people review the right files.
Create a dot github forward slash CODEOWNERS file.
For security-critical paths, assign the security team.
src forward slash financial_rag forward slash security forward slash asterisk.
Falco forward slash asterisk. Cilium forward slash asterisk.
Dot gitleaks dot toml. Security forward slash asterisk.
Policies forward slash asterisk.
For infrastructure paths, assign the platform team.
Infrastructure forward slash asterisk. Helm forward slash asterisk.
Terraform forward slash asterisk. Karpenter forward slash asterisk.
ArgoCD forward slash asterisk.
For database migrations, assign database owners.
Migrations forward slash asterisk.
Src forward slash financial_rag forward slash storage forward slash asterisk.
For CI slash CD configuration, assign the platform team.
Dot github forward slash workflows forward slash asterisk.
Dot github forward slash CODEOWNERS itself.
For SOC 2 evidence and compliance, assign the compliance team.
Soc2 forward slash asterisk. Runbooks forward slash asterisk.
For root config files, assign all senior engineers.
Pyproject dot toml. Dockerfile.
Commit the CODEOWNERS file and push to main.
Now when a developer opens a PR that changes a security file,
GitHub automatically requests review from the security team.
No way to bypass.
Test that CODEOWNERS works.
Create a test branch. Touch a security file.
Open a PR. Check that the security team was auto-requested.
Then close the PR and clean up the branch.
Save the CODEOWNERS file as evidence.
Copy it to the evidence directory.
Your lab exercise is to create a PR that modifies a security file.
Verify the security label is added.
Verify the security team is automatically requested for review.
In the next lecture, we will add pre-merge validation.
Required status checks that run on every PR.
---
[## LECTURE 7.3 — PRE-MERGE VALIDATION: REQUIRED STATUS CHECKS]
Reviews catch logic errors.
But what about code that passes review but fails tests?
Or introduces a vulnerability? Or breaks the build?
You need automated validation that runs on every PR
and blocks merge if anything fails.
Required status checks are the answer.
Let me walk through the complete pre-merge validation pipeline.
First, secret scan with Gitleaks.
Checks for hardcoded secrets in the entire Git history.
Uses the dot gitleaks dot toml configuration.
Second, Trivy filesystem scan.
Scans the codebase, Dockerfile, and configuration files.
Fails on CRITICAL and HIGH vulnerabilities.
Third, dependency scan with pip-audit.
Scans pyproject dot toml for vulnerable Python packages.
Fails on CRITICAL and HIGH severity findings.
Fourth, code quality with Ruff and MyPy.
Ruff checks linting and formatting.
MyPy performs static type checking with strict mode.
Fifth, unit tests with coverage.
Runs all unit tests. Fails if coverage drops below sixty percent.
Outputs coverage XML for upload to Codecov.
Sixth, Conftest validation for infrastructure changes.
Only runs if the PR has the infrastructure label.
Renders Helm templates and validates them against Rego policies.
Seventh, migration test for database changes.
Only runs if the PR has the database label.
Starts a PostgreSQL test container.
Tests upgrade, downgrade, and re-upgrade.
Now add these as required status checks in branch protection.
Update the branch protection configuration.
Add the context names to the required status checks list.
Now every PR must pass all these checks before merge.
If any fails, the merge button is disabled.
What does a developer see when they forget to run tests?
Required checks pending. Unit tests pending. Integration tests pending.
And required checks failing. A secret scan failure or a type error.
Merge is blocked until all checks pass.
Your lab exercise is to create a PR that intentionally breaks a test.
Verify the merge is blocked. Fix the test and verify the merge becomes available.
In the next lecture, we will deploy ArgoCD GitOps.
And enable self-heal to revert manual changes.
---
[## LECTURE 7.4 — ARGOCD GITOPS: SELF-HEALING AND DRIFT DETECTION]
GitHub protects your code.
But what about your Kubernetes configuration?
Someone with kubectl access could change a deployment directly,
bypassing all your controls.
That is configuration drift.
ArgoCD implements GitOps. Your cluster state is always synced to what is in Git.
If someone changes something directly, ArgoCD reverts it automatically.
Create the ArgoCD application manifest.
Source repo URL is your GitHub repository.
Target revision is main. Path is infrastructure forward slash helm.
Destination server is the Kubernetes API.
Namespace is financial-rag.
Sync policy automated. Prune true. Delete resources not in Git.
Self-heal true. Revert any manual changes.
Allow empty false.
Sync options include CreateNamespace, ApplyOutOfSyncOnly, and PruneLast.
Retry limit five. Backoff duration five seconds.
Factor two. Max duration three minutes.
Apply the ArgoCD application.
Now let us see drift detection in action.
Check sync status. argocd app get financial-rag.
Sync Status should be Synced. Health Status Healthy.
Now manually change a deployment.
kubectl scale deployment financial-rag-agent-api to ten replicas.
Wait thirty seconds. Check sync status again.
It will be OutOfSync.
View the drift. argocd app diff.
It shows the live replicas ten and the desired replicas six.
ArgoCD self-heals within seconds. The sync status returns to Synced.
Integrate ArgoCD with GitHub Actions for automated sync after merges.
When you push to main, the deploy workflow runs.
Install ArgoCD CLI. Login to ArgoCD.
Run argocd app sync. Wait for sync to complete.
Verify the health status is Healthy.
Save the deployment evidence to S3.
Save ArgoCD sync history as evidence.
argocd app history financial-rag.
Save the sync status as JSON.
Your lab exercise is to make a change to your Helm chart and push to Git.
Watch ArgoCD auto-sync.
Then manually change a resource in Kubernetes.
Watch ArgoCD revert it.
In the next lecture, we will implement canary deployments.
And automated rollback on error rate spikes.
---
[## LECTURE 7.5 — CANARY DEPLOYMENTS: AUTOMATED ROLLBACK ON ERROR RATE SPIKE]
Rolling back is good.
Not needing to roll back is better.
Canary deployments let you test changes on a small percentage of traffic
before full rollout.
If something breaks, only ten percent of users are affected.
Argo Rollouts provides canary deployment capabilities.
First, install Argo Rollouts.
Create the namespace. Apply the install manifest.
Wait for all pods to be ready.
Now create a Rollout resource instead of a Deployment.
The spec is similar to a Deployment.
But the strategy is canary.
Canary steps. Step one, set weight ten percent.
Step two, pause for five minutes.
Step three, set weight twenty-five percent.
Step four, pause for five minutes.
Step five, set weight fifty percent.
Step six, pause for ten minutes.
Step seven, set weight one hundred percent. Full rollout.
Now add analysis during canary.
Analysis starts at step one. Step one is after the first ten percent weight.
The analysis template is called api-success-rate.
Create the analysis template.
Metrics include success rate and p95 latency.
Interval is thirty seconds. Query Prometheus.
For success rate, success condition is result greater than or equal to zero point nine five.
Failure condition is result less than or equal to zero point nine zero.
Failure limit is three. Three failures before abort.
For p95 latency, success condition is result less than two seconds.
Failure condition is result greater than three seconds.
Now monitor a canary rollout.
kubectl argo rollouts get rollout with watch.
It shows the current step, set weight, and actual weight.
The output shows two sets of pods.
Stable pods handling ninety percent of traffic.
Canary pods handling ten percent of traffic.
If analysis passes, you can promote manually.
kubectl argo rollouts promote.
If something is wrong, you can abort.
kubectl argo rollouts abort.
Save the rollout history as evidence.
kubectl argo rollouts get rollout with output JSON.
Save to the evidence directory.
Your lab exercise is to deploy a change using canary strategy.
Monitor the rollout progress.
Verify analysis pauses if success rate drops.
In the next lecture, we will implement database migrations.
With downgrade testing in CI.
---
[## LECTURE 7.6 — DATABASE MIGRATIONS: REVERSIBLE ALEMBIC WITH DOWNGRADE TESTING]
Application rollbacks are easy.
Database migrations are hard.
If you add a column and then roll back,
you cannot just undo the application. The column still exists.
You need migrations that are reversible.
Alembic supports downgrade migrations.
Every upgrade must have a corresponding downgrade.
Here is a reversible migration.
Add a column called query_classification to analysis_history.
In the upgrade, first add the column as nullable.
Add an index on the new column.
Then backfill existing rows. Set query_classification to general for all nulls.
After backfill, alter the column to be not nullable.
This avoids locking the table for a long time.
In the downgrade, reverse the order.
First, alter the column to be nullable again.
Then drop the index. Then drop the column.
Now test the migration locally.
alembic upgrade head. Upgrade succeeds.
alembic downgrade minus one. Downgrade succeeds.
alembic upgrade head again. Re-upgrade succeeds.
Verify the column exists after upgrade.
psql backslash d analysis_history. Look for query_classification.
Verify it is gone after downgrade.
The CI migration test runs on every PR that touches migrations.
It starts a PostgreSQL test container.
It applies all migrations. It tests downgrade. It tests upgrade again.
This ensures every migration is reversible.
If a migration breaks the downgrade path, the PR is blocked.
Your lab exercise is to create a reversible migration.
Test upgrade and downgrade locally.
Push to PR and verify CI passes.
In the next lecture, we will generate a monthly change audit report.
Complete traceability from commit to production.
---
[## LECTURE 7.7 — CHANGE AUDIT REPORT: COMPLETE TRACEABILITY]
Your auditor will ask. Who changed what, when, and why?
You need a complete audit trail of every change.
From Git commit to production deployment.
Create a monthly change audit report generator.
The script takes year and month as arguments.
Defaults to the current month.
First, query GitHub API for all PRs merged in the month.
Filter by merged date between month start and month end.
Extract number, title, author, merged at, approvers, and labels.
Print a markdown table of all merged PRs.
Total count. Number, title, author, merged date, labels.
Second, query ArgoCD for deployment history.
argocd app history financial-rag in JSON format.
Filter by deployedAt within the month.
Print a table of all deployments.
Revision, deployed at time, message, and status.
Third, verify change control.
Check branch protection status. Check that all PRs required two reviewers.
Check no direct pushes to main. Check ArgoCD self-heal active.
Add a certification section.
All changes were submitted as pull requests.
Approved by at least two reviewers.
Passed all CI checks before merge.
Deployed via ArgoCD GitOps. No direct kubectl changes.
Save the report to soc2-evidence forward slash change-audits.
Upload the report to the immutable S3 bucket.
Schedule this as a monthly CronJob.
Run at 2 AM on the first day of every month.
The CronJob uses the compliance-runner service account.
Your lab exercise is to generate a change audit report.
Verify that every deployment is traceable to a Git commit and PR.
Review the report for any untracked changes.
In the final lecture of Phase 7, we will assemble the complete CC8.1 evidence package.
And collect change management evidence daily.
---
[## LECTURE 7.8 — CC8.1 EVIDENCE PACKAGE]
You need to collect CC8.1 evidence every day.
Not just once. Every day.
So when the auditor asks for evidence from six months ago, you have it.
Create a script called collect-change-management-evidence dot sh.
Create an evidence directory for CC8.1 under today's date.
First, save the branch protection configuration.
gh api to get the branch protection.
Save as branch-protection dot json.
Second, save PRs merged today.
gh api to get closed PRs. Filter by merged date equals today.
Save as merged-prs-today dot json.
Third, save ArgoCD app status.
argocd app get financial-rag with output JSON.
Save as argocd-app-status dot json.
Fourth, save ArgoCD sync history.
argocd app history financial-rag with output JSON.
Save as argocd-sync-history dot json.
Fifth, check for drift.
Extract the sync status from ArgoCD app status.
If the status is OutOfSync, drift is detected.
Create a drift status JSON file.
Sixth, save deployment rollout history.
kubectl rollout history for the API deployment.
Save as deployment-rollout-history dot txt.
Seventh, save the CODEOWNERS file.
Copy dot github forward slash CODEOWNERS to the evidence directory.
Generate a summary JSON file.
Branch protection enabled. Required reviews count.
Force push disabled. Admin enforced.
PRs merged today count. ArgoCD sync status.
Drift detected boolean. CODEOWNERS configured.
Sync all evidence to S3 with SSE KMS.
Add this step to your daily evidence collection workflow.
Key takeaways for Phase 7.
GitHub branch protection with required reviews and status checks.
CODEOWNERS for security and infrastructure ownership.
Pre-merge validation including security scans, tests, and policy checks.
ArgoCD GitOps with auto-sync and drift detection.
Rollback procedures automated and documented.
Reversible database migrations with downgrade paths.
Canary deployments with automated analysis.
Complete change audit trail from commit to production.
What is ready for your auditor.
No direct pushes to main allowed.
Two-person approval for all changes.
Security team review for sensitive changes.
All changes tested before merge.
Cluster state matches Git. No drift.
Rollback procedures tested.
Database migrations reversible.
Canary deployments minimize blast radius.
Every change traceable to PR and author.
In Phase 8, we will cover Vendor and Third-Party Risk.
BAA requirements, vendor assessment framework,
AWS Shared Responsibility Model, and image provenance.
Continue to Phase 8 when you are ready.
---
**End of Phase 7 SRT**
**Total lines:** 120
**Duration:** ~1 hour 40 minutes
Shall I continue with **Phase 8 — Vendor & Third-Party Risk**?