Your application is secure. Your database is encrypted.
Your logs are immutable. But what about the container image
you just pushed to production?
Does it contain a vulnerability from six months ago
that someone forgot to patch? That is the problem
with supply chain security.
Your base image has vulnerabilities.
Your Python dependencies have vulnerabilities.
Even your distroless image has vulnerabilities in the kernel.
For SOC 2, you need to find and fix these
before they reach production.
Hi there, and welcome to Phase 5 of our SOC 2 journey.
In this phase, we are building a complete
vulnerability management program in CI/CD.
Container scanning, dependency scanning, secret detection.
SBOM generation, CVE SLAs, image signing,
and policy as code. By the end of these two hours,
every container image you deploy will be scanned,
signed, and verified before it ever touches production.
Let me start with the most critical tool.
Trivy for container scanning.
Trivy is an open-source vulnerability scanner.
It checks OS packages and language dependencies.
It is fast, accurate, and integrates directly into GitHub Actions.
First, configure Trivy with a dot trivy dot yaml file.
Set severity to CRITICAL, HIGH, and MEDIUM.
MEDIUM only warns, does not fail the build.
Set ignore-unfixed to false.
Report vulnerabilities even if no fix is available yet.
Set vulnerability type to os and library.
Skip directories like dot git, dot venv, tests.
Skip files like dot env example and docker-compose files.
Set format to table and exit-code to one.
Exit-code one means fail the CI on any CRITICAL or HIGH finding.
Create a dot trivyignore file for false positives.
Now integrate Trivy into GitHub Actions.
Create a workflow file called ci dot yml.
Trigger on pull requests to main and develop.
Also trigger on push to main and on a daily schedule.
The daily schedule catches vulnerabilities in dependencies
that were already merged.
In the security-scan job, first build the Docker image.
Then run a filesystem scan with Trivy.
Scan the entire codebase including the Dockerfile.
Then run an image scan on the built container.
Both scans output SARIF format.
This format is supported by GitHub's security tab.
Upload both SARIF files to GitHub using the CodeQL action.
Now vulnerabilities appear directly in the GitHub Security tab.
Developers see them without leaving the pull request.
What happens when a vulnerability is found?
The CI pipeline fails with clear output.
A table shows the library, vulnerability ID, severity,
installed version, and fixed version.
For false positives or unavoidable vulnerabilities,
add them to dot trivyignore with a comment.
Explain why each ignored vulnerability is acceptable.
Now set up a weekly scheduled scan.
Run every Monday at 6 AM.
Scan with severity CRITICAL, HIGH, and MEDIUM.
Convert the SARIF to Security Hub format and import.
Create GitHub issues for any new critical findings.
The issue includes the vulnerability ID, severity,
package, fixed version, and description.
Your lab exercise is to run Trivy on your Docker image.
Identify any CRITICAL or HIGH vulnerabilities.
For each vulnerability, determine if it is a false positive
or needs remediation.
Create a dot trivyignore file for any false positives.
Document your vulnerability remediation SLA.
In the next lecture, we will scan Python dependencies.
---
[## LECTURE 5.2 — DEPENDENCY SCANNING: PIP-AUDIT AND SAFETY]
Container scanning finds vulnerabilities in OS packages.
But what about your Python dependencies?
FastAPI, Pydantic, SQLAlchemy, LangChain.
Each one could have vulnerabilities.
You need to scan your pyproject.toml and requirements.txt directly.
Let me show you pip-audit.
pip-audit is a tool from the Python Packaging Authority.
It scans dependencies for known vulnerabilities.
Add a dependency-scan job to your CI workflow.
First, setup Python with the correct version.
Install pip-audit and safety.
Then install your package in editable mode with dev dependencies.
Run pip-audit with your pyproject.toml as the requirement.
Output SARIF format and include descriptions.
Also run safety check on requirements.txt.
Upload the pip-audit SARIF to GitHub.
Then check if any CRITICAL vulnerabilities were found.
If yes, fail the build.
Now automate dependency updates with Dependabot.
Create a dot github forward slash dependabot dot yml file.
For Python dependencies, set the package ecosystem to pip.
Schedule weekly on Monday at 9 AM.
Set open pull requests limit to ten.
Labels include dependencies and security.
Group minor and patch updates together to reduce noise.
Only auto-merge security updates.
For Docker base images, also schedule weekly.
Ignore major Python version upgrades.
Stay on your current major version for stability.
For GitHub Actions, also schedule weekly.
Now add a pre-commit hook to catch vulnerabilities
before they are even committed.
Create a dot pre-commit-config dot yaml file.
Add the python-safety-dependencies-check hook.
It scans pyproject.toml for vulnerable dependencies.
Add a local pip-audit hook.
Now developers get immediate feedback.
If they add an outdated vulnerable package like requests 2.28.0,
the commit is blocked.
The output shows the vulnerability ID, package, severity,
and the title. It also tells them which version to upgrade to.
Your lab exercise is to run pip-audit on your pyproject.toml.
Identify any vulnerable dependencies.
Update them to patched versions.
Configure Dependabot for automated updates.
Test the pre-commit hook by intentionally adding
an outdated vulnerable package.
In the next lecture, we will detect secrets in Git history.
With Gitleaks and TruffleHog.
---
[## LECTURE 5.3 — SECRET DETECTION: GITLEAKS AND TRUFFLEHOG]
Vulnerabilities are one thing.
Hardcoded secrets are another.
And they are arguably more dangerous.
An API key in a commit is immediately compromised.
You need to prevent secrets from ever entering your repository.
Let me show you Gitleaks.
Gitleaks scans for secrets in Git history.
Add it to your pre-commit configuration.
Rev v8.18.4 is stable.
Also add TruffleHog for additional coverage.
TruffleHog verifies secrets by attempting to use them.
It has a lower false positive rate.
Now configure custom rules for your specific secrets.
Create a dot gitleaks dot toml file.
First rule. OpenAI API keys.
The regex looks for sk dash followed by 48 alphanumeric characters.
Tags include key, openai, llm, critical.
Second rule. Groq API keys.
The regex looks for gsk underscore followed by 48 alphanumeric characters.
Third rule. AWS Access Keys. AKIA followed by 16 uppercase letters or digits.
Fourth rule. Vault Tokens.
hvs dot followed by alphanumeric and underscore dash characters.
Fifth rule. JWT Tokens.
The standard JWT regex with three base64 sections separated by dots.
Sixth rule. Database connection strings.
PostgreSQL URLs with username, password, and host.
The allowlist section excludes false positives.
Exclude dot env example files.
Exclude the dot gitleaks dot toml file itself.
Exclude dot pre-commit-config dot yaml.
Exclude test fixtures.
Now run secret scanning in CI.
This catches anything that bypasses the pre-commit hook.
Checkout with fetch-depth zero for full history.
Run Gitleaks with your configuration file.
Output SARIF format.
Run TruffleHog in a Docker container.
TruffleHog scans the filesystem with the only-verified flag.
This means it actually tests the secrets, reducing false positives.
Upload the Gitleaks SARIF to GitHub.
If the scan fails, run a revocation script.
Parse the findings and revoke any exposed secrets.
Call the OpenAI API to revoke a leaked key.
For AWS keys, call iam dot delete_access_key.
For Vault tokens, call the Vault API to revoke.
What happens when a secret is found in a commit?
The pre-commit hook blocks the commit.
Gitleaks prints the finding, the secret, the rule, the file, and the commit.
The output says commit blocked. Remove secret and use Vault instead.
To bypass, not recommended, you can set SKIP equals gitleaks.
But that defeats the purpose.
Your lab exercise is to add a fake secret to a file.
Verify the pre-commit hook blocks it.
Then remove the secret and commit successfully.
Document your secret revocation process.
In the next lecture, we will generate a Software Bill of Materials.
An SBOM for every container image.
---
[## LECTURE 5.4 — SBOM GENERATION: SOFTWARE BILL OF MATERIALS]
Your auditor will ask. What is in your container?
What dependencies are you shipping?
You need a Software Bill of Materials.
A complete inventory of every package, library,
and component in your application.
SBOMs are becoming mandatory for government contracts
and enterprise customers.
Syft from Anchore generates SBOMs in multiple formats.
Add an SBOM generation job to your CI workflow.
First, build the Docker image.
Then generate an SBOM with Syft in SPDX JSON format.
SPDX is the Linux Foundation's standard.
Also generate a CycloneDX format SBOM.
CycloneDX is preferred by many security tools.
Upload both SBOMs as build artifacts.
Attest the SBOM to GitHub using gh attestation.
This proves the SBOM matches the image.
Then upload the SBOM to Dependency Track.
Dependency Track is an open-source component analysis platform.
It tracks vulnerabilities across your SBOM over time.
Use an API key for authentication.
Here is what an SBOM looks like in SPDX format.
It has an SPDXID and a name.
Creation info includes the creation time and the tool that generated it.
Then a list of packages.
Each package has a name, version info, download location,
license declared, and copyright text.
External references include CPE identifiers and package URLs.
Relationships show which packages are contained in the document.
This is a complete inventory.
Now verify the SBOM matches what is actually running.
Generate an SBOM from the running container.
Then compare it with the committed SBOM using diff.
Also verify the SBOM signature with Cosign.
cosign verify-attestation with the public key.
Your lab exercise is to generate an SBOM for your container image.
In SPDX and CycloneDX formats.
Upload it to Dependency Track or a similar platform.
Verify that the SBOM includes all your Python dependencies
and base OS packages.
In the next lecture, we will define CVE SLAs.
And enforce vulnerability response policies.
---
[## LECTURE 5.5 — CVE SLA: VULNERABILITY RESPONSE POLICY]
Finding vulnerabilities is step one.
Fixing them within an agreed timeframe is step two.
SOC 2 expects you to have SLAs for vulnerability remediation.
First, define your SLA policy.
Create security forward slash cve-sla-policy dot yaml.
For CRITICAL severity, response hours is twenty-four.
Must acknowledge within twenty-four hours.
Fix days is seven. Must deploy fix within seven days.
Escalation is PagerDuty. Wake someone up.
Requires CAB is false. No change board for emergency fixes.
For HIGH severity, response hours is seventy-two.
Fix days is fourteen.
Escalation is Slack. Post to the security channel.
Requires CAB is true. Needs change approval.
For MEDIUM severity, response days is seven.
Fix days is thirty. Escalation is email.
For LOW severity, response days is thirty.
Fix days is ninety. Escalation is none.
Define exceptions for false positives or awaiting upstream fixes.
Now enforce these SLAs with automation.
Create a CVE SLA enforcement workflow.
Run daily at 6 AM.
Scan the current image for CRITICAL and HIGH CVEs with Trivy.
Output to a JSON file.
Then run a Python script to check SLA compliance.
Load the exceptions from the policy file.
For each vulnerability, calculate its age in days.
If severity is CRITICAL and age is greater than seven days,
add it to violations.
If severity is HIGH and age is greater than fourteen days,
If violations exist, create a markdown report and exit with code one.
For scheduled runs, also create a PagerDuty alert.
Send a critical severity alert that CVE SLA breach is detected.
The routing key comes from GitHub secrets.
Now create a dashboard to track SLA compliance.
A CVE SLA tracker class.
It queries the vulnerability database and calculates compliance.
The generate_compliance_report method returns a dict.
Total active CVEs, SLA compliance rate, breakdown by severity,
exceptions granted, and oldest CVE age.
Your lab exercise is to define your CVE SLA policy.
Create a tracking mechanism for open vulnerabilities.
Simulate a critical CVE older than seven days.
Verify that an alert is triggered.
In the next lecture, we will sign container images.
With Cosign and Notation.
---
[## LECTURE 5.6 — IMAGE SIGNING: COSIGN AND NOTATION]
You have scanned your image. No vulnerabilities.
But how do you know the image running in production
is the same one you scanned?
What if someone tampered with it in the registry?
Image signing cryptographically verifies that an image
came from your CI pipeline and has not been modified.
Let me show you Cosign from Sigstore.
First, generate a key pair.
cosign generate-key-pair.
This creates two files. cosign dot key, the private key.
And cosign dot pub, the public key.
Store the private key in Vault. Never in Git.
Store the public key in Git. It is safe to share.
Now sign your image in CI.
In the build-and-sign job, first build the Docker image.
Push it to the registry with the commit SHA as a tag.
Install Cosign using the sigstore action.
Then sign the image with the private key.
Set the password and private key from GitHub secrets.
Finally, verify the signature immediately after signing.
This proves the signature is valid before proceeding.
Now enforce signature verification in Kubernetes.
Create a ClusterImagePolicy.
Images that match the glob pattern must be signed.
The authority section includes the static public key.
Also include keyless authority for development environments.
Set mode to enforce. Reject unsigned images.
In your deployment, add an annotation.
cosign dot sigstore dot dev forward slash verify equals true.
The admission controller checks the signature before allowing the pod.
Verify signatures in production.
Get all pods and extract their image names.
Loop through each image and run cosign verify.
Monitor the admission controller logs.
kubectl logs minus n cosign-system deployment forward slash cosign-webhook.
It logs every verification attempt.
Your lab exercise is to generate a Cosign key pair.
Sign your container image. Push the signed image to a registry.
Verify the signature.
Test what happens when you try to deploy an unsigned image.
The admission controller should reject it.
In the next lecture, we will validate Kubernetes manifests.
With OPA Conftest.
---
[## LECTURE 5.7 — POLICY AS CODE: OPA CONFTEST]
You have scanned, signed, and verified your images.
But what about the Kubernetes manifests themselves?
Are they configured securely?
Are they using the right image registry?
Do they have resource limits?
Policy as Code with Open Policy Agent Conftest
lets you validate YAML manifests before deployment.
Write policies in Rego, a declarative query language.
Create a policies directory and a security dot rego file.
First policy. Enforce image registry.
If the kind is Deployment, get the container image.
If the image does not start with your registry, deny it.
Second policy. Enforce run as non-root.
If the container does not have securityContext dot runAsNonRoot equals true, deny it.
Third policy. Enforce resource limits.
If the container does not have resources dot limits, deny it.
Without limits, a single container could starve all others.
Fourth policy. Enforce read-only root filesystem.
If the container does not have readOnlyRootFilesystem equals true, deny it.
This prevents attackers from writing to the container's filesystem.
Fifth policy. Prevent NodePort services.
If the service type is NodePort, deny it.
NodePort exposes services on a high port on every node.
Use LoadBalancer or ClusterIP instead.
Sixth policy. Require labels.
If the deployment does not have a label called app, deny it.
Labels are required for monitoring and debugging.
Now run Conftest in CI.
Install Conftest by downloading the binary from GitHub.
Then run helm template to generate the Kubernetes manifests.
Pipe the manifests to conftest test.
Point to the policies directory.
Output JSON and check for failures.
If any failures exist, print them and exit with code one.
Test locally. conftest test deployment dot yaml dash dash policy policies.
The output shows which policies failed and why.
Your lab exercise is to write a Rego policy.
Enforce your organization's security standards.
Run Conftest on your Helm templates.
Fix any violations. Document your policy rules.
In the next lecture, we will build a vulnerability dashboard.
With Grafana and Security Hub.
---
[## LECTURE 5.8 — VULNERABILITY DASHBOARD: GRAFANA AND SECURITY HUB]
You are scanning, signing, and validating.
But how do you see the big picture?
How many critical CVEs are open?
Are they getting fixed within SLA?
A vulnerability dashboard gives you visibility
across your entire organization.
Here are the Prometheus queries for vulnerability metrics.
First, critical CVEs by image in the last seven days.
Sum by image of trivy_vulnerabilities with severity CRITICAL and status open.
Second, CVE age distribution as a histogram quantile.
Third, SLA compliance rate over time.
Sum of CVEs closed within SLA divided by total CVEs, times one hundred.
Fourth, vulnerabilities by severity.
Sum by severity of trivy_vulnerabilities with status open.
Fifth, images with the most vulnerabilities. Top ten.
Sixth, remediation time trend. Average by month of the days from detection to fix.
Now create the dashboard JSON for Grafana.
The dashboard has a stat panel for SLA compliance.
A bar chart for critical CVEs by image.
A heatmap for CVE age distribution.
Integrate with AWS Security Hub.
Import Trivy findings to Security Hub using batch-import-findings.
Create a custom insight for CVE SLA breaches.
Set up a weekly report.
The complete dashboard layout has several panels.
SLA compliance, critical CVEs by image, CVE age distribution.
Vulnerabilities by type. OS packages, Python, Node, Go.
Open CVEs by severity. Remediation queue.
Remediation trend in days. Top ten most vulnerable images.
Your lab exercise is to create a vulnerability dashboard
in your observability platform.
Set up weekly email reports to the security team.
Configure alerts for SLA breaches.
Key takeaways for Phase 5.
Trivy container scanning in CI/CD.
Dependency scanning with pip-audit and Dependabot.
Secret detection with Gitleaks pre-commit hooks.
SBOM generation in SPDX and CycloneDX formats.
CVE SLAs defined and enforced.
Image signing with Cosign.
Policy as Code with OPA Conftest.
Vulnerability dashboard with SLA tracking.
What is ready for your auditor.
Every container scanned before deployment.
All dependencies tracked and updated automatically.
No secrets in Git history.
Complete SBOM for every release.
CVE remediation SLAs enforced.
Signed images with cryptographic verification.
Policy validation preventing insecure configurations.
Real-time vulnerability visibility.
In Phase 6, we will cover Availability Controls.
Multi-AZ RDS, Redis AOF persistence, HPA with Karpenter,
PodDisruptionBudgets, and chaos engineering.
Continue to Phase 6 when you are ready.
---
**End of Phase 5 SRT**
**Total lines:** 135
**Duration:** ~1 hour 45 minutes
Shall I continue with **Phase 6 — Availability Controls**?