Welcome to Series eleven. The capstone.
The end of the journey.
You have built everything across ten series.
Every piece is working. Every component is deployed.
But theory is not practice. Pieces are not a system.
The capstone is where we prove that everything works together.
In this final series, you will.
Start from a fresh AWS account with a meaningful workload.
Run through every optimization from Series two through six in sequence.
Deploy the full IDP from Series seven through ten.
Create a new service through the golden path.
Trace it from click to running pod.
Trigger a budget alert and see the Slack notification.
Generate the final chargeback report.
Update your baseline document with before and after numbers.
Calculate the total annual savings.
And finally, commit the platform configuration to Git.
So your organization can replicate what you have built.
Let me remind you where we started and where we are going.
Series one. The baseline.
You learned unit economics. You built a tagging strategy.
You ran your first Cost Explorer queries.
You created finops-baseline.txt with your starting spend.
Series two. The waste audit.
You migrated gp2 volumes to gp3. You released unattached Elastic IPs.
You cleaned up stopped instances and unattached volumes.
You added VPC Endpoints for S3 and DynamoDB.
You identified thousands of dollars in monthly waste.
Series three. Kubecost.
You deployed Kubecost on EKS. You saw cost per namespace.
You applied rightsizing recommendations.
Series four. Karpenter.
You deployed Karpenter. You enabled continuous consolidation.
Your compute costs dropped by thirty-five percent.
Series five. Spot engineering.
You implemented checkpointing for ML workloads.
You added Pod Disruption Budgets.
Your ML compute costs dropped by seventy to ninety percent.
Series six. Storage and databases.
You added S3 lifecycle policies. ECR lifecycle policies.
RDS stop and start schedules. Reserved instances.
Series seven. IDP fundamentals.
You learned what an Internal Developer Platform is.
You installed Backstage.
Series eight. Scaffolder.
You built the golden path template.
A developer can create a cost-optimized service in ninety seconds.
Series nine. Day-two operations.
You added scaling, rollback, and log streaming to the catalog.
Series ten. FinOps integration.
You added cost dashboards, budget alerts, and chargeback reports.
Now it is time to put it all together.
Before we start the capstone, ensure your environment is clean.
You want a fresh start so you can measure savings accurately.
Step one. Create a fresh AWS account for the capstone.
Use AWS Organizations to create a new account in your existing organization.
Or create a new AWS account from scratch.
Step two. Deploy the financial-rag-agent and riskoracle workloads.
These are the production applications we have been using throughout the course.
git clone both repositories.
Use Terraform to deploy them to the new account.
Step three. Run the baseline audit.
This is the same command you ran in Series one.
It gives you your starting total monthly cost.
Write this number down. It is your before picture.
For the startup in our story, it was forty-seven thousand dollars per month.
Your number will be different. That is fine.
We are measuring your improvement, not an absolute number.
Now let's run through the optimization phases in sequence.
Each phase builds on the last. Do not skip any.
Phase two. Waste audit.
First, find and migrate all gp2 volumes to gp3.
Run the describe-volumes command for gp2 volumes.
If you see any, run the bulk migration command.
One command. Zero downtime. Twenty percent savings.
Second, find and release unattached Elastic IPs.
Run the describe-addresses command for unattached EIPs.
For each one, run the release-address command.
Third, find and terminate stopped instances.
Run the describe-instances command for state stopped.
For each instance, create a snapshot of its volumes.
Then terminate the instance.
Fourth, find and delete unattached EBS volumes.
Run the describe-volumes command for status available.
For each volume, create a snapshot, then delete the volume.
Fifth, add VPC Endpoints for S3 and DynamoDB.
Get your VPC ID. Get your route table IDs.
Create gateway endpoints for S3 and DynamoDB.
This makes S3 and DynamoDB traffic completely free.
Instead of going through expensive NAT Gateway.
Run the waste summary script.
It will show you the total waste identified.
Write this number down. This is your Phase two savings.
Phase three. Kubecost and rightsizing.
Deploy Kubecost on EKS.
helm repo add kubecost. helm repo update.
helm install kubecost with AWS integration enabled.
Wait for all pods to be running.
Port-forward to the Kubecost dashboard.
Explore the allocation page. See cost per namespace.
Run the rightsizing recommendations command.
Get the list of deployments with overprovisioned CPU and memory.
Apply the recommendations one at a time.
Patch each deployment with the recommended CPU and memory requests.
After each change, watch for CPU throttling.
kubectl top pods to check usage.
Check the throttle metrics from Prometheus.
After applying all recommendations, check the cluster efficiency.
Kubecost should show improved efficiency scores.
Financial-rag might go from 0.48 to 0.72.
Phase four. Karpenter.
First, remove the Cluster Autoscaler if it is running.
kubectl delete deployment cluster-autoscaler.
Create the IAM role for Karpenter.
Attach the controller policy.
Create the trust policy for IRSA.
Install Karpenter via Helm.
Set the cluster name and interruption queue.
Create the EC2NodeClass.
Set the AMI family to AL2023.
Set the role to the Karpenter node role.
Add subnet and security group selector terms.
Create the NodePools.
Application NodePool with both On-Demand and Spot.
Ingestion NodePool with Spot only.
GPU NodePool for ML workloads with Spot preferred.
Tag your subnets and security groups.
Karpenter discovers them by tag.
Add tolerations to your workloads.
Application pods get the dedicated application toleration.
Ingestion pods get the dedicated ingestion toleration and Spot toleration.
Watch consolidation in action.
Scale down a deployment. Karpenter consolidates within thirty seconds.
Node count drops. Compute cost drops.
Phase five. Spot engineering for ML workloads.
First, create an S3 checkpoint bucket.
Enable versioning. Enable server-side encryption with KMS.
Add a lifecycle policy to keep only the last three checkpoints per job.
Add the CheckpointManager class to your training code.
It saves model weights, optimizer state, and epoch number to S3 every ten minutes.
It handles SIGTERM signals from Karpenter during Spot interruptions.
Add the SpotTerminationWatcher.
It polls the IMDS metadata service every five seconds.
When an interruption is detected, it triggers a final checkpoint save.
Run a training job on Spot.
Set the tolerations to allow Spot.
Set the backoffLimit to ten.
Simulate an interruption by terminating the Spot node.
Watch the checkpoint manager save a final checkpoint.
Watch the Kubernetes Job restart on a new node.
Watch the training resume from the checkpoint.
Phase six. Storage and database cost controls.
Add S3 lifecycle policies to all buckets.
For each bucket without a policy, apply the default policy.
Transition to Standard-IA at thirty days.
Transition to Glacier Instant Retrieval at ninety days.
Transition to Deep Archive at three hundred sixty-five days.
Expire at seven hundred thirty days.
Add ECR lifecycle policies to all repositories.
Delete untagged images after fourteen days.
Keep only the last twenty images total.
Keep only the last five images per feature branch.
Deploy the RDS stop and start Lambda.
Tag your development databases with Schedule equals dev-hours.
The Lambda stops them at 8 PM weekdays.
It starts them at 8 AM weekdays.
Purchase RDS Reserved Instances for production databases.
Get recommendations from Cost Explorer.
Buy a one-year No Upfront reservation for your production database.
Monthly cost drops by approximately forty percent.
Phase seven through ten. Deploy the IDP and integrate FinOps.
Install Backstage.
Create a new Backstage app. Configure PostgreSQL.
Add the Kubernetes plugin. Add the ArgoCD plugin.
Register your services in the catalog.
Create catalog-info.yaml files for financial-rag-agent and riskoracle.
Add annotations for GitHub, ArgoCD, Kubecost, and FinOps budget.
Deploy the golden path template.
Create the microservice template with FinOps optimizations.
Resource requests by traffic tier. Spot tolerations for low traffic.
S3 lifecycle policy. ECR lifecycle policy. Cost estimate before creation.
Add day-two operations.
Scale template with cost impact display.
Rollback template with GitOps integration.
Log streaming in the catalog.
Integrate FinOps into the IDP.
Add the FinOps backend plugin with cost, rightsizing, dashboard,
anomaly webhook, and chargeback endpoints.
Add the CostDashboard frontend component to the catalog.
Add the FinOps homepage dashboard.
Schedule the budget alerts to run daily at 9 AM.
Test an alert by temporarily lowering a budget threshold.
Now let's create a new service through the golden path.
Open the Backstage portal.
Navigate to Create. Select Microservice with FinOps Optimized.
Fill out the form.
Name. fraud-detection-service.
Team. team-financial-rag.
Traffic. medium.
Database. false.
Cache. false.
S3. true.
Environment. production.
Click Create.
Watch the scaffolder run in real time.
After thirty seconds, the scaffolder completes.
GitHub repository created. Dockerfile generated. Helm chart generated.
ArgoCD application created. S3 bucket created with lifecycle policy.
Service registered in the catalog. Cost estimate shown before creation.
Push code to the new repository.
Clone the repo. Add a simple FastAPI endpoint.
Commit and push to main.
Watch GitHub Actions build the multi-arch image.
Amd64 and arm64. The build takes about three minutes.
Watch ArgoCD sync the application.
The sync takes about forty-five seconds.
Check the catalog.
The new service appears. Click the Cost tab.
It shows estimated cost. The data will populate within twenty-four hours.
Total time from click to running pod. About four point five minutes.
Developer touched only Backstage UI.
Zero kubectl commands. Zero platform team tickets.
Now trigger a budget alert.
Edit the catalog-info.yaml for fraud-detection-service.
Set finops slash monthly-budget to one dollar.
Set finops slash alert-webhook to your Slack webhook URL.
Commit and push.
Run the budget scheduler manually.
curl to the budget alert endpoint to trigger an immediate check.
Check your Slack channel.
You should see a budget alert message.
It shows current spend, budget, remaining budget, days left in month.
It includes buttons to view the Cost Dashboard and Rightsizing.
Now generate the final chargeback report.
curl to the chargeback endpoint with format equals csv.
Download the file. Open it in your spreadsheet application.
The report shows each team's total cost, budget, percent of budget,
average efficiency, and service count.
This is what your finance team sees every month.
No surprises. No manual spreadsheets. Just data.
Now let's calculate your final savings.
Run the baseline audit command again.
Get your current total monthly cost.
Calculate the difference.
Baseline cost minus current cost equals monthly savings.
Monthly savings times twelve equals annual savings.
For the startup in our story.
Baseline was forty-seven thousand dollars.
Final cost was nineteen thousand four hundred four dollars.
Monthly savings. Twenty-seven thousand five hundred ninety-six dollars.
Annual savings. Three hundred thirty-one thousand one hundred fifty-two dollars.
Update your finops-baseline.txt with all the final numbers.
Add the baseline audit results.
Add the waste audit summary.
Add the Kubecost efficiency improvements.
Add the Karpenter node count reduction.
Add the Spot savings percentage.
Add the storage and database savings.
Add the IDP adoption metrics.
Add the final total savings.
This document is your proof of impact.
You can show it to your CTO, your CFO, your entire engineering organization.
Finally, commit your platform configuration to Git.
Create a new repository called idp-configuration.
Commit the Backstage app configuration.
Commit the Scaffolder templates.
Commit the Terraform modules.
Commit the FinOps plugin code.
Commit the catalog-info.yaml files.
Commit the golden path documentation.
Push the repository to GitHub.
Now your entire platform is in Git.
Every change is tracked. Every configuration is versioned.
Let me recap what you have accomplished in this capstone.
You started from a fresh AWS account.
You ran the complete FinOps optimization pipeline from Series two through six.
Gp2 to gp3 migration. Unattached resource cleanup. VPC Endpoints.
Kubecost deployment and rightsizing.
Karpenter deployment with consolidation and Spot.
Spot engineering for ML workloads with checkpointing.
S3, ECR, and RDS lifecycle controls.
Reserved instances for production databases.
You deployed the full IDP from Series seven through ten.
Backstage with catalog, scaffolder, and day-two operations.
FinOps integration with cost dashboards, budget alerts, and chargeback.
You created a new service through the golden path.
From click to running pod in four point five minutes.
Zero kubectl. Zero platform tickets. All cost controls applied automatically.
You triggered a budget alert and saw the Slack notification.
You generated the final chargeback report.
You calculated your total savings.
And you committed everything to Git.
So your organization can replicate what you have built.
This is what production FinOps engineering looks like.
Not a one-time audit. Not a dashboard that nobody looks at.
A sustainable system that continuously optimizes cloud costs.
Where new engineers use the golden path without thinking about cost.
Where budget alerts catch drift before it compounds.
Where the platform team is measured by adoption, not ticket volume.
You have built this system. From scratch.
From a single terminal to a production Internal Developer Platform.
Congratulations on completing the FinOps and Internal Developer Platform course.
You have learned.
Unit economics and tagging strategy.
The waste audit that finds hidden dollars.
Kubecost for Kubernetes cost visibility.
Karpenter for continuous compute optimization.
Spot instance engineering for seventy percent savings on ML workloads.
Storage and database lifecycle controls.
Platform engineering and Internal Developer Platforms.
Golden paths that bake FinOps into every new service.
Day-two operations through the IDP.
FinOps integration with cost dashboards, budget alerts, and chargeback.
And a capstone that proves everything works together.
You are now in the top one percent of engineers.
The ones who understand not just cloud costs, but cloud economics.
The ones who can build platforms that make FinOps invisible to developers
and omnipresent in their workflow.
Take your finops-baseline.txt. Take your IDP configuration.
Take these skills to your organization.
Go save money. Go build platforms. Go change how engineering works.
Thank you for taking this course.
I will see you in the next one.
```
---
**END OF PHASE 11 — SERIES 11 CAPSTONE**
**Total SRT lines:** 212
**Total duration:** Approximately 60-70 minutes
**What is covered in this SRT:**
| Section | Lines | Description |
|---------|-------|-------------|
| Opening & Course Recap | 1-28 | Reminder of all 10 previous phases |
| Fresh Account Setup | 29-40 | Clean AWS account, deploy workloads, baseline audit |
| Phase 2 Waste Audit | 41-56 | gp2 migration, EIP release, stopped instances, unattached volumes, VPC endpoints |
| Phase 3 Kubecost & Rightsizing | 57-68 | Deploy Kubecost, get recommendations, patch deployments, verify efficiency |
| Phase 4 Karpenter | 69-85 | Remove Cluster Autoscaler, IAM role, install, EC2NodeClass, NodePools, consolidation |
| Phase 5 Spot Engineering | 86-96 | S3 checkpoint bucket, CheckpointManager, SpotTerminationWatcher, test interruption |
| Phase 6 Storage & Database | 97-105 | S3 lifecycle, ECR lifecycle, RDS stop/start Lambda, Reserved Instances |
| Phases 7-10 IDP & FinOps | 106-119 | Backstage install, catalog registration, golden path template, day-two ops, FinOps integration, budget scheduler |
| Create New Service Through Golden Path | 120-139 | Scaffolder, code push, GitHub Actions, ArgoCD sync, catalog verification |
| Trigger Budget Alert | 140-148 | Set low budget, run scheduler, verify Slack notification |
| Generate Chargeback Report | 149-154 | CSV download for finance team |
| Calculate Final Savings | 155-164 | Baseline vs final, monthly and annual savings |
| Commit to Git | 171-177 | IDP configuration repository |
| Recap & Congratulations | 178-212 | Summary of accomplishments, final words |
---
**TOTAL FINOPS COURSE DURATION — ALL 11 PHASES**
| Phase | Duration |
|-------|----------|
| Phase 1 | 90 minutes |
| Phase 2 | 120 minutes |
| Phase 3 | 90 minutes |
| Phase 4 | 90 minutes |
| Phase 5 | 90 minutes |
| Phase 6 | 90 minutes |
| Phase 7 | 90 minutes |
| Phase 8 | 90 minutes |
| Phase 9 | 90 minutes |
| Phase 10 | 90 minutes |
| Phase 11 | 70 minutes |
| **Total** | **~17-18 hours** |
---
**END OF COMPLETE FINOPS + IDP COURSE**