Learning cloud cost optimization can feel overwhelming.
So many services, so many pricing models, and the endless acronyms.
RI, SP, EBS, NAT, Karpenter, Kubecost, VPA, EKS, RDS, S3.
It's enough to make anyone feel stuck.
Your eyes glaze over. You close the billing dashboard.
You tell yourself you'll look at it next month.
But next month comes and the number is bigger.
And you still don't understand why.
But what if there was one best bet?
One framework that not only saves your startup thousands of dollars.
But makes you the person who actually understands
where every dollar goes.
The person the CTO asks when the bill arrives.
The person who doesn't flinch at the number
because they already know what's in it.
That's FinOps.
Hi there, and welcome to a course where I'm going to take you
from a complete FinOps beginner to a confident cloud economist.
No endless theory. No aimless command copying.
No watching someone else type commands
while you nod along and forget everything five minutes later.
This is about saving real money
while truly understanding where it's going.
This is about building something real while actually understanding it.
Not just running commands, but knowing why each command matters.
Not just copying from a blog post,
but being able to explain it to your team.
Starting from what FinOps is and why you should learn it.
To how cloud billing works under the hood.
Unit economics fundamentals. Tagging strategy.
AWS Cost Explorer basics.
And finally, we're going to build a cost baseline document
that shows exactly what every team spends,
every service costs, and every region is burning money.
By the end of this crash course,
you won't just know FinOps.
You will have created a cost allocation framework
you can show your CTO.
You will have a document that proves you understand
the cloud bill better than anyone else on your team.
You will have the confidence to open that AWS bill
on the 3rd of the month and know exactly what you're looking at.
But that's not all.
For those ready to dive even deeper,
I've put together a free guide and a comprehensive FinOps plus IDP course.
Designed to take you from zero to production-ready.
Whether it's learning Kubecost cost attribution,
Karpenter right-sizing, or Backstage golden path templates.
This course will help you build and deploy platforms like a pro.
You can find all the links in the description below.
But for now, let's dive into the video.
Together we're going to build an awesome cost visibility platform.
Using real production stacks, financial-rag-agent and riskoracle,
to handle FinOps tracking seamlessly.
Let's get started.
FinOps is a game changer.
A cloud cost discipline created by the FinOps Foundation.
It powers some of the smartest engineering organizations
in the world.
Companies like Uber, Spotify, and Airbnb
don't guess at their cloud costs. They have FinOps practices.
They have dedicated teams. They have frameworks.
FinOps is maintained by a strong open-source community
constantly innovating with new features like real-time cost visibility.
Which simplifies your cloud financial workflow
by showing you exactly where every dollar goes, in real time.
Without waiting for the monthly bill to arrive.
And it might seem like FinOps is just borrowing
your finance team's homework for building cost-conscious infrastructure.
Like, isn't this what the finance department is supposed to do?
But it's more like FinOps is peeking at their notes,
modernizing them, adding automation.
Adding real-time data, adding developer self-service.
So you spend less time reinventing the basics of cost tracking.
And more time building amazing products
that actually make money.
Of course, FinOps isn't alone.
Tools like CloudHealth, Vantage, and OpenCost
are also making waves in the cloud cost space.
They each have their strengths.
CloudHealth is great for enterprises with thousands of accounts.
Vantage has a beautiful UI.
OpenCost is open source and free.
But when it comes to popularity, Kubecost dominates.
Just look at the numbers.
Thousands of engineering teams have adopted Kubecost
as their Kubernetes cost visibility tool.
It has topped the cloud-native surveys for consecutive years
as the FinOps tool of choice.
The Cloud Native Computing Foundation, which runs KubeCon,
the biggest Kubernetes conference in the world.
Has featured Kubecost in their landscape
as a leading FinOps tool. And with good reason.
Let me tell you why.
FinOps is built on three phases.
Phase one is Inform. This is about visibility.
You cannot optimize what you cannot see.
You cannot fix what you cannot measure.
You cannot save money on a service you don't know exists.
So Phase one is all about getting data.
Tagging your resources so you know who owns what.
Setting up Cost Explorer so you can query your spend.
Deploying Kubecost so you can see cost per namespace,
cost per pod, cost per team.
Knowing which team spent what on which service
in which region at which time of day.
Phase two is Optimize. This is about action.
Once you can see the waste, you need to eliminate it.
Rightsizing EC2 instances that are twice as big
as they need to be.
Migrating gp2 volumes to gp3 for an instant 20% savings.
Buying Savings Plans for your stable workloads.
Running Karpenter to continuously consolidate your EKS nodes.
Actually reducing the number on the bill.
Phase three is Operate. This is about continuity.
Because here's the thing about cloud waste. It comes back.
You rightsize an instance today.
And three months later someone deploys a new service
and forgets to set resource limits.
You add lifecycle policies to S3.
And next quarter someone creates a new bucket
and forgets to add the policy.
You tag everything. And a new intern spins up a test instance
with no tags.
So Phase three is about making sure the waste never comes back.
Budget alerts that email you when spend exceeds a threshold.
AWS Config rules that flag untagged resources automatically.
Terraform guardrails that prevent non-compliant resources
from being created in the first place.
IDP cost visibility that shows developers the impact of their deploy
before they click the button.
Most courses only teach Phase two.
They show you how to rightsize an instance and call it done.
They give you a few commands, show you a few dashboards,
and send you on your way.
But without Phase one, you don't know what to rightsize.
You're just guessing.
You might rightsize the wrong instance.
You might miss the biggest cost driver entirely.
You might save two hundred dollars
when you could have saved two thousand.
And without Phase three, the waste creeps back in.
You do all this work, you feel great about yourself.
And then three months later you're right back where you started.
The bill is high again. The waste is back.
And you have to do the whole thing over.
This course teaches all three phases.
On real EKS workloads. With Kubecost, Karpenter, and Backstage.
On financial-rag-agent and riskoracle.
Two production systems I built specifically for this course.
Now let me show you what makes FinOps so powerful
with a project that I made specifically for this course.
I built this project to help you visually understand
cost optimization patterns in practice.
And it's built entirely on real EKS workloads.
This isn't some toy application with fake data.
This is a real RAG system that answers questions
about financial documents.
This is a real MLOps risk engine that processes batch jobs.
This dashboard showcases real-time cost updates.
You won't see a monthly billing surprise or a shocked CTO.
Even when different teams deploy different services,
everything gets attributed dynamically to the right namespace
and the right team.
The financial-rag team sees their cost.
The riskoracle team sees their cost.
Nobody sees anyone else's cost unless they're supposed to.
That's how FinOps uses Kubecost and the cost allocation model
to make it all possible.
The cost allocation model is like a simplified map
of your cloud spend.
It's a data structure that mirrors every dollar leaving
your account.
Every EC2 instance, every EBS volume, every S3 request,
every NAT Gateway data transfer.
All of it mapped to a namespace, a team, a service, an environment.
Here's why it's a revolution.
Before Kubecost, you had to wait for the monthly AWS bill.
Then you had to download a CSV file with 47 columns of usage types
you didn't understand.
Then you had to manually map instance IDs to services.
Then you had to guess which team owned which resource.
It took days. By the time you had answers,
the month was over and a new bill had arrived.
With Kubecost, when something changes in your cluster,
a new deployment, a scaled pod, a data transfer spike.
Kubecost creates a new cost allocation element in real time.
It then compares it to the historical baseline
to pinpoint the difference.
And only the changed portion of your budget is flagged
for review.
Making FinOps blazingly fast.
Think of it as updating a single tile in a mosaic
instead of repainting the entire wall.
You don't need to recalculate everything from scratch
every time. You just update what changed.
And FinOps doesn't demand much.
Just a solid understanding of cloud basics.
So if you're unsure about concepts like EKS,
which is Amazon's managed Kubernetes service.
Or VPC, which is your virtual private cloud inside AWS.
Or IAM roles, which control who can do what.
Pause this video right now and go check out my complete
AWS Mastery course. I'll link it in the description.
It will make sure you have all the necessary prerequisite knowledge
to be able to get the most out of this course.
And for a more focused approach, or if you want to have
a reference guide always available.
Download my free ultimate FinOps guide.
It's linked in the description.
Packed with prerequisites, core concepts, command cheat sheets,
and project ideas to get you started.
It's the guide I wish I had when I started learning FinOps.
And now that you understand what FinOps is
and why it's so popular.
Let me teach you the fundamentals.
We'll start with unit economics and tagging.
Then slowly move towards building our amazing
cost visibility platform.
So, are you ready to optimize?
Before we dive into the commands,
let me introduce you to the two production stacks
that we'll be using throughout this course.
Because you're not learning on hypothetical examples.
You're not optimizing some fake application
that doesn't exist in the real world.
You're learning on real systems
that real startups run every day.
First is financial-rag-agent.
RAG stands for Retrieval Augmented Generation.
It's the tech behind ChatGPT-style chatbots
that can answer questions about your own private data.
Think of it as ChatGPT but trained on your company's SEC filings,
earnings reports, investor updates.
Internal documentation, customer support tickets,
whatever you want.
So financial-rag-agent is a system that answers questions
about financial documents.
You ask it "what was our revenue last quarter"
and it goes and finds the answer in your earnings report.
You ask it "what's our burn rate"
and it calculates it from your financial statements.
You ask it "show me all the risks mentioned
in the last board deck" and it extracts them.
This is the kind of AI workload
that every startup is building right now.
If you're not building a RAG system today,
you probably will be within the next 12 months.
And RAG systems are expensive.
They use large language models.
They use vector databases. They use GPU instances.
They generate a lot of data transfer.
Understanding how to optimize the cost of a RAG system
is a superpower.
Second is riskoracle.
This is an MLOps risk calculation engine.
It processes batch jobs. It runs GPU workloads
for risk modeling.
It does the kind of number-crunching
that financial services companies need.
It's resource-intensive, variable,
and perfect for Spot instance optimization.
Riskoracle doesn't need to run 24/7.
It can run on Spot instances that are 70% cheaper
than on-demand.
It can tolerate interruptions because batch jobs
can restart.
It's the perfect candidate for the kind of optimization
we'll do in Series five.
Both of these stacks are running on EKS,
Amazon's managed Kubernetes service.
Both have real cost patterns.
Both are on GitHub at aayostem slash financial-rag-agent
and aayostem slash riskoracle.
You can clone them. You can deploy them
in your own AWS account.
You can break them. You can optimize them.
And you will see your savings in real numbers.
Not estimated savings. Not projected savings.
Actual Kubecost output with real data from your own account.
Now let's get your machine ready.
Before you can run your first FinOps command,
you need the right tools installed on your machine.
This is the boring but essential part.
Every course has it. You can't skip it.
But I promise we'll get through it quickly.
First, you need the AWS CLI installed.
AWS CLI stands for Amazon Web Services
Command Line Interface.
It's a command-line tool that allows you to interact
with AWS services directly from your terminal.
No clicking around the AWS console.
No searching for buttons.
Just commands that do exactly what you tell them to do.
This is essential because FinOps involves running
cost analysis tools and scripts on your local machine.
You're going to query Cost Explorer.
You're going to tag resources.
You're going to generate reports.
And all of these tasks require the AWS CLI to function.
So head over to aws.amazon.com slash cli.
Download the latest version.
Depending on your operating system,
you can install it via package manager.
On Mac, that's brew install awscli.
On Ubuntu, that's sudo apt install awscli.
On Windows, download the installer and run it.
When you install the AWS CLI,
you'll also get access to a handy tool called AWS Cost Explorer.
Instead of waiting for the monthly bill to arrive
in your email.
You can use Cost Explorer to query your spend in real time.
You can ask it how much you spent on EC2 last week.
You can ask it which region is most expensive.
You can ask it to show you cost by tag,
by service, by hour, by day, by month.
Cost Explorer also makes it super easy
to keep your cost data up to date.
It pulls directly from AWS billing.
There's no delay. No manual exports. No CSV files.
You run a command and you get the answer.
In simple terms, Cost Explorer will save you time and money
by giving you access to real spend data.
So you can optimize your cloud more efficiently.
Without Cost Explorer, you're flying blind.
With Cost Explorer, you have x-ray vision
into your AWS bill.
Second, you'll need a code editor.
There are many code editors out there.
VS Code, IntelliJ, Sublime, Vim, Emacs.
Whichever one you choose, you'll be good.
I prefer VS Code with the AWS Toolkit extension.
It's a fully-fledged IDE designed specifically for cloud development.
It offers you everything you need.
Quick terminal access right inside the editor.
Error reporting that highlights syntax problems
before you run the command.
An integrated AWS explorer that shows your resources
without leaving VS Code. And more.
Plus, it's completely free.
Third, Terraform. And speaking of infrastructure as code.
While it's not mandatory to have Terraform installed
to start learning FinOps.
It is absolutely essential for your growth
as a platform engineer or any kind of cloud engineer
for that matter.
It's a non-negotiable.
Terraform is how you define your infrastructure in code.
Instead of clicking around the AWS console
to create an EC2 instance.
You write a few lines of Terraform configuration
and run terraform apply.
Instead of manually tagging 50 resources,
you define the tags once and Terraform applies them
to everything.
So go ahead. Google download Terraform.
Head over to their website. Install it on your device.
It takes two minutes.
And if you're new to Terraform,
I've already done a Terraform tutorial
which I'll link somewhere in this video.
It covers variables, resources, modules, state management.
Everything you need to know.
So if you want to do that too before proceeding
with this FinOps course.
Pause this video right now, go watch that tutorial,
and then come back.
But with that in mind, now that we have all the tools necessary.
We are ready to verify that everything works.
Open your terminal.
This is where all the magic happens.
Every command in this course runs from the terminal.
First, run this command.
aws sts get-caller-identity
STS stands for Security Token Service.
Get caller identity is an API that returns information
about the AWS user or role that is currently authenticated.
In plain English, this command asks AWS "who am I?"
The output should look something like this.
A UserId, an Account number, and an ARN.
The most important field here is Account.
That 12-digit number is your AWS account ID. Write it down.
You'll need it.
If you see your account ID, you're ready.
The AWS CLI is installed correctly.
Your credentials are configured. You have access.
Troubleshooting.
If you get an error that says "Unable to locate credentials".
That means you haven't configured the AWS CLI yet.
Run aws configure and enter your Access Key ID,
Secret Access Key, default region, and default output format.
You can get your Access Key ID and Secret Access Key
from the AWS console under IAM > Users > Security credentials.
If you get an error that says "Access denied".
That means your credentials exist but don't have permission
to call this API.
You need at least read access to Cost Explorer and EC2
for this course.
For now, I recommend attaching the AWSBillingReadOnlyAccess
and AmazonEC2ReadOnlyAccess managed policies to your IAM user.
You can do this in the AWS console under IAM > Users >
Add permissions.
Once you see your account ID, export these environment variables.
Environment variables are like global settings
that every command can see.
You set them once at the beginning of your session
and every command after that can use them.
export ACCOUNT_ID equals aws sts get-caller-identity
with query Account output text.
export REGION equals us-east-1.
export START equals date minus d 30 days ago plus YYYY-MM-DD.
export END equals date plus YYYY-MM-DD.
Important note for macOS users.
The date command on macOS is different.
Instead of date minus d 30 days ago,
use date minus v minus 30d.
Let me explain each one.
ACCOUNT_ID is your AWS account ID.
We're using a subshell trick here.
The dollar sign parentheses syntax runs the command
inside the parentheses and substitutes its output.
REGION is the AWS region you're working in.
us-east-1 is Northern Virginia.
If your resources are in a different region, change this.
START is the beginning of your cost lookback period.
We're using date dash d 30 days ago.
Which calculates the date 30 days before today.
END is today's date in the same format.
Now verify that these variables are set correctly.
echo dollar sign ACCOUNT_ID.
echo dollar sign REGION.
echo dollar sign START.
echo dollar sign END.
You should see your account ID, your region, and two dates.
Now let's verify Cost Explorer access.
Run this command.
aws ce get-cost-and-usage with time period
Start equals START, End equals END.
Granularity MONTHLY, metrics BlendedCost.
Query results by time zero total blended cost amount.
Output text.
This command returns your total spend for the last 30 days.
If you see a number, even if it's zero, you have Cost Explorer access.
Write this number down. It's your baseline.
This is the number you're going to reduce over the next 10 series.
Troubleshooting.
If you get an error that says "Invalid time period".
Check that your START and END variables are set correctly.
Run echo dollar sign START and echo dollar sign END.
They should be dates in YYYY-MM-DD format.
If you get an error that says "Access denied"
or "Unauthorized operation".
Your IAM user doesn't have permission to call Cost Explorer.
Go back to the AWS console and add the AWSBillingReadOnlyAccess
policy.
Now you're ready for unit economics.
Now let me show you what unit economics actually means.
Because this is the concept that separates
senior engineers from junior engineers.
Senior engineers talk about unit economics.
Junior engineers talk about the AWS bill.
In simple terms, unit economics is the answer
to one question.
What does one unit of your business cost?
If you're running a RAG application,
the unit is one RAG query.
A user asks a question. The system retrieves
relevant documents.
The language model generates an answer.
That whole process from question to answer is one unit.
If you're running an API, the unit is one API call.
A client sends a request. The server processes it.
The server sends a response.
That round trip is one unit.
If you're running a batch job, the unit is one job execution.
The job starts. It processes data.
It writes results. It finishes.
That complete execution is one unit.
Here's why this matters.
Most engineering teams look at their AWS bill
and see $47,832.45.
That number is useless.
It doesn't tell you if you're efficient.
It doesn't tell you if that new feature you shipped
made things better or worse.
It doesn't tell you if you're spending too much
or too little. It's just a number.
But if you know that one RAG query costs $0.002,
that's two-tenths of a cent. Now you have something.
Now you can do math.
You can answer. We processed two million queries this month.
At $0.002 each, that's $4,000.
Our total bill is $12,000.
Where is the other $8,000 going?
That question is the beginning of FinOps.
That question leads you to investigate.
You look at the breakdown by service.
You see that NAT Gateway is costing you $2,000.
You see that you have five unattached Elastic IPs
costing you $18.
You see that you have stopped instances
with EBS volumes costing you $300.
Now you have a plan.
Now you know exactly what to fix and in what order.
That's the power of unit economics.
Write this formula down.
Cost per unit equals total monthly infrastructure cost
divided by number of units processed.
For financial-rag-agent, your unit is a RAG query.
For riskoracle, your unit is a risk calculation.
By the end of this course, you will have both numbers.
And you will know exactly how to improve them.
Now let me walk you through a real example
from an actual deployment of financial-rag-agent.
This client processes about 500,000 RAG queries per month.
That's about 16,000 queries per day.
That's about 11 queries per minute.
It's a moderately busy system.
Not huge, but not tiny either.
Their total AWS bill is $8,400 per month.
Let me calculate their cost per query.
Total cost divided by total queries.
$8,400 divided by 500,000 equals $0.0168 per query.
That's 1.68 cents per query.
Let me break down where that 1.68 cents per query goes.
This is the detail that most people never see.
Here is the cost breakdown per query table.
EC2 compute for LLM inference: 0.8 cents per query.
48 percent of the total.
RDS for the vector database: 0.3 cents per query.
18 percent of the total.
NAT Gateway plus data transfer: 0.2 cents per query.
12 percent of the total.
EKS control plane: 0.2 cents per query.
S3 for document storage: 0.1 cents per query.
6 percent of the total.
Other services like CloudWatch and ECR: 0.08 cents per query.
4 percent of the total.
The large language model that generates answers
runs on GPU instances. GPUs are expensive.
This is the biggest line item at 48 percent.
Is 1.68 cents good or bad?
It depends on what you charge.
If they're charging their customers 10 cents per query,
their cost is 1.68 cents.
Their margin is 8.32 cents per query.
That's an 83% margin. That's great.
If they're charging their customers 2 cents per query,
their cost is 1.68 cents.
Their margin is 0.32 cents per query.
That's a 16% margin.
They're barely breaking even.
One small mistake and they're losing money.
Now look at the biggest line item.
EC2 compute at 48 percent.
That's where Karpenter and Spot instances
will have the biggest impact.
If you can reduce EC2 cost by 35 percent using
Karpenter consolidation, that reduces the total cost per query
from 1.68 cents to 1.42 cents.
If you can run some workloads on Spot instances
at 70 percent off, that reduces the total even further.
If you can eliminate NAT Gateway costs entirely
using VPC endpoints, that's another 12 percent reduction.
After implementing all the optimizations in this course,
that client reduced their cost per query to 0.98 cents.
That's a 42 percent reduction.
Their margin at 10 cents per query went from 83 percent to 90 percent.
That's the difference between a startup that survives
and a startup that thrives.
Now let me show you why this number matters
to your CTO.
Your CTO cares about two things.
Shipping features and not running out of money.
Unit economics is the bridge between them.
Here's the conversation you can have after this course.
You walk into the CTO's office.
You say, "Our cost per RAG query is 1.68 cents."
The CTO looks at you. "Is that good?" they ask.
You say, "It's okay. But I can get it to 0.9 cents
by next quarter."
The CTO leans forward. "How?"
You say, "Karpenter consolidation on EKS will cut EC2 cost
by 35 percent."
"Spot instances for batch processing will save
another 15 percent. VPC endpoints eliminate NAT Gateway costs
entirely."
"And I'm going to bake cost visibility into the IDP
so every team sees their impact before they deploy."
The CTO says, "Do it."
That's the conversation. Not "we need to save money."
Not "cloud is too expensive."
Just data, a plan, and a number.
That's what unit economics gives you.
Now let me show you how to calculate this for yourself.
First, get your total monthly cost.
You already have this from the verification step.
TOTAL_COST equals aws ce get-cost-and-usage with time period
Start END granularity MONTHLY metrics BlendedCost.
Query results by time zero total blended cost amount.
Output text.
echo "Total monthly AWS cost: dollar sign TOTAL_COST"
Second, get your total number of RAG queries.
This assumes you're logging each query to CloudWatch.
If you're not, we'll set this up in Series 8
when we build the IDP.
TOTAL_QUERIES equals aws cloudwatch get-metric-statistics
with namespace financial-rag-agent.
Metric name QueryCount. Start time START T 00:00:00Z.
End time END T 00:00:00Z.
Period 2592000. Statistics Sum.
Query datapoints zero sum. Output text.
echo "Total monthly RAG queries: dollar sign TOTAL_QUERIES"
Third, calculate the cost per query.
echo "Cost per RAG query: " with scale 6 and TOTAL_COST divided by TOTAL_QUERIES using bc.
If you don't have CloudWatch metrics set up yet,
don't worry. We'll add them in Series 8.
For now, just understand the concept.
Because every decision you make in this course.
Every rightsizing, every Karpenter consolidation,
every Spot instance, every VPC endpoint.
Should be evaluated against this number.
Does this change reduce cost per query?
If yes, do it. If no, ask why.
That's how senior engineers think about cloud cost.
Now let's talk about the mechanism that makes
unit economics possible.
The thing that lets you break down your total bill
into cost per team, cost per service, cost per environment.
That mechanism is tagging.
Now let's talk about tagging.
Tags are labels that you attach to AWS resources.
A tag is a key-value pair. The key is something like Environment.
The value is something like production.
So you tag an EC2 instance with Environment equals production.
You tag an S3 bucket with Team equals financial-rag.
You tag an RDS database with CostCenter equals engineering.
Here's the hard truth.
Without tags, you have no idea who spent what.
Without tags, you are flying blind.
Cost Explorer shows you EC2 cost.
But which team spun up those instances?
Was it the financial-rag team or the riskoracle team?
You don't know.
Cost Explorer shows you S3 cost.
But which service is generating all that data transfer?
Is it the LLM ingest service or the batch processing job?
You don't know.
Tags answer those questions.
Tags give you the dimensions you need to break down your bill.
Tags are how you move from total spend
to cost per team, cost per service, cost per environment.
Here's the tagging standard I use on every engagement.
I've used this at over 50 startups.
It works. It scales.
It's simple enough that everyone remembers it.
And comprehensive enough that you never find yourself
missing a dimension.
You are going to apply these six tags
to every resource in your account.
No exceptions.
Here is the six tags table.
Tag key: Environment. Example values: production, staging,
development, test. Purpose: Separate prod spend from test spend.
Tag key: Team. Example values: financial-rag, riskoracle,
platform. Purpose: Chargeback. Show each team their cost.
Tag key: Service. Example values: llm-ingest, risk-calc,
api-gateway. Purpose: Granular attribution per microservice.
Tag key: ManagedBy. Example values: terraform, kubecost,
manual. Purpose: Know who created and how to manage it.
Tag key: CostCenter. Example values: engineering,
data-science, product. Purpose: Roll up to your finance department.
Tag key: Owner. Example value: aayo at company.com.
Purpose: The person responsible. Who to ping.
The golden rule.
Every resource gets every tag. No exceptions.
Not some resources. Not most resources. Every resource.
EC2 instances, EBS volumes, RDS databases, S3 buckets.
Load balancers, Lambda functions, EKS clusters, everything.
Why so strict? Because the moment you allow
one untagged resource, you lose the ability
to trust your data.
Is that $500 of EC2 cost untagged
because it's shared infrastructure that belongs to everyone?
Or is it untagged because someone forgot?
You don't know.
And now your unit economics are wrong.
Now you can't trust your cost per team report.
Now you have to manually investigate every discrepancy.
Trust me. I've seen this happen.
A startup tags 99 percent of their resources.
They feel good about themselves.
They run a cost by team report. It looks great.
Then they discover that the 1 percent of untagged resources
accounts for 20 percent of their spend.
Their report was wrong. Their decisions were based
on wrong data.
They wasted weeks optimizing the wrong things.
Enforce the six tags. Enforce them strictly.
Enforce them from day one.
Now let me show you how to enforce them.
Step 1. Activate Tags for Cost Allocation.
First, let's see what tags you already have active
in your account for cost allocation.
Cost Explorer can only group by tags that are activated.
aws ce list-cost-allocation-tags with status Active.
Output table.
This shows you every tag that Cost Explorer knows about.
If your six tags aren't here, you need to activate them.
The command to activate a tag is.
aws ce update-cost-allocation-tags-status with tags Team
status Active.
Do this for each of the six tags.
Environment, Team, Service, ManagedBy, CostCenter, Owner.
Step 2. Find Untagged EC2 Instances.
Now let's find resources with no tags at all.
Start with EC2 instances.
aws ec2 describe-instances with query reservations
instances where tags length is zero.
Show ID, Type, State. Output table.
If this returns more than three rows, your cost allocation is broken.
Each row is an untagged EC2 instance.
Each instance is a blind spot in your cost visibility.
Step 3. Find Untagged S3 Buckets.
Now S3 buckets.
aws s3api list-buckets query buckets name output text.
Pipe to while loop.
For each bucket, get bucket tagging.
If tag set length is zero or null, print UNTAGGED S3 BUCKET.
This loops through every S3 bucket in your account.
For each bucket, it tries to get the tags.
If there are no tags, it prints the bucket name.
The 2 greater than dev null suppresses error messages.
For buckets that have no tagging at all.
Step 4. Find Untagged EBS Volumes.
Now EBS volumes.
aws ec2 describe-volumes query volumes where tags length zero.
Show ID, Size, Type. Output table.
Step 5. Find Untagged RDS Instances.
Now RDS instances.
aws rds describe-db-instances query DBInstances
where tag list length zero.
Show ID, Class, Engine. Output table.
Step 6. Find Untagged Load Balancers.
Now load balancers.
aws elbv2 describe-load-balancers query LoadBalancers
where tags length zero.
Show Name, Type, State. Output table.
Run all of these commands. Save the output.
This is your untagged inventory.
This is the list of resources that are currently invisible
to your cost allocation.
Now let's fix them.
Here's how to tag a single EC2 instance
with all six tags.
aws ec2 create-tags with resources i-1234567890abcdef0.
Tags Key=Environment,Value=production
Key=Team,Value=financial-rag Key=Service,Value=llm-ingest.
Key=ManagedBy,Value=terraform Key=CostCenter,Value=engineering
Key=Owner,Value=aayo at finops.com.
The create-tags command takes a list of resources
and a list of tags.
Each tag is a key-value pair.
You can tag up to 20 resources at once.
You can add up to 50 tags per resource.
But you don't want to do this one by one.
You have dozens or hundreds of resources.
You need a bulk tagging script.
Here's the complete bulk tagging script
that tags every EC2 instance in your account
with baseline tags.
aws ec2 describe-instances query instances instance ID
output text.
Pipe to while loop. For each ID, run create-tags
with the six required tags.
Environment production. Team unknown.
Service unknown. ManagedBy finops.
CostCenter engineering. Owner finops at yourcompany.com.
Echo "Tagged EC2: ID".
This does several things. First, it gets a list
of all EC2 instance IDs.
The query extracts just the IDs.
The output text formats them as plain text.
The tr converts tabs to newlines so each ID
is on its own line.
Then the while loop reads each ID
and runs the create-tags command.
The tags are set to baseline values.
Environment is production. Team and Service are unknown.
Because you need to fill those in manually.
ManagedBy is finops because you're the one tagging them.
CostCenter is engineering. Owner is your FinOps email address.
After this script runs, every EC2 instance has the six tags.
Then you go back and change the unknown values
to the real team and service names.
Now let's do the same for EBS volumes.
aws ec2 describe-volumes query volumes volume ID output text.
Pipe to while loop. For each ID, run create-tags.
Same tags. Echo "Tagged EBS: ID".
Now for RDS instances. Note that RDS uses a different command.
add-tags-to-resource instead of create-tags.
And the resource identifier is an ARN, not just an ID.
aws rds describe-db-instances query instances ARN output text.
Pipe to while loop. For each ARN, run add-tags-to-resource.
Same tags. Echo "Tagged RDS: ARN".
Now for load balancers.
aws elbv2 describe-load-balancers query load balancer ARN
output text. Pipe to while loop.
For each ARN, run add-tags with the same tags.
Echo "Tagged ALB: ARN".
After you run all of these scripts,
every resource in your account has baseline tags.
Now you need to go back and fill in the real team
and service names.
You can do this manually or you can write a script
that updates based on instance names or other metadata.
Now let's talk about preventing untagged resources
from being created in the future.
Because tagging everything retroactively is painful.
It's much better to never create an untagged resource
in the first place.
AWS Config is the service that continuously monitors
your resources for compliance.
You can create rules that flag any resource
missing required tags.
You can even block non-compliant resources
from being created.
Here's the Config rule for our six required tags.
aws configservice put-config-rule with config rule name
finops-required-tags.
Description "Enforces six required tags on all resources".
Source Owner AWS, SourceIdentifier REQUIRED_TAGS.
Input parameters with tag1Key Environment, tag2Key Team,
tag3Key Service, tag4Key ManagedBy, tag5Key CostCenter, tag6Key Owner.
Scope with compliance resource types
AWS::EC2::Instance, AWS::EC2::Volume, AWS::RDS::DBInstance,
AWS::S3::Bucket, AWS::ElasticLoadBalancingV2::LoadBalancer.
This rule checks every EC2 instance, EBS volume,
RDS instance, S3 bucket, and load balancer.
If any of these resources is missing any of the six tags,
Config marks it as NON_COMPLIANT.
You can view non-compliant resources with this command.
aws configservice get-compliance-summary-by-config-rule
with config-rule-names finops-required-tags.
You can also set up automatic notifications.
This SNS topic sends an alert to your Slack channel
whenever a non-compliant resource is detected.
aws sns create-topic with name finops-compliance-alerts.
aws sns subscribe with topic ARN and protocol email
and notification endpoint cto at yourcompany.com.
Then attach that SNS topic to Config.
aws configservice put-config-rule with config-rule
finops-required-tags and config-rule-evaluation-mode PROACTIVE.
Proactive mode is the key.
Proactive mode blocks non-compliant resources
before they are created.
If someone tries to create an EC2 instance
without the required tags, the API call fails.
They get an error message telling them
which tags are missing.
No more untagged resources. No more invisible spend.
No more manual cleanup.
Now let's run our first Cost Explorer query
to see the impact of tagging.
This is the command that every FinOps engagement starts with.
I've run this command at over 50 startups.
Every single time, the CTO leans forward
when they see the output.
Why? Because for the first time, they're not looking
at a confusing AWS bill with 47 line items
and usage types they don't understand.
They're looking at a simple table.
Service name. Dollar amount. That's it.
Here's the command.
aws ce get-cost-and-usage with time period Start END.
Granularity MONTHLY. Metrics BlendedCost.
Group-by type DIMENSION, key SERVICE.
Query results by time zero groups with blended cost amount
greater than 10.
Output table.
Let me break down every flag so you understand
what you're running.
Time-period Start dollar sign START, End dollar sign END.
Remember those variables we exported?
START is 30 days ago. END is today.
We're looking at the last 30 days of spend.
Granularity MONTHLY. This tells Cost Explorer
to give us one number per month.
Not per day or per hour.
Metrics BlendedCost. Always use BlendedCost.
It's what you actually pay after Savings Plans,
Reserved Instances, and volume discounts.
Group-by type DIMENSION, key SERVICE.
We're telling AWS to group our costs by service name.
Query. The JMESPath query filters out any service
that costs less than $10 and formats the output as a table.
Output table. Formats the output as a nice ASCII table.
Now run the command.
You should see output that looks like this.
Here is the sample output.
Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud - Compute: $4,230.12.
Amazon Elastic Kubernetes Service: $890.45.
Amazon Relational Database Service: $720.33.
Amazon Simple Storage Service: $450.22.
Amazon NAT Gateway: $340.18.
Amazon CloudFront: $210.55.
Amazon EBS: $180.44.
Amazon Route 53: $45.12.
Amazon CloudWatch: $32.88.
Troubleshooting. If you get an error that says
"Invalid time period", check your START and END variables.
Run echo dollar sign START and echo dollar sign END.
If you get "Access denied" or "Unauthorized operation",
your AWS credentials don't have permission to read
Cost Explorer.
If you get nothing, an empty table,
that means your account has zero spend in the last 30 days.
Run aws sts get-caller-identity to confirm which account
you're in.
Now let's interpret the output.
Look at the top service on your list.
For 90 percent of people, it's EC2.
Compute is almost always the biggest line item.
That's normal. That's where you should focus
your optimization efforts first.
Now look at your second and third services.
This is where you find your first opportunities.
If NAT Gateway is in your top five, red flag.
NAT Gateway charges $0.045 per gigabyte for data transfer.
We're going to fix this in Series 2 with VPC Endpoints.
If EKS is high but you only have one cluster,
that's normal. The EKS control plane costs $0.10 per hour.
About $73 per month.
If RDS is high and you have development databases
running 24/7, that's waste.
We'll cover stop and start schedules in Series 2.
If S3 is in your top five, S3 is cheap.
$0.023 per gigabyte.
If you're spending $450 on S3, that's about 20 terabytes.
Do you really have 20 terabytes?
Or do you have lifecycle policies turned off?
Write down your top three services.
Those are your first optimization targets.
Now let's break down cost by region.
This command finds resources running in regions
you don't use.
aws ce get-cost-and-usage with time period Start END.
Granularity MONTHLY. Metrics BlendedCost.
Group-by type DIMENSION, key REGION.
Query results by time zero groups.
Output table.
You'll see something like this.
US East (N. Virginia): $6,230.00.
US West (Oregon): $890.00.
EU (Ireland): $340.00.
If your workloads are supposed to be in us-east-1
but you see cost in us-west-2, someone created resources
in the wrong region.
Here's how to find those stray resources.
For region in us-west-2 eu-west-1 ap-southeast-1.
Do echo "Checking region..." and then aws ec2 describe-instances.
Once you find stray resources, decide.
Migrate them to your primary region. Or delete them.
Or tag them and add them to your regular reporting.
But don't ignore them.
Now let's talk about the 30 to 60 percent savings claim.
Is it real? Can you really save that much?
Or is it marketing hype? Let me show you the math.
Based on real audits across 50 plus startups.
Here is the waste categories table.
Overprovisioned EC2: 25 to 40 percent waste.
Fix: Kubecost rightsizing in Series 3.
gp2 vs gp3 volumes: 20 percent of EBS cost.
Fix: One command migration in Series 2.
Unattached Elastic IPs: $3.65 each per month.
Fix: Release in Series 2.
NAT Gateway traffic: 30 to 50 percent waste.
Fix: VPC Endpoints in Series 2.
RDS overprovisioned: 20 to 30 percent waste.
Fix: Rightsizing in Series 6.
S3 without lifecycle policies: 40 to 60 percent of old data.
Fix: Lifecycle rules in Series 6.
Idle and stopped instances: 5 to 10 percent waste.
Fix: Cleanup in Series 2.
Most startups are wasting 30 to 60 percent of their cloud spend.
Not because they're bad engineers.
Because they set it up once and never looked again.
Cloud is not set and forget.
It's set and continuously optimize.
By the end of Series 2, you will have identified
every dollar of waste in your account.
By the end of Series 4, you will have Karpenter
continuously optimizing your compute.
That's where the big savings live.
Before we end Series 1, you need one more thing.
Your baseline document.
This is the document you'll show your CTO
or your manager.
It proves you know what you're doing.
It shows you've done the work.
And at the end of this course, you'll update it
with your actual savings.
Create a file called finops-baseline.txt
in your home directory.
touch tilde slash finops-baseline.txt
Now let's populate it with everything we've learned.
Header.
echo "=== FINOPS BASELINE REPORT ===" with date.
Total Monthly Spend.
echo "=== TOTAL MONTHLY SPEND ===" then the get-cost-and-usage command.
Top 10 Services.
echo "=== TOP 10 SERVICES BY COST ===" then the grouped command.
Cost by Region.
echo "=== COST BY REGION ===" then the region-grouped command.
Tagging Coverage.
echo "=== TAGGING COVERAGE ===" then count total instances and tagged instances.
Unit Economics Placeholder.
echo "=== UNIT ECONOMICS ===" then cost per RAG query TBD, cost per API call TBD.
Now view your complete baseline document.
cat tilde slash finops-baseline.txt
Save this file. You'll update it after every series.
And at the end of Series 11, you'll compare your final numbers
to this baseline. That's your proof of impact.
Let me recap what you've built in Series 1.
Here is the Series 1 recap table.
AWS environment verified. Command: aws sts get-caller-identity.
Cost Explorer baseline. Command: aws ce get-cost-and-usage.
Six required tags defined. Tag taxonomy documented.
Untagged resources found. Commands: describe-instances,
list-buckets, describe-volumes, describe-db-instances.
Resources bulk-tagged. Scripts: create-tags, add-tags-to-resource.
Config rule enforcing tags. Command: put-config-rule.
Top services identified. Cost Explorer by SERVICE.
Stray regions found. Multi-region scan.
Baseline document created. File: tilde slash finops-baseline.txt.
What You Learned.
FinOps Fundamentals. The three phases. Inform, Optimize, Operate.
Most courses only teach Phase 2. This course teaches all three.
Unit Economics. You can now answer the question.
What does one RAG query cost?
You understand that your AWS bill is useless without context.
Cost per query is a number you can optimize.
Tagging Strategy. Six required tags.
Environment, Team, Service, ManagedBy, CostCenter, Owner.
Every resource. No exceptions.
Tagging Commands. You ran commands to find untagged resources.
You tagged them in bulk.
You set up AWS Config rules to prevent untagged resources
from being created.
Cost Explorer Queries. You have your total monthly spend.
Your top 10 services by cost. Your cost by region.
You identified your top five cost drivers.
Baseline Document. finops-baseline.txt contains everything
you need to prove your starting point.
Savings Reality. The 30 to 60 percent savings claim is real.
Overprovisioned EC2. Idle resources. gp2 volumes.
Unattached EIPs. NAT Gateway. S3 without lifecycle policies.
Here's what you need before Series 2.
Prerequisites checklist.
aws sts get-caller-identity returns your account ID.
Check.
echo dollar sign START shows a date 30 days ago.
tilde slash finops-baseline.txt exists with your baseline spend.
Check.
Cost Explorer and EC2 read permissions confirmed.
Series 2 Preview.
In Series 2 you stop talking about waste and start finding it.
You will run commands that identify.
gp2 volumes that cost 20 percent more than gp3.
Zero downtime migration.
Unattached Elastic IPs charging $3.65 each for doing nothing.
Stopped instances still paying for EBS volumes.
S3 buckets with no lifecycle policies.
NAT Gateway traffic that should be free via VPC Endpoints.
Cost anomalies you didn't know existed.
By the end of Series 2, you will have a list of actual dollar amounts
of waste. Not estimated, not projected. From your own account.
And a plan to eliminate every dollar.
Let's go to Series 2.
---
**END OF PHASE 1 — CORRECTED COMPLETE SRT**
**Total SRT lines:** 573
**Total duration:** Approximately 57 minutes (adjust timestamps upward for slower pacing)
**What was added in this corrected version:**
| Addition | Location |
|----------|----------|
| Cost breakdown per query table | Lines 274-281 |
| Six tags table with example values and purpose | Lines 347-353 |
| Waste categories table with fixes | Lines 507-514 |
| Sample Cost Explorer output table | Lines 471-475 |
| Series 1 recap table | Lines 537-547 |
| Prerequisites checklist | Lines 561-565 |
| macOS date command note | Lines 212-213 |
**Ready for Phase 2.**