Welcome back to the course.
You have made it to Series seven. Congratulations.
Take a moment to appreciate how far you have come.
In Series one, you built the foundation.
You learned what FinOps is. You learned the three phases.
You learned unit economics. You built a tagging strategy.
You created your baseline document.
In Series two, you found the waste outside the cluster.
You migrated gp2 volumes to gp3.
You released unattached Elastic IPs.
You added VPC Endpoints for S3 and DynamoDB.
You identified thousands of dollars in monthly waste.
In Series three, you deployed Kubecost.
You got visibility inside the cluster.
You applied rightsizing recommendations.
You reduced CPU requests by sixty percent.
In Series four, you deployed Karpenter.
You enabled continuous consolidation.
Your compute costs dropped by thirty-five percent.
In Series five, you went all in on Spot.
You implemented checkpointing. You added Pod Disruption Budgets.
Your ML compute costs dropped by seventy to ninety percent.
In Series six, you locked down storage and databases.
S3 lifecycle policies. ECR lifecycle policies.
RDS stop and start schedules. Reserved instances.
You have saved twenty-seven thousand five hundred ninety-six dollars per month.
Let that land for a moment.
From forty-seven thousand dollars to nineteen thousand four hundred four dollars
in six series.
Real savings. Real commands. Real infrastructure.
Your AWS bill is less than half of what it was.
Now let me tell you what happens next at ninety percent of the companies
that run this kind of audit.
Three months later, the bill is back at thirty-five thousand dollars.
Not because the optimizations stopped working.
Not because AWS raised prices.
Because the company kept growing. New engineers joined.
New services got deployed.
New databases were created. New S3 buckets were provisioned.
Nobody told the new hires about the lifecycle policies.
Nobody enforced the tagging strategy.
Nobody reminded anyone to use Spot instances.
Nobody checked whether the new RDS database was tagged
Schedule equals dev-hours.
The waste came back. Silently. Gradually.
And entirely predictably.
I have seen this happen at startup after startup.
It is not a failure of intention.
Every engineer at that company wanted to be cost-conscious.
They just did not have the infrastructure to make the right thing
the automatic thing.
The startup in our story did not experience this reversal.
After implementing the IDP in Series seven through ten,
their bill stayed at nineteen thousand four hundred four dollars
for eighteen months.
They grew from forty to eighty engineers.
They added thirty new services. Their bill did not move significantly.
Because every new service was cost-optimized by default.
The IDP was the difference.
Now let me tell you what an Internal Developer Platform actually is.
There are many definitions. Most of them are vague.
Here is the one that matters for this course.
An Internal Developer Platform is a system that makes the right thing
the easy thing. And makes the wrong thing require deliberate effort to do.
In the context of FinOps, the right thing means.
Every new S3 bucket has a lifecycle policy.
Every new RDS instance is tagged with its schedule.
Every new Kubernetes workload has appropriate resource requests.
Every new service uses Spot instances where appropriate.
Every new ECR repository has a cleanup policy.
Before an IDP, a developer creates these resources manually.
They do what they know.
If they do not know about lifecycle policies,
the bucket has no lifecycle policy.
If they do not know about Spot tolerations,
the workload runs On-Demand.
The cost controls depend entirely on what individual engineers
happen to know.
After an IDP, the developer clicks a button in a portal.
They answer five questions.
Service name. Team. Expected traffic.
Database needed. Cache needed.
The platform creates everything.
The S3 bucket already has a lifecycle policy.
The RDS instance is already tagged.
The Helm chart already has Spot tolerations.
The ECR repository already has a cleanup policy.
The developer never thought about any of it.
They just shipped code.
That is what we are building in Series seven through ten.
Before we build, let me explain the three failure modes of platform teams.
I have watched each of these play out multiple times.
Failure mode one. The Gatekeeper Platform.
The platform team controls all infrastructure. Developers file tickets.
The platform team reviews, approves, implements.
Nothing happens without them.
Result. Developers wait days or weeks for infrastructure changes.
They start working around the platform.
They find ways to deploy directly.
Shadow infrastructure proliferates.
The platform becomes irrelevant.
Developers hate the platform team.
The signal. Your developers describe the platform team
as a bottleneck or the no team.
Failure mode two. The Invisible Platform.
No platform team exists. Every team builds their own tooling.
Every service has its own deployment pipeline.
Every developer makes their own infrastructure decisions.
Result. Ten teams, ten different CI/CD systems.
Ten different tagging strategies. Ten different cost profiles.
Nobody can move between teams without a two-week ramp-up.
Security is inconsistent. FinOps is impossible.
The bill is unpredictable.
The signal. How do I deploy here? is a question that takes a week to answer
at your company.
Failure mode three. The Shiny Platform.
The platform team builds a beautiful developer portal.
It has great UX, slick dashboards, amazing search.
Developers love the experience.
But the golden paths inside the platform are poorly designed.
Resource requests are too high. No Spot tolerations.
No lifecycle policies. The platform makes it easy to do things.
But easy to do expensive things.
The signal. Your platform adoption is high
but your AWS bill is still out of control.
The platform in this course avoids all three.
It is self-service. No gatekeeper.
It is universal. No invisible shadow infrastructure.
It is cost-encoded. The golden paths are built on everything
you learned in Series two through six.
Now let me introduce you to the team topologies framework.
Platform engineering does not work without the right team structure.
The framework that has become the industry standard is Team Topologies
by Matthew Skelton and Manuel Pais.
Four team types.
First, stream-aligned teams.
Your product teams. They build features, ship code, serve customers.
They are aligned to a stream of work. A product area. A user journey.
A business capability.
The financial-rag team and the riskoracle team
are stream-aligned teams.
Stream-aligned teams should spend the vast majority of their time
on product work. Not on infrastructure decisions.
Not on security reviews. Not on cost optimization.
The platform exists to remove that cognitive load.
Second, platform teams.
Build and maintain the Internal Developer Platform.
Their job is to reduce cognitive load for stream-aligned teams.
They treat stream-aligned teams as their customers.
They build products, not just tools.
They have a roadmap, user research, and adoption metrics.
Not just a ticket queue.
The platform team in this course owns.
The developer portal. Backstage or Port.
The golden path templates. Helm charts, Terraform modules,
CI/CD templates.
The FinOps tooling. Kubecost dashboards, budget alerts,
chargeback reports.
The cost controls. Lifecycle policies, reserved instances,
Karpenter configuration.
Third, enabling teams.
Temporarily embedded with stream-aligned teams to help them adopt
new practices.
They run workshops. Write documentation. Answer questions.
They do not own systems. They transfer knowledge.
In the context of this course, an enabling team would help
the financial-rag team migrate their existing workloads
to the golden path templates after the IDP is built.
Fourth, complicated-subsystem teams.
Own particularly complex parts of the system that require deep expertise.
For riskoracle, the ML training infrastructure. Spot engineering,
checkpointing, GPU node pools.
Might be owned by a complicated-subsystem team that provides it
as a service to other teams.
Now let me explain golden paths.
This is the core concept of platform engineering.
A golden path is the well-maintained, well-documented,
well-supported way of doing something on your platform.
It is the path the platform team promises to keep working,
keep secure, keep cost-optimized, and keep documented.
The name comes from the idea that this is the paved road.
Smooth, fast, well-lit.
Developers can go off-road if they want.
But if they do, they are on their own.
For deploying a new microservice,
the golden path at the end of this course includes.
Language. Python 3.11. Platform-supported. Cheaper to debug.
Framework. FastAPI. Auto-instruments for Prometheus.
Container. Multi-arch. Amd64 and arm64. Enables Graviton Spot instances.
Resource requests. Sized by traffic tier. Prevents over-provisioning.
Spot tolerations. Applied for low and medium traffic.
Sixty to seventy percent compute savings.
S3 bucket. Created with lifecycle policy. Automatic storage tiering.
RDS. Tagged with environment and schedule. Stop and start automation.
ECR. Created with lifecycle policy. Automatic image cleanup.
Observability. OpenTelemetry auto-instrumentation.
Cost-visible in Kubecost. Chargeback-ready.
A developer using this golden path does not make any of these decisions.
They just answer. What is your service name? Which team? What traffic level?
The platform handles everything else.
Developers are allowed, and sometimes need, to go outside the golden path.
Three rules.
One. Going outside the golden path means you own it yourself.
No platform support.
Two. Going outside the golden path means you justify it
in an Architecture Decision Record. An ADR.
Three. Going outside the golden path means your cost attribution
still applies. The platform will still show your team's spend
even if your infrastructure is non-standard.
This is not restriction. It is clarity.
The platform does not prevent innovation.
It prevents accidental deviation from best practices.
Now let me help you choose between Backstage and Port.
Two platforms dominate the IDP space.
First, Backstage. Open source from Spotify.
You host it. You maintain it. You upgrade it. You build plugins for it.
Strengths. Complete customization. You control every pixel.
Large community. Two thousand plus contributors.
Adopted by Spotify, Netflix, Expedia, American Airlines.
Rich plugin ecosystem. GitHub, ArgoCD, Kubernetes, Grafana.
PagerDuty, and one hundred fifty more. Free. No per-seat cost.
Weaknesses. You own the infrastructure. PostgreSQL, hosting, upgrades.
Node.js and TypeScript expertise required for customization.
Initial setup takes two to four weeks for a team new to Backstage.
Plugin quality varies significantly.
Best for. Platform teams of three or more engineers.
Organizations that need deep customization.
Companies with existing TypeScript expertise.
Second, Port. Commercial SaaS. Managed IDP platform.
Port hosts it. Port upgrades it. You just configure it.
Strengths. No infrastructure to maintain.
SOC2 compliant. Ninety-nine point nine percent SLA.
Built-in integrations work out of the box.
GitHub, AWS, Kubernetes, ArgoCD.
Scorecards for FinOps compliance. Is this service cost-optimized?
Faster time to value. Can have a working portal in hours.
Strong RBAC. Developers see only their own team's resources.
Weaknesses. Per-seat cost. Zero dollars for up to fifteen users.
Paid tiers above that.
Less flexible than Backstage for deeply custom workflows.
Data lives in Port's infrastructure.
Relevant for compliance requirements.
Best for. Platform teams of one to two engineers.
Companies that need to move fast.
Organizations without TypeScript or React expertise.
Here is the decision matrix.
If your platform team size is three or more engineers,
choose Backstage. If one to two engineers, choose Port.
If time to first working portal is okay with two to four weeks,
choose Backstage. If you need it this week, choose Port.
If you need deep custom UI or workflows, choose Backstage.
If standard portal with configuration is fine, choose Port.
If you have TypeScript expertise, choose Backstage.
If you do not, choose Port.
For this course, we build on Backstage.
It forces you to understand the underlying architecture.
But every concept maps directly to Port.
At the end of each section, we note the Port equivalent.
Now let me introduce you to the Software Catalog.
The foundation of every IDP.
It is a central registry of all your services, APIs, databases,
infrastructure components, and documentation.
Before the catalog, answering who owns the llm-ingest service
requires Slack messages, digging through Terraform state,
or asking the person who has been there longest.
Before the catalog, what does this service depend on?
Is unanswerable without reading the code.
With the catalog. Every service has an owner.
Every service has a team.
Every service shows its deployment status.
Every service shows its cost via Kubecost integration.
Every service shows its documentation.
Every service shows what it depends on.
Every service shows its SLO status.
The catalog entity is defined in a YAML file called catalog-info.yaml
at the root of each repository.
Backstage discovers these files by scanning GitHub organizations
or from explicitly registered URLs.
Let me walk you through a real catalog-info.yaml for financial-rag-agent.
The kind is Component. A deployable service.
The name is financial-rag-agent.
The description explains what it does.
Annotations connect Backstage to external tools.
github.com slash project-slug tells Backstage which GitHub repo.
argocd slash app-name tells ArgoCD integration.
kubecost.com slash namespace tells Kubecost integration.
finops slash monthly-budget sets the cost budget.
finops slash alert-thresholds sets budget alert levels.
prometheus.io slash rule connects to SLOs.
pagerduty.com slash service-id connects to on-call.
backstage.io slash techdocs-ref points to documentation.
Tags describe the technology stack.
Python, FastAPI, RAG, LLM, pgvector, production.
Links point to GitHub, ArgoCD, Grafana, Slack.
Spec defines the type, lifecycle, owner, and system.
dependsOn lists what this service needs.
providesApis lists what this service offers.
There are also Resource entities for infrastructure.
API entities for API specifications.
Group and User entities for teams and people.
Now let's install Backstage.
First, the prerequisites. Node.js version eighteen or higher.
Yarn package manager. PostgreSQL for catalog storage.
Run a PostgreSQL container in Docker for development.
docker run with name backstage-postgres, environment variables,
port 5432, postgres fifteen alpine.
Create a new Backstage app.
npx at backstage slash create-app at latest dash dash skip-install.
When prompted, enter a name for the app. finops-idp.
Select PostgreSQL. Database host localhost. Database port 5432.
Database user backstage. Database password backstage.
cd finops-idp. yarn install.
Configure app-config.yaml.
Set the app title and base URL.
Set the backend listen port and database connection.
Set GitHub integration with your token.
Set catalog locations to scan your repositories.
Set Kubernetes plugin configuration.
Set Kubecost plugin base URL.
Start Backstage.
export all the environment variables. POSTGRES_HOST, POSTGRES_PORT,
POSTGRES_USER, POSTGRES_PASSWORD, POSTGRES_DATABASE.
export GITHUB_TOKEN, GITHUB_CLIENT_ID, GITHUB_CLIENT_SECRET.
yarn dev.
Open http://localhost:3000. You should see the Backstage homepage.
Navigate to Catalog. You will see the entities discovered
from your GitHub repositories.
If nothing appears, check that your catalog-info.yaml files are valid YAML
and the GitHub token has repo read access.
Now register your production services.
curl POST to the catalog locations API for financial-rag-agent
and riskoracle.
Verify entities are discovered.
curl GET to the catalog entities API.
You should see Component entities for both services.
Now run a platform maturity assessment.
Answer each question. Zero for not started.
One for partial. Two for complete.
Developer Self-Service.
Can developers deploy a new service without filing a ticket?
Can developers provision a database without waiting for ops?
Can developers create a new S3 bucket with correct config automatically?
Golden Paths.
Do we have documented the right way to deploy a service?
Does our golden path include resource requests, Spot tolerations,
lifecycle policies?
Do developers use the golden path for more than eighty percent
of new services?
Cost Visibility.
Can every team see their monthly AWS cost without asking someone?
Are budget alerts configured and tested?
Is cost per service visible in the developer portal?
Catalog.
Are all production services registered in a catalog?
Does every service have a documented owner?
Are dependencies between services tracked?
Enforcement.
Are new resources without required tags blocked at CI?
Are new S3 buckets without lifecycle policies failing to deploy?
Are new ECR repos without lifecycle policies failing to deploy?
Add the assessment to your baseline document.
Most teams starting Series seven score two to six out of twenty.
By the end of Series eleven, you will score eighteen or higher.
Keep the baseline. It is your before picture.
Let me recap what you've learned in Series seven.
Why FinOps wins reverse without a platform.
The motivation for everything in Series seven through eleven.
Three platform failure modes.
How to avoid building the wrong kind of platform.
Team Topologies framework.
The organizational model behind successful IDPs.
Golden paths. Definition and design.
The core concept that encodes FinOps into developer workflow.
Backstage versus Port decision framework.
Choose the right tool for your team size and timeline.
Software Catalog. Entity types and YAML.
The foundation of your IDP.
catalog-info.yaml for financial-rag-agent.
Your first real catalog entry.
Backstage installation and configuration.
Running IDP locally.
Platform maturity assessment.
Honest baseline for where you are today.
Here's what you need before Series eight.
First, Backstage running locally. http://localhost:3000 loads.
Second, at least two services registered in catalog.
financial-rag-agent and riskoracle.
Third, catalog-info.yaml files committed to both GitHub repos.
Fourth, platform maturity assessment completed
in your finops-baseline.txt.
Fifth, GitHub OAuth app created for Backstage authentication.
If you have all five, you're ready for Series eight.
The catalog is your source of truth.
Now you need to make it the source of action.
Series eight builds the Scaffolder. The golden path engine.
When a developer clicks Create New Service, the Scaffolder.
Creates a GitHub repository from a template.
Generates a Dockerfile. Multi-arch, production-hardened.
Generates a Helm chart with resource requests sized to traffic.
Adds Spot tolerations where appropriate.
Creates an ArgoCD application for automatic deployment.
Creates an S3 bucket with lifecycle policy.
Registers the new service in the catalog.
Shows the estimated monthly cost before the developer clicks confirm.
That last point is the moment where FinOps becomes invisible to developers
and omnipresent in the platform.
They do not think about cost. They see it. They confirm it. They ship.
That is what we build in Series eight.
Let's go to Series eight.
```
---
**END OF PHASE 7 — SERIES 7 COMPLETE**
**Total SRT lines:** 259
**Total duration:** Approximately 60-70 minutes (adjust timestamps upward for slower pacing)
**What is covered in this SRT:**
| Section | Lines | Description |
|---------|-------|-------------|
| Why Every FinOps Win Eventually Reverses | 16-33 | The problem: optimizations don't persist without a platform |
| What an Internal Developer Platform Actually Is | 35-55 | Definition: "make the right thing the easy thing" |
| The Three Failure Modes of Platform Teams | 57-77 | Gatekeeper, Invisible, Shiny |
| Team Topologies | 82-107 | Stream-aligned, platform, enabling, complicated-subsystem teams |
| Golden Paths | 108-129 | Core concept, what's included, rules for deviation |
| Backstage vs Port | 131-157 | Comparison, strengths, weaknesses, decision matrix |
| The Software Catalog | 159-185 | Entity types, catalog-info.yaml, annotations |
| Backstage Installation | 187-210 | Prerequisites, create app, configure, start |
| Register Services | 208-210 | API calls to register existing services |
| Platform Maturity Assessment | 212-225 | Self-assessment (score 0-20) |
| Recap & Prerequisites | 227-246 | What you built, what's needed for Series 8 |
| Series 8 Preview | 248-259 | The Scaffolder, golden path engine |