Welcome back to the course.
In Series seven, you installed Backstage and registered your existing services
in the catalog.
You have a source of truth. But a catalog without action is just documentation.
Marginally better than a Confluence page that nobody reads.
Series eight turns the catalog into a deployment machine.
By the end of this series, a developer on your team can open the IDP portal,
click Create New Service, fill in five fields, and get back.
A GitHub repository with production-ready code structure.
A multi-arch Dockerfile that supports both amd64 and arm64 for Graviton Spot.
A Helm chart with resource requests sized to their traffic tier.
Spot tolerations applied automatically for low and medium traffic.
An S3 bucket with lifecycle policy already configured.
An ArgoCD application wired to their cluster.
The service registered in the catalog.
And an estimated monthly cost displayed before they click confirm.
Total time. Under ninety seconds.
Zero tickets. Zero platform team involvement.
Zero cost policy violations, because the right policies are baked into
the template.
This is the golden path made real.
Let me explain the Scaffolder architecture.
Backstage's Scaffolder has three layers.
Layer one is the Developer Portal UI.
A form with fields like service name, team, traffic tier, database needed,
cache needed.
Layer two is the Scaffolder Engine.
It executes steps defined in a template.yaml file.
Each step calls a built-in or custom action.
Layer three is the external APIs.
GitHub API to create repositories and push files.
Kubernetes API to create ArgoCD applications.
Catalog API to register the new entity.
The template YAML defines what steps run, in what order, with what inputs.
The developer fills in the form. The engine executes.
The developer gets links to everything that was created.
First, let's install the required Scaffolder plugins.
cd finops-idp.
Add the GitHub scaffolder actions module.
yarn add at backstage slash plugin-scaffolder-backend-module-github.
Add the Kubernetes actions module for creating ArgoCD apps.
yarn add at backstage slash plugin-scaffolder-backend-module-kubernetes.
Add the AWS actions module for creating S3 buckets and tagging resources.
yarn add at backstage slash plugin-scaffolder-backend-module-aws.
Add the ArgoCD plugin for the frontend and backend.
yarn add at roadiehq slash backstage-plugin-argo-cd.
yarn add at roadiehq slash backstage-plugin-argo-cd-backend.
Now register the modules in your backend.
Open packages slash backend slash src slash index.ts.
Add imports for each plugin.
backend.add for scaffolder-backend.
backend.add for scaffolder-backend-module-github.
backend.add for scaffolder-backend-module-kubernetes.
backend.add for scaffolder-backend-module-aws.
backend.add for catalog-backend.
backend.add for catalog-backend-module-github.
Now let's create the golden path template.
Create a templates directory in your infrastructure repo.
mkdir dash p infrastructure/backstage/templates/microservice.
cd infrastructure/backstage/templates/microservice.
The main template file is called template.yaml.
Let me walk you through it section by section.
First, the metadata.
apiVersion is scaffolder.backstage.io/v1beta3.
kind is Template.
name is microservice-finops.
title is Microservice with FinOps Optimized.
description explains what this template does.
Creates a production-ready microservice with FinOps best practices built in.
Spot tolerations, resource requests by traffic tier, S3 lifecycle policy,
ArgoCD deployment, Kubecost cost attribution, and pre-deploy cost estimate.
tags include Python, FastAPI, production, finops, and recommended.
Next, the parameters section.
This defines the form the developer sees.
Parameter one. Service Information.
Required fields. Name, team, description.
Service name must be lowercase, hyphens only.
Example. fraud-detection, payment-processor, risk-api.
Team is an OwnerPicker field. It pulls from the catalog.
The developer selects their team.
Description is a text area for one sentence.
Language defaults to Python. Options are Python, Go, and Node.js.
Parameter two. Infrastructure Configuration.
Traffic tier. Low, medium, or high.
Low means less than one thousand requests per day.
Medium means one thousand to one hundred thousand requests per day.
High means more than one hundred thousand requests per day.
Needs database. Boolean. Creates an RDS t4g.micro with stop and start schedule.
Needs cache. Boolean. Creates an ElastiCache t4g.micro node.
Needs S3. Boolean. Creates an S3 bucket with lifecycle policy.
Defaults to true.
Environment. Dev, staging, or production. Defaults to dev.
Parameter three. Cost Estimate and Confirmation.
A description explains that the estimate is based on selections
and assumes standard FinOps optimization profile.
A checkbox confirms the developer has reviewed the cost estimate.
They must check it to proceed.
Now the steps section.
This is where the actions happen.
Step one. Calculate and display cost estimate.
This is a debug log action that prints an ASCII table to the console.
The table shows compute cost based on traffic tier.
Low traffic. CPU twelve dollars. Memory eight dollars. Spot capacity type.
Seventy percent discount.
Medium traffic. CPU twenty-eight dollars. Memory eighteen dollars.
On-Demand capacity type.
High traffic. CPU ninety-five dollars. Memory fifty-two dollars.
HPA with one to ten replicas.
If database is needed, RDS t4g.micro PostgreSQL costs sixteen dollars per month.
Stop and start schedule reduces effective cost to about six dollars per month.
If cache is needed, ElastiCache t4g.micro Redis costs twelve dollars per month.
If S3 is needed, storage with lifecycle policy costs about five dollars per month.
Platform costs for ECR, CloudWatch, and NAT total about eight dollars per month.
Total estimate for low traffic is thirty-three to forty-five dollars per month.
Medium traffic is sixty to eighty dollars per month.
High traffic is one hundred sixty to two hundred twenty dollars per month.
The table also lists optimizations applied automatically.
Spot instances for low-traffic workloads.
Graviton ARM64 instances where available.
Gp3 storage on all EBS volumes.
S3 lifecycle policy if S3 selected.
RDS stop and start schedule if database selected.
ECR lifecycle policy on container repository.
Step two. Validate cost acknowledgement.
If the checkbox is not checked, the template fails with an error.
Step three. Fetch the skeleton.
This is a fetch template action.
It takes the skeleton directory and substitutes variables.
The skeleton contains the template files.
Dockerfile, Helm chart, catalog-info.yaml, GitHub Actions workflow.
Step four. Create GitHub repository.
This is a GitHub repo create action.
It creates a new repository under your GitHub organization.
Step five. Push generated files to GitHub.
This pushes the skeleton files to the new repository.
Step six. Create S3 bucket if needed.
This is an AWS S3 create action.
It creates a bucket with the name service name dash environment dash data.
It adds tags for Name, Team, Service, Environment, and ManagedBy.
It adds lifecycle rules for FinOps tiering.
Transition to Standard-IA at thirty days.
Transition to Glacier Instant Retrieval at ninety days.
Transition to Deep Archive at three hundred sixty-five days.
Expire at seven hundred thirty days.
Step seven. Create ArgoCD application.
This is a Kubernetes apply action.
It creates an Application resource in the argocd namespace.
The application points to the Helm chart in the new repository.
Sync policy includes prune, self-heal, and automatic creation of the namespace.
Step eight. Register in Backstage catalog.
This is a catalog register action.
It adds the new service to the Software Catalog.
Finally, the output section.
Links to GitHub repository, service in catalog, ArgoCD application,
and cost dashboard.
Text output with next steps for the developer.
Now let's create the skeleton files.
Create the skeleton directory.
mkdir dash p infrastructure/backstage/templates/microservice/skeleton.
First, the Dockerfile skeleton.
For Python, use python three point eleven slim bookworm.
Multi-stage build. Builder stage installs dependencies.
Runtime stage copies the installed packages and runs as non-root user.
The runtime stage creates an appuser with user ID one thousand.
It sets environment variables to disable bytecode compilation and enable unbuffered output.
It exposes port eight thousand.
It adds a healthcheck that curls the health endpoint.
It runs uvicorn with two workers.
For Go, use golang one point twenty-two alpine.
Builder stage downloads modules and compiles a static binary.
Runtime stage uses gcr.io/distroless static for the smallest possible image.
For Node.js, use node twenty alpine.
Production stage uses npm ci dash dash only production.
Runs as non-root user.
Second, the Helm values.yaml skeleton.
Replica count is set by traffic tier.
Image repository is a placeholder. GitHub Actions will set it.
Resource requests and limits are set by traffic tier.
Low traffic. One hundred millicpu. Two hundred fifty-six megabytes.
Two hundred millicpu limit. Five hundred twelve megabytes limit.
Medium traffic. Five hundred millicpu. One gigabyte.
One thousand millicpu limit. Two gigabyte limit.
High traffic. Two thousand millicpu. Four gigabytes.
Four thousand millicpu limit. Eight gigabyte limit.
If use_spot is true, add Spot tolerations.
Tolerations for capacity-type spot and dedicated application.
Node selector prefers ARM64 architecture for twenty percent additional savings.
Affinity prefers Spot instances with weight eighty.
On-Demand fallback with weight twenty.
If use_spot is false, use On-Demand only.
Pod anti-affinity spreads replicas across availability zones.
If HPA is enabled for high traffic services, configure autoscaling.
Min replicas equals replica count. Max replicas equals ten.
Target CPU utilization seventy percent.
Target memory utilization eighty percent.
Scale down behavior. Stabilization window five minutes.
Remove one pod per minute.
Scale up behavior. Stabilization window thirty seconds.
Add two pods per thirty seconds.
Third, the catalog-info.yaml skeleton.
Annotations include GitHub project slug, ArgoCD app name,
Kubecost namespace, and Kubernetes ID.
FinOps annotations include traffic tier, spot-enabled, monthly budget,
alert thresholds, and cost tier set by field.
Tags include language, traffic tier, finops-optimized,
spot-enabled if applicable, PostgreSQL if needed, Redis if needed.
Fourth, the GitHub Actions CI skeleton.
The workflow has three jobs. Test, security, and build.
The test job installs dependencies and runs tests.
For Python, it runs ruff, mypy, and pytest with coverage.
For Go, it runs go vet and go test.
For Node.js, it runs npm test.
The security job runs gitleaks for secret scanning.
It runs Trivy for filesystem vulnerability scanning.
It uploads results to GitHub Security tab.
The build job runs only on pushes to main.
It configures AWS credentials using OIDC.
It logs into ECR.
It sets up QEMU for multi-arch builds.
It sets up Docker Buildx.
It builds and pushes a multi-arch image.
Platforms are linux/amd64 and linux/arm64.
This enables Graviton Spot instances.
It scans the container image with Trivy.
It updates the Helm values.yaml file with the new image tag.
It commits and pushes the change with skip ci in the commit message.
The skip ci flag prevents an infinite loop of CI runs.
Now register the template in Backstage.
Add the template location to app-config.yaml.
Type url with target pointing to the template.yaml file on GitHub.
Restart Backstage. Ctrl C then yarn dev.
Verify the template appears in the catalog.
curl to the catalog entities API with filter kind equals Template.
Now test the scaffolder end-to-end.
Create a test service.
In the Backstage UI, navigate to Create.
Select Microservice with FinOps Optimized.
Fill out the form.
Name test-finops-service.
Team team-platform.
Traffic low.
Database no.
Cache no.
S3 yes.
Environment dev.
Click Create.
After creation, verify the GitHub repo was created.
gh repo view aayostem/test-finops-service.
Verify files were generated correctly.
gh api to list repository contents.
Expected files include Dockerfile, helm directory, GitHub workflows directory,
catalog-info.yaml, requirements.txt, and main.py.
Verify Helm values have Spot tolerations for low traffic.
Get the values.yaml file, decode it from base64, and grep for tolerations.
Verify ArgoCD app was created.
kubectl get application test-finops-service-dev in the argocd namespace.
Verify S3 bucket was created with lifecycle policy.
aws s3api get-bucket-lifecycle-configuration for test-finops-service-dev-data.
Verify service appears in the catalog.
curl to the catalog entities API for the component.
Now let me show you the Port equivalent.
If you chose Port over Backstage, here is the configuration.
Create a self-service action.
Identifier create_microservice_finops.
Title Microservice with FinOps Optimized.
Trigger type self-service. Blueprint microservice.
User inputs include name, team, traffic tier, needs database, needs S3.
Action type workflow. Workflow name github-create-microservice.
Parameters include repo name, team, traffic tier, needs database, needs S3,
and estimated monthly cost.
Now update your baseline document.
Add the templates registered.
curl to the catalog entities API for Templates.
Add the golden path FinOps controls list.
Resource requests sized by traffic tier.
Spot tolerations applied automatically for low-traffic services.
Graviton ARM64 preferred in node selector for Spot.
HPA configured for high-traffic services.
S3 bucket with lifecycle policy.
RDS tagged schedule dev-hours for stop and start automation.
ECR lifecycle policy on generated repository.
finops slash monthly-budget annotation set in catalog-info.yaml.
Multi-arch Docker build enables ARM64 Spot instances.
Cost estimate displayed before service creation.
Add the catalog entities list.
curl to the catalog entities API for Components.
Let me recap what you've built in Series eight.
You created a complete golden path template.
Five parameters turn into a full service.
Any engineer can create cost-optimized services in ninety seconds.
You added a cost estimate to the scaffolder form.
FinOps visibility at the moment of highest leverage.
The developer sees the cost before they click create.
You created a multi-arch Dockerfile skeleton.
ARM64 and Graviton Spot are available automatically.
Twenty percent savings on compute for zero effort.
You configured Helm values with Spot tolerations by traffic tier.
Correct compute type without developer knowledge.
Low traffic gets Spot automatically. High traffic gets On-Demand.
You added HPA configuration for high-traffic services.
Scaling is configured correctly from day one.
You created an S3 bucket with lifecycle policy.
Storage cost controls are applied at creation, not retroactively.
You added a GitHub Actions CI workflow with multi-arch build.
Container images work on Graviton Spot.
The workflow includes test, security scan, build, and push.
You configured ArgoCD application creation.
Deployment is wired up at service creation time.
You added a finops slash monthly-budget annotation.
Budget accountability is encoded in code, not just in a dashboard.
You tested the scaffolder end-to-end.
A real service was created, deployed, and registered.
Here's what you need before Series nine.
First, the template registered in Backstage.
Navigate to Create and see the template.
Second, a test service created end-to-end.
GitHub repo, ArgoCD app, S3 bucket, and catalog entry all present.
Third, multi-arch CI pipeline verified.
Check ECR image has both amd64 and arm64 manifests.
Fourth, your baseline document updated with template controls list.
Fifth, at least three services in the catalog, including the test service.
If you have all five, you're ready for Series nine.
The golden path creates services.
Series nine completes the deployment loop and adds day-two operations.
The things developers need to do after a service is running.
You will wire up. Scale a service with real-time cost impact shown before applying.
Rollback to a previous image tag from the catalog, not kubectl.
Stream logs from running pods without kubectl access.
Restart a deployment from the catalog.
View real-time Kubernetes resource usage.
And you will trace a complete deployment from developer's first click
to running pod in EKS. Every step visible in the catalog.
In under five minutes.
This is the moment the platform becomes something developers actually want to use.
Not just a policy enforcement tool, but a genuine productivity accelerator.
Let's go to Series nine.
```
---
**END OF PHASE 8 — SERIES 8 COMPLETE**
**Total SRT lines:** 201
**Total duration:** Approximately 60-70 minutes (adjust timestamps upward for slower pacing)
**What is covered in this SRT:**
| Section | Lines | Description |
|---------|-------|-------------|
| What You Are Building | 5-12 | Golden path: 5 fields → complete service in 90 seconds |
| Scaffolder Architecture | 14-20 | Three layers: UI, Engine, APIs |
| Install Required Plugins | 22-32 | GitHub, Kubernetes, AWS, ArgoCD modules |
| Complete Golden Path Template | 37-89 | Template.yaml with parameters, steps, output |
| Skeleton Files | 90-129 | Dockerfile, Helm values, catalog-info, GitHub Actions |
| Register Template | 130-135 | Add location to app-config, restart Backstage |
| Test End-to-End | 136-152 | Create test service, verify all components |
| Port Equivalent | 153-157 | Self-service action for Port users |
| Update Baseline | 158-165 | Add template controls, catalog entities |
| Recap & Prerequisites | 166-189 | What you built, what's needed for Series 9 |
| Series 9 Preview | 191-201 | Day-two operations, complete deployment trace |