Welcome back to the course.
In Series eight, you built the scaffolder.
A developer clicks Create, answers five questions.
They get a GitHub repo, a Helm chart, an ArgoCD app,
an S3 bucket, and a catalog entry. All cost-optimized by default.
But that is day one. What about day two?
On day two, the developer needs to.
Scale their service from two replicas to five during a traffic spike.
Roll back to the previous image tag after a bad deploy.
Stream logs from a crashing pod without asking for kubectl access.
Restart a deployment that is stuck in a bad state.
Check whether their service is actually running on Spot instances.
Understand why their pod failed to schedule.
Right now, every one of those actions requires kubectl.
Which means either the developer has cluster access, which is a security risk.
Or they file a ticket with the platform team, which is a bottleneck.
Neither is acceptable.
Series nine closes that gap.
By the end, developers perform every day-two operation through the Backstage UI.
With cost impact shown for every action that changes resource consumption.
The platform team is not involved.
The cluster is not directly accessible.
Everything goes through the golden path.
First, let's install the Kubernetes plugin for Backstage.
This gives Backstage direct visibility into your cluster.
It shows pod status, resource usage, events, and rollout history.
All filtered to the service the developer is looking at.
cd finops-idp.
Add the frontend plugin.
yarn at cwd packages/app add at backstage slash plugin-kubernetes.
Add the backend plugin.
yarn at cwd packages/backend add at backstage slash plugin-kubernetes-backend.
Wire up the backend.
Open packages slash backend slash src slash index.ts.
Add backend.add for the kubernetes-backend plugin.
Configure cluster access in app-config.yaml.
Add the kubernetes section.
Service locator method is multiTenant.
Cluster locator methods use config.
Define the cluster name, URL, auth provider as AWS.
Skip TLS verify false.
Assume role is the IAM role for Backstage to read the cluster.
Map catalog entities to Kubernetes resources by label.
The scaffolder already adds the app.kubernetes.io/name label to all pods.
So the Kubernetes plugin knows which pods belong to which service.
Create an IAM role for Backstage cluster access.
First, get your OIDC ID.
OIDC_ID equals the cluster OIDC issuer from the describe-cluster command.
Create a trust policy that allows the Backstage service account
to assume the role.
Create the IAM role.
Attach the ReadOnlyAccess managed policy.
Now create Kubernetes RBAC for Backstage.
Create a service account in the backstage namespace.
Annotate it with the IAM role ARN.
Create a ClusterRole called backstage-kubernetes-reader.
It allows get, list, and watch on pods, services, events, deployments,
replicasets, ingresses, and horizontalpodautoscalers.
Create a ClusterRoleBinding that binds the service account to the role.
Now wire the Kubernetes tab into the catalog page.
Open packages slash app slash src slash components slash catalog slash EntityPage.tsx.
Import EntityKubernetesContent and isKubernetesAvailable from the kubernetes plugin.
Add a new route to the service entity page.
Path slash kubernetes, title Kubernetes, condition isKubernetesAvailable.
Content is EntityKubernetesContent with refresh interval thirty seconds.
Now let's build day-two operations via Scaffolder actions.
Day-two operations like scale, rollback, restart, and log stream.
They appear as buttons on the catalog entity page.
They trigger GitHub Actions workflows.
Keeping all cluster mutations auditable in Git.
First, create custom Backstage actions.
Create a file called kubernetes-actions.ts in packages slash backend slash src slash plugins slash scaffolder-actions.
First action. Scale a Kubernetes deployment.
Use createTemplateAction from the scaffolder-node package.
Define the input schema. Namespace, deployment, replicas, reason, and actor.
In the handler, load the kubeconfig from default.
Create an AppsV1Api client.
Get the current replica count from the deployment.
Log the scale event with actor and reason.
Patch the deployment with the new replica count.
Return the previous and new replicas as output.
Second action. Rollback a deployment to a specific image tag.
Input schema includes repo URL, image tag, namespace, deployment, and reason.
In the handler, use the Octokit GitHub API client.
Get the current helm values.yaml file from the repository.
Update the image tag in the file.
Commit and push the change with skip ci in the commit message.
This triggers ArgoCD to sync the new image.
Register the custom actions in your backend.
Open packages slash backend slash src slash index.ts.
Import scaleDeploymentAction and rollbackDeploymentAction.
Add a backend plugin that registers these actions.
Now create the scale service template.
A YAML file that defines a self-service action for developers.
The template parameters include service name, namespace, current replicas,
new replicas, and reason.
The cost impact review step shows the estimated cost per replica and the monthly cost change.
The scale step calls the kubernetes scale-deployment action.
Passing the namespace, deployment, new replicas, reason, and actor.
The output shows the scale complete message.
Previous replicas, new replicas, monthly cost change, reason, and actor.
Links to Kubernetes and cost dashboard.
Now create the rollback service template.
Parameters include service name, image tag, reason, and optionally create an incident.
The rollback step calls the kubernetes rollback-deployment action.
It updates the values.yaml file in GitHub.
If create incident is true, it creates a GitHub issue to track the rollback.
The issue includes the service name, rolled-back image tag, triggering user, time, and reason.
Now let's walk through a complete deployment trace.
From developer click to running pod.
This is the end-to-end validation of your golden path.
Scenario. A new developer joins the financial-rag team.
They need to create the filing-classifier service.
They have never used kubectl. They have never touched Terraform.
They open the Backstage portal.
Step one. Developer creates the service via Backstage UI.
Parameters chosen. Name filing-classifier, team team-financial-rag, traffic medium,
database false, cache false, S3 true, environment dev.
Step two. Scaffolder runs automatically.
Verify GitHub repo was created.
gh repo view aayostem slash filing-classifier.
Verify generated files.
gh api to list the git tree. Expect GitHub workflows, Dockerfile,
catalog-info.yaml, helm charts, main.py, requirements.txt, and tests.
Step three. Developer writes code and pushes.
Clone the repository. Make a trivial change, like updating the README.
Commit and push to main.
Step four. GitHub Actions runs automatically.
Watch the CI pipeline with gh run watch.
Verify multi-arch image was pushed to ECR.
Check that the image manifest has both amd64 and arm64 architectures.
The manifest type should be application slash vnd.docker.distribution.manifest.list.v2 plus json.
That is a multi-arch manifest list.
Step five. ArgoCD syncs automatically.
Watch the ArgoCD application with kubectl get application.
Verify pods are running on the correct node type.
For medium traffic, On-Demand nodes.
Check the node capacity type label.
It should say on-demand.
Step six. Developer checks the catalog via Backstage UI.
Verify catalog entry via API.
curl to the catalog entities endpoint for the component.
Check name, owner, budget annotation, traffic tier annotation,
spot enabled annotation, and lifecycle.
Step seven. Measure total time.
From click Create to running pod in EKS.
Scaffolder takes about thirty seconds.
GitHub Actions takes about three minutes for build, test, push, and update.
ArgoCD sync takes about forty-five seconds.
Total about four point five minutes.
Developer touched only Backstage UI.
Zero kubectl commands used. Zero platform team tickets.
Eight cost optimizations applied automatically.
Now let's build log streaming without kubectl.
Developers need logs. Giving them kubectl cluster access is a security risk.
Build a log streaming endpoint.
Create a file called log-stream.ts in packages slash backend slash src slash plugins.
Create a new Express router.
A GET endpoint at slash pod-logs.
Query parameters include namespace, pod, container, and lines.
Create a KubeConfig and load from default.
Create a Log client.
Use the Kubernetes log API to stream logs.
Set content type to text plain and transfer encoding to chunked.
Stream the logs to the response.
Create a log viewer component in the catalog.
The component fetches the list of pods in the namespace.
It lets the developer select a pod and click Load Logs.
It colorizes the output.
Red for errors, yellow for warnings, blue for info.
Now integrate ArgoCD into the catalog.
Install the ArgoCD plugin.
yarn add at roadiehq slash backstage-plugin-argo-cd for the frontend.
yarn add at roadiehq slash backstage-plugin-argo-cd-backend for the backend.
Add ArgoCD configuration to app-config.yaml.
Define an ArgoCD instance with name, URL, and token.
In the catalog entity page, add the EntityArgoCDOverviewCard.
It shows sync status, health, and last sync time.
Now let's track platform adoption metrics.
This is the ultimate measure of platform success.
Are developers using the platform?
That is the question your CTO will ask.
Create a metrics endpoint at slash platform-metrics slash adoption.
Fetch all component entities from the catalog.
Calculate how many were created via the scaffolder.
Look for the annotation finops slash cost-tier-set-by equals backstage-scaffolder.
Calculate how many have a monthly budget annotation.
How many have spot enabled.
How many are production services.
Group by traffic tier. Low, medium, high.
Return the metrics in JSON.
Total services, golden path coverage percentage, budget annotated percentage,
spot enabled percentage, production services count, and breakdown by traffic tier.
Check your adoption metrics.
curl to localhost 7007 slash api slash platform-metrics slash adoption.
Target metrics by the end of Series eleven.
Golden path coverage greater than eighty percent.
Budget annotated greater than ninety percent.
Spot enabled greater than fifty percent for all low-traffic services.
Now update your baseline document.
Add the operations templates.
List each template with its description.
Add platform adoption metrics.
Run the curl command and append the JSON output.
Add deployment performance metrics.
End-to-end time from click to running pod. About four point five minutes.
Kubectl commands required. Zero.
Platform team tickets required. Zero.
FinOps controls applied automatically. Eight.
Let me recap what you've built in Series nine.
You added the Kubernetes plugin with cluster RBAC.
Live pod status in catalog without kubectl.
You created custom scale and rollback scaffolder actions.
Day-two operations via IDP, fully auditable.
You added the scale template with cost impact display.
Engineers see the cost before they scale.
You added the rollback template with GitOps integration.
Incident rollback in the UI, Git-auditable.
You added automatic incident issue creation on rollback.
Incident tracking is automatic.
You built a log streaming endpoint and viewer component.
Logs in the catalog, no kubectl needed.
You added ArgoCD integration in the catalog.
Deployment status in one place.
You built a platform adoption metrics endpoint.
Data-driven platform investment decisions.
You traced an end-to-end deployment in four point five minutes.
Proof that the golden path works.
Here's what you need before Series ten.
First, the Kubernetes plugin showing pod status in the catalog.
Second, the scale template working.
Test by scaling a service from the UI, then verify in the cluster.
Third, the rollback template working.
Test by triggering a rollback, then verify the values.yaml file was updated in GitHub.
Fourth, the log viewer showing pod logs in the catalog.
Fifth, the adoption metrics endpoint returning data.
Sixth, your baseline document updated with deployment performance metrics.
If you have all six, you're ready for Series ten.
You have built the platform. You have built the golden paths.
You have built self-service operations.
Every service created goes through the FinOps-optimized pipeline automatically.
Series ten closes the loop.
It brings FinOps cost data directly into the developer's workflow inside the platform itself.
You will build.
Live cost dashboards per service in the catalog Cost tab.
Budget alerts that fire in Slack when a team hits eighty percent of their monthly budget.
Chargeback reports showing each team's spend for the monthly finance review.
An anomaly detection webhook that routes AWS cost anomalies to service owners.
A FinOps homepage dashboard showing total spend, team budgets, and top cost drivers.
After Series ten, a developer opening the Backstage catalog sees their service's monthly cost,
their team's budget usage, and any active cost anomalies.
Without opening a single AWS console page.
FinOps becomes invisible to them and omnipresent in their workflow.
That is the final piece of the FinOps platform puzzle.
Let's go to Series ten.
```
---
**END OF PHASE 9 — SERIES 9 COMPLETE**
**Total SRT lines:** 192
**Total duration:** Approximately 55-65 minutes
**What is covered in this SRT:**
| Section | Lines | Description |
|---------|-------|-------------|
| The Gap Between Creation and Operation | 4-13 | Day-two operations require kubectl today — security risk or bottleneck |
| Kubernetes Plugin for Backstage | 15-43 | Install, configure, IAM role, RBAC, catalog tab |
| Day-Two Operations via Scaffolder Actions | 45-75 | Custom scale and rollback actions, cost impact display |
| Complete Deployment Trace | 81-108 | End-to-end from click to running pod (4.5 minutes) |
| Log Streaming Without kubectl | 110-123 | Express endpoint, log viewer component, colorized output |
| ArgoCD Integration | 124-130 | Show sync status in catalog |
| Platform Adoption Metrics | 131-143 | Track golden path coverage, budget annotations, spot usage |
| Update Baseline | 145-151 | Add templates, adoption metrics, deployment performance |
| Recap & Prerequisites | 152-176 | What you built, what's needed for Series 10 |
| Series 10 Preview | 178-192 | FinOps integration, cost dashboards, budget alerts, chargeback |