Welcome back to the course.
In Series one, you built the foundation.
You learned what FinOps is. You learned the three phases.
You learned unit economics. You built a tagging strategy.
You created your baseline document.
In Series two, you found the waste outside the cluster.
You migrated gp2 volumes to gp3.
You released unattached Elastic IPs.
You added VPC Endpoints for S3 and DynamoDB.
In Series three, you deployed Kubecost.
You got visibility inside the cluster.
You applied rightsizing recommendations.
You reduced CPU requests by sixty percent.
In Series four, you deployed Karpenter.
You enabled continuous consolidation.
You added Spot versus On-Demand splits.
Your compute costs dropped by thirty-five percent.
Now it's time to go all in on Spot.
Series five is about Spot instance engineering for ML workloads.
This is where the real savings live.
This is where you go from saving thirty-five percent on compute
to saving seventy to ninety percent on ML workloads.
This is where you learn to handle the thing that scares
most engineers away from Spot. Interruptions.
Most engineering teams avoid Spot instances for ML workloads
because of one word. Interruption.
They picture a training job running for six hours,
getting interrupted at hour five, losing everything, and starting over.
They picture angry data scientists.
They picture missed deadlines.
They picture the chaos of a production incident
caused by AWS reclaiming an instance.
So they run everything On-Demand.
They pay full price. They feel safe.
What they are actually paying for is the illusion of safety.
Because On-Demand instances can also be terminated.
AWS reboots for maintenance.
And the cost is real.
For a startup running eight GPU training jobs per night
at one dollar twenty cents per hour for four hours each.
That is one thousand one hundred fifty-two dollars per month
on compute that runs while most of the company sleeps.
With Spot engineering done correctly,
that same workload costs two hundred eighty-eight to
three hundred forty-five dollars per month. Seventy to seventy-five percent cheaper.
Zero lost jobs. Zero failed training runs.
The difference is not luck. It is engineering.
Let me explain how Spot interruptions actually work.
Understanding the mechanism removes the fear.
When AWS needs capacity back, the sequence is.
Step one. AWS decides to reclaim your Spot instance.
Step two. AWS publishes an interruption notice to the
EC2 Instance Metadata Service. IMDS for short.
The endpoint is http://169.254.169.254/latest/meta-data/spot/termination-time.
Step three. The endpoint returns a UTC timestamp.
The exact time the instance will be terminated.
Step four. You have approximately two minutes between when the notice appears
and when the instance is killed.
Step five. AWS also publishes an EventBridge event
and an SQS message so Karpenter can act at the cluster level.
Two minutes is enough time to.
Save a model checkpoint to S3. Flush in-flight data to PostgreSQL.
Complete the current batch and mark it done.
Signal the orchestration layer to reschedule on a new instance.
Two minutes is not enough time to.
Train a new epoch. Run inference on a large batch.
Do anything you have not already designed for.
The engineering question is not how do I avoid interruptions.
It is how do I make interruptions cost me less than two minutes of work.
Before we write any code, let's set up our environment.
export ACCOUNT_ID equals aws sts get-caller-identity query Account output text.
export REGION equals us-east-1.
export CLUSTER_NAME equals finops-cluster.
export CHECKPOINT_BUCKET equals riskoracle-checkpoints dash your account ID.
Verify Karpenter is running from Series four.
kubectl get pods dash n karpenter.
kubectl get nodepool.
Now you're ready.
First, let's analyse Spot price stability.
Before picking instance types, understand their price stability.
A Spot instance family with volatile prices will interrupt you frequently.
One with stable prices might run for weeks uninterrupted.
Create a script called spot-stability-analysis.sh.
Define your candidate instance types.
g4dn.xlarge, g4dn.2xlarge, g5.xlarge, g5.2xlarge, p3.2xlarge.
Look back seven days.
For each instance type, get the Spot price history.
Use Python to calculate statistics.
Average price, minimum, maximum, current price.
Calculate the coefficient of variation.
Standard deviation divided by average, times one hundred.
The coefficient of variation tells you how stable the price is.
Lower is more stable.
If the coefficient of variation is less than five percent,
the interruption risk is low. Excellent Spot candidate. Use freely.
If it is between five and fifteen percent,
the interruption risk is medium. Good candidate. Checkpoint every five minutes.
If it is greater than fifteen percent,
the interruption risk is high. Use with On-Demand fallback only.
Run the script.
You will see the stability scores for each instance type.
A real finding from riskoracle.
g4dn.xlarge in us-east-1 runs at a coefficient of variation less than three percent.
It almost never gets interrupted.
p3.2xlarge runs at about eighteen percent. Much more volatile.
We run training jobs on g4dn with Spot.
We only fall back to p3 on-demand for the final evaluation run
that cannot be interrupted.
Now let's set up the S3 checkpoint bucket.
aws s3api create-bucket with bucket name and region.
Enable versioning on the bucket.
This lets you recover from a corrupted checkpoint.
Add a lifecycle policy.
Keep only the last three checkpoints per job.
Enable server-side encryption with AWS KMS.
Required for financial data.
Now you have a durable, encrypted checkpoint bucket.
Now let me show you the production checkpointing implementation.
This is the complete, production-grade checkpointing system used by riskoracle.
Not a toy example. The actual code pattern deployed in production.
Create a file called checkpoint_manager.py in src slash riskoracle slash training.
Let me explain the design decisions.
S3 as checkpoint store. Survives instance termination.
Atomic writes via multipart upload. No partial checkpoints.
SHA-256 verification. Detect corruption before loading.
Keep last three checkpoints. Rolling window. S3 cost controlled.
SIGTERM and SIGINT handlers. Karpenter sends SIGTERM on drain.
Separate metadata from weights. Fast status checks without downloading weights.
First, define the CheckpointMetadata dataclass.
It stores job ID, epoch, step, loss, metric, timestamp, instance ID,
capacity type, SHA-256 checksum, training seconds, and interruption count.
This metadata is stored separately from the weights.
You can read the metadata without downloading gigabytes of model weights.
Now the CheckpointManager class.
In the init method, store the job ID, bucket, model, and optimizer.
Create an S3 client.
Initialize the current epoch, step, loss, and metric.
Record the training start time.
Get the instance ID and capacity type from the EC2 metadata service.
Register signal handlers for SIGTERM and SIGINT.
These are critical for graceful shutdown.
Start a background thread for time-based checkpointing.
Save every ten minutes regardless of epoch.
The signal handler is the most important part of this class.
When SIGTERM is received, which Karpenter sends when draining a node,
save a final checkpoint immediately.
Set the interrupted flag to true.
Increment the interruption counter.
Save the checkpoint. Then exit cleanly.
Exit code zero allows Karpenter to proceed with termination.
The save method writes a checkpoint to S3 atomically.
First, create a temporary file.
Save the model state dict and optimizer state dict to that file.
Compute the SHA-256 hash of the file for integrity verification.
Upload the file to S3 with server-side encryption.
Add metadata including the job ID, epoch, and SHA-256 hash.
Save the metadata separately as a JSON file.
This allows fast status checks without downloading weights.
Clean up old checkpoints. Keep only the last three.
The load latest method loads the most recent checkpoint from S3.
First, read the metadata JSON file.
This is fast because it is small.
Then download the weights file.
Verify the SHA-256 checksum before loading.
If the checksum does not match, the checkpoint is corrupted.
Raise an error. Do not load corrupted weights.
Load the checkpoint into the model and optimizer.
Return the next epoch to start from.
Now let's add an IMDS-based Spot termination watcher.
This is your second line of defence.
The checkpoint manager handles SIGTERM from Karpenter.
But what if Karpenter's SQS queue has a delay?
The IMDS watcher polls the metadata service directly.
It runs as a sidecar thread alongside your training loop.
Create a file called spot_watcher.py in src slash riskoracle slash training.
The SpotTerminationWatcher class polls IMDS every five seconds.
First, get an IMDSv2 token.
IMDSv2 requires a session token for security.
Then check the termination-time endpoint.
If it returns a timestamp, an interruption is imminent.
When an interruption is detected, call the registered callback.
The callback should save a checkpoint and exit.
Now let's put it all together in a complete training script.
Create a file called train.py in src slash riskoracle slash training.
First, parse environment variables.
JOB ID, CHECKPOINT BUCKET, MAX EPOCHS.
Build the model and optimizer.
Move to GPU if available.
Initialise the CheckpointManager.
This loads the latest checkpoint automatically.
Start the SpotTerminationWatcher.
Pass a callback that marks the checkpoint manager as interrupted and saves.
In the training loop, check the interrupted flag at every epoch start.
If interrupted, break the loop and exit.
After each epoch, update the checkpoint manager with the current loss.
Save a checkpoint every five epochs.
At the end of training, save a final checkpoint.
Stop the spot watcher.
Now let's create a Kubernetes Job to run this training script with Spot configuration.
Create a YAML file for the Job.
Set backoffLimit to ten.
Each interruption consumes one retry.
The job will automatically resume from the last checkpoint.
Set ttlSecondsAfterFinished to eighty-six thousand four hundred.
Keep logs for debugging for one day.
Add nodeSelector for the GPU NodePool.
Add tolerations for nvidia.com/gpu and Spot instances.
Set terminationGracePeriodSeconds to ninety seconds.
Give the checkpoint manager enough time to save before the instance is terminated.
Add a liveness probe.
Check a heartbeat file every sixty seconds.
If no heartbeat for five minutes, restart the pod.
This detects hung training loops.
Create a service account with S3 permissions.
Create an IAM policy that allows get, put, delete, and list on the checkpoint bucket.
Attach the policy to a role.
Annotate the service account with the role ARN.
Now let's add a PodDisruptionBudget for training jobs.
Set maxUnavailable to one.
With three parallel training jobs, at least two will always run.
This prevents Karpenter from consolidating all your training nodes at once.
Now let's implement multi-AZ Spot diversification.
Single-AZ Spot pools can run dry simultaneously.
All your Spot instances in us-east-1a get interrupted at the same time.
Spread across Availability Zones and instance families.
This reduces correlated interruptions.
Check Spot capacity across Availability Zones for your instance types.
Loop through each zone and each instance type.
Get the current Spot price.
Update your GPU NodePool to spread across Availability Zones.
Add a requirement for topology.kubernetes.io/zone.
List the zones you want to use.
Now let's monitor your Spot interruption rate.
Count Spot interruption events from Karpenter logs.
kubectl logs dash n karpenter dash l app.kubernetes.io/name=karpenter with since 720 hours.
Pipe to grep dash c interruption.
List checkpoints created by interrupted jobs.
aws s3api list-objects-v2 on the checkpoint bucket.
Check metadata for interruption counts per job.
Loop through each job prefix.
Download the latest-metadata.json file.
Extract the interruption count.
Now measure your savings.
Update your baseline document.
Add the capacity type distribution from your nodes.
Add the current Spot prices for GPU instances.
Add the total number of interruptions handled.
Add the compute cost comparison.
Before Spot, On-Demand g4dn.xlarge costs one thousand one hundred fifty-two dollars per month.
After Spot, g4dn.xlarge Spot at about thirty cents per hour costs two hundred eighty-eight dollars per month.
Monthly savings eight hundred sixty-four dollars. Seventy-five percent.
Let me recap what you've built in Series five.
You built a Spot price stability analysis script.
Evidence-based instance type selection.
You created an S3 checkpoint bucket with versioning and KMS encryption.
Durable, encrypted checkpoint storage.
You built a production CheckpointManager with SHA-256 verification.
Zero lost training progress.
You added a SIGTERM handler for Karpenter drain.
Clean shutdown within the two-minute window.
You added an IMDS SpotTerminationWatcher with five-second polling.
Second line of defence for interruptions.
You created a complete training script with Spot engineering.
End-to-end production pattern.
You created a Kubernetes Job with backoffLimit and graceful termination.
Automatic retry with checkpoint resume.
You implemented multi-AZ Spot diversification.
Reduced correlated interruption risk.
You added a PodDisruptionBudget for training.
Controlled disruption during consolidation.
You measured your savings and documented them.
Seventy-five percent GPU compute cost reduction.
Here's what you need before Series six.
First, at least one training job completed with Spot.
Check S3 for checkpoints.
aws s3 ls s3 colon slash slash dollar sign CHECKPOINT_BUCKET slash checkpoints slash.
Second, interruption count in metadata shows zero or more.
The job ran on Spot.
Third, your baseline document updated with Spot savings figures.
Fourth, PodDisruptionBudget applied to training workloads.
If you have all four, you're ready for Series six.
In Series six, we attack the second and third biggest line items.
Storage and databases.
Series two through five optimized compute.
It is the biggest line item. And you have cut it by sixty to seventy-five percent.
Series six attacks the second and third biggest line items.
Storage and databases.
S3 lifecycle policies that automatically move old data through tiers.
Standard to Infrequent Access to Glacier to Deep Archive.
RDS stop and start schedules. Lambda-driven. Save sixty percent on dev databases.
ECR image lifecycle policies.
Delete untagged images after fourteen days.
RDS Reserved Instance purchasing.
ElastiCache Reserved Nodes.
Terraform enforcement so none of it ever drifts back.
Expected savings from Series six.
One thousand two hundred to one thousand eight hundred dollars per month on a typical startup stack.
Permanent. Automated. Zero ongoing effort.
Let's go to Series six.
```
---
**END OF PHASE 5 — SERIES 5 COMPLETE**
**Total SRT lines:** 204
**Total duration:** Approximately 40-50 minutes
**What is covered in this SRT:**
| Section | Lines | Description |
|---------|-------|-------------|
| The Fear That Costs You 70% | 11-24 | Why teams avoid Spot, real cost of On-Demand |
| How Spot Interruption Works | 25-37 | 2-minute warning, IMDS endpoint, EventBridge |
| Environment Setup | 38-43 | Variables, verify Karpenter |
| Spot Price Stability Analysis | 44-58 | Coefficient of variation, stability scoring |
| S3 Checkpoint Bucket | 59-64 | Create bucket, versioning, lifecycle, encryption |
| CheckpointManager Implementation | 65-102 | Complete production checkpointing code |
| SpotTerminationWatcher | 103-112 | IMDS polling sidecar |
| Complete Training Script | 113-125 | End-to-end Spot-engineered training |
| Kubernetes Job with Spot | 126-139 | backoffLimit, terminationGracePeriodSeconds, liveness probe |
| Service Account with S3 Permissions | 140-143 | IAM policy, IRSA annotation |
| PodDisruptionBudget | 144-146 | maxUnavailable: 1 |
| Multi-AZ Spot Diversification | 147-151 | Spread across AZs |
| Monitor Interruption Rate | 152-159 | Count interruptions, check metadata |
| Savings Measurement | 160-166 | Update baseline, compute savings |
| Recap & Prerequisites | 167-189 | What you built, what's needed for Series 6 |
| Series 6 Preview | 191-204 | Storage and database optimizations |