Welcome back to the course.
In Series one, you built the foundation.
You learned what FinOps is. You learned the three phases.
You learned unit economics. You built a tagging strategy.
You created your baseline document.
In Series two, you found the waste outside the cluster.
You migrated gp2 volumes to gp3.
You released unattached Elastic IPs.
You added VPC Endpoints for S3 and DynamoDB.
In Series three, you deployed Kubecost.
You got visibility inside the cluster.
You applied rightsizing recommendations.
You reduced CPU requests by sixty percent.
In Series four, you deployed Karpenter.
You enabled continuous consolidation.
You added Spot versus On-Demand splits.
Your compute costs dropped by thirty-five percent.
In Series five, you went all in on Spot.
You implemented checkpointing.
You added Pod Disruption Budgets.
Your ML compute costs dropped by seventy to ninety percent.
Now it's time to talk about storage and databases.
The quiet killers.
The costs that don't go down when you scale in.
The bills that keep growing even when you're not adding users.
Storage and databases are different from compute.
Compute is elastic. You can scale it up and down.
You can use Spot. You can consolidate nodes.
You can turn it off when you don't need it.
Storage is persistent. Once you store data, it stays there.
You pay for it forever. Every month. Every byte.
Even if no one ever looks at it again.
Even if it's a log file from three years ago.
Even if it's a backup of a service that no longer exists.
Databases are stateful. You can't just turn them off.
You can't just scale them down without planning.
You have to think about data migration, connection pooling,
caching layers, read replicas, backup retention.
You have to plan.
But storage and databases also have huge opportunities
for savings.
S3 lifecycle policies can automatically move old data
to cheaper tiers.
S3 Intelligent-Tiering can do this automatically
without you writing rules.
ECR image cleanup can delete untagged images
you're not using.
RDS stop and start schedules can save you sixty percent
on development databases.
RDS reserved instances can save you forty to sixty percent
on production databases.
ElastiCache savings plans can save you on caching.
And all of this can be enforced with Terraform
so it never drifts.
Let me tell you a story.
Remember the startup from previous series?
After all their optimizations, their AWS bill was down
to twenty thousand dollars per month.
They were thrilled. But storage was still a problem.
A quiet problem. A problem that was growing every month
without anyone noticing.
They had fifteen terabytes of data in S3.
Most of it was old. Logs from six months ago.
Model checkpoints from failed experiments
that no one remembered.
Backup files from services that had been decommissioned.
User uploads from a feature that was deprecated.
All of it was sitting in S3 Standard.
S3 Standard costs two point three cents per gigabyte per month.
Fifteen terabytes costs three hundred forty-five dollars per month.
Not huge compared to their twenty thousand dollar bill.
But it was growing.
Every month, they added another terabyte.
Every month, the cost went up by twenty-three dollars.
In a year, that's two hundred seventy-six dollars more per month.
In two years, that's five hundred fifty-two dollars more per month.
It compounds.
We added lifecycle policies.
Data older than thirty days moved to Standard-IA
at one point two five cents per gigabyte.
Data older than ninety days moved to Glacier Instant Retrieval
at zero point four cents per gigabyte.
Data older than three hundred sixty-five days moved
to Glacier Deep Archive at zero point zero nine nine cents per gigabyte.
The cost dropped from three hundred forty-five dollars
to sixty dollars per month.
Savings of two hundred eighty-five dollars per month.
Over three thousand dollars per year.
And now it stays low. Old data automatically moves
to cheaper tiers. They don't have to think about it.
Then we looked at ECR.
Their container registry was a disaster.
Every build pushed a new image. Every developer pushed images
for their feature branches.
Every CI run pushed images for testing.
They never cleaned up.
They had over two thousand images. Many of them untagged.
Many of them from builds that failed.
Many of them from branches that were deleted months ago.
Many of them from experiments that never made it to production.
ECR storage costs ten cents per gigabyte per month.
Two thousand images, average size five hundred megabytes,
is one terabyte. One hundred dollars per month.
Not huge. But unnecessary.
All of those images were useless.
No one was ever going to use a failed build
from a deleted branch.
We added an ECR lifecycle policy.
Untagged images deleted after thirty days.
Images older than ninety days deleted regardless of tags.
Keep only the ten most recent images per repository.
The number of images dropped from two thousand to two hundred.
Storage cost dropped from one hundred dollars to ten dollars per month.
Then we looked at RDS.
Their production database was running on a db.r5.large instance.
On-Demand. No reserved instance.
They were paying two hundred dollars per month for a database
that could have cost one hundred twenty dollars
with a one-year reservation.
They had three development databases,
each running twenty-four seven.
No one used them at night. No one used them on weekends.
No one used them during holidays. But they were running.
They were costing money. They were wasting resources.
We purchased a one-year Regional Reserved Instance
for the production database.
Upfront payment of six hundred dollars.
Monthly cost dropped from two hundred dollars
to one hundred twenty dollars.
Break-even in five months. After that, pure savings.
Eight hundred dollars saved in the first year.
We added stop and start schedules for development databases.
Lambda functions stop instances at 8 PM and start them at 8 AM.
Stop on Friday night. Start on Monday morning.
Monthly cost dropped by sixty percent.
From sixty dollars to twenty-four dollars per database.
Three databases, savings of one hundred eight dollars per month.
Over one thousand two hundred dollars per year.
Then we looked at ElastiCache.
They had a Redis cluster for session storage.
On-Demand. No savings plan.
They were paying forty dollars per month for a cache
that could have cost twenty-five dollars with a savings plan.
We purchased a one-year savings plan.
Monthly cost dropped to twenty-five dollars.
Savings of fifteen dollars per month. One hundred eighty dollars per year.
Total storage and database savings.
Over six hundred dollars per month.
Seven thousand two hundred dollars per year.
Not the biggest savings in the course, but important.
And permanent. These controls don't need to be reapplied.
They just work.
That's what storage and database cost controls deliver.
Now let me show you how to do it.
First, let's set up our environment.
export ACCOUNT_ID equals aws sts get-caller-identity query Account output text.
export REGION equals us-east-1.
export START equals date minus d 30 days ago plus YYYY-MM-DD.
export END equals date plus YYYY-MM-DD.
Verify your current storage spend.
aws ce get-cost-and-usage with filter for S3, RDS, ElastiCache, and ECR.
Write this number down. It is your baseline for Series six.
Let's start with S3.
First, find your most expensive buckets.
Loop through all S3 buckets.
For each bucket, get the total size in gigabytes.
Calculate the estimated monthly cost at the Standard tier.
Sort by cost descending.
The top result is your most expensive bucket.
Now check the storage class distribution for each bucket.
List all objects. Count how many are in Standard,
how many in Standard-IA, how many in Glacier Instant Retrieval,
how many in Glacier Flexible Retrieval, and how many in Deep Archive.
If most objects are in Standard and the bucket is old,
you have a lifecycle policy problem.
Now check if lifecycle policies exist.
For each bucket, try to get the lifecycle configuration.
If the command fails, the bucket has no lifecycle policy.
Print the bucket name and its size.
These are your optimization targets.
Now let's understand the tiering strategy.
Data zero to thirty days old stays in Standard.
Cost two point three cents per gigabyte per month.
Active data. Frequent access.
Data thirty-one to ninety days old moves to Standard-IA.
Cost one point two five cents per gigabyte per month.
Infrequent but fast retrieval.
Data ninety-one to one hundred eighty days old moves
to Glacier Instant Retrieval.
Cost zero point four cents per gigabyte per month.
Rare access, instant retrieval.
Data one hundred eighty-one to three hundred sixty-five days old
moves to Glacier Flexible Retrieval.
Cost zero point three six cents per gigabyte per month.
Archive, minutes to retrieve.
Data older than three hundred sixty-five days moves
to Deep Archive.
Cost zero point zero nine nine cents per gigabyte per month.
Compliance, twelve to forty-eight hours retrieval.
Data older than seven hundred thirty days is deleted.
Gone forever.
There is a trap you need to understand.
The IA minimum charge trap.
S3 Standard-IA has a thirty-day minimum storage charge per object.
If you store a one kilobyte log file for one day and delete it,
you pay for thirty days.
Never use IA for objects smaller than one hundred twenty-eight kilobytes.
Never use IA for objects shorter-lived than thirty days.
The lifecycle policy below filters by object size to avoid this.
Create a lifecycle policy for the financial-rag documents bucket.
Rule one. Transition logs and old data.
Filter on the logs prefix and object size greater than one hundred twenty-eight kilobytes.
Transition to Standard-IA at thirty days.
Transition to Glacier Instant Retrieval at ninety days.
Transition to Deep Archive at three hundred sixty-five days.
Expire at seven hundred thirty days.
Rule two. Transition model checkpoints.
Filter on the checkpoints prefix.
Transition to Standard-IA at seven days.
Transition to Glacier Instant Retrieval at ninety days.
Expire at one hundred eighty days.
Rule three. Transition SEC filings.
Filter on the filings prefix.
Transition to Standard-IA at ninety days.
Transition to Glacier Instant Retrieval at three hundred sixty-five days.
Rule four. Delete incomplete multipart uploads after seven days.
Rule five. Clean old versions of objects.
Transition noncurrent versions to Standard-IA at thirty days.
Transition to Glacier Instant Retrieval at ninety days.
Expire noncurrent versions at three hundred sixty-five days.
Apply the lifecycle policy to the financial-rag documents bucket.
aws s3api put-bucket-lifecycle-configuration.
Verify the policy was applied.
aws s3api get-bucket-lifecycle-configuration.
Now bulk apply lifecycle to all unprotected buckets.
Create a script called bulk-apply-lifecycle.sh.
Loop through every bucket.
Check if a lifecycle policy already exists.
If not, apply a default lifecycle policy.
Transition large objects to Standard-IA at thirty days,
to Glacier Instant Retrieval at ninety days,
to Deep Archive at three hundred sixty-five days.
Expire at seven hundred thirty days.
Abort incomplete multipart uploads after seven days.
For buckets with unpredictable access patterns,
use S3 Intelligent-Tiering instead of manual lifecycle rules.
Riskoracle experiment outputs. Data science ad-hoc analysis.
You don't know when it will be accessed.
Intelligent-Tiering automatically moves data between tiers
based on access patterns.
No rules to write. No guessing.
Enable archive access tiers at ninety days.
Enable deep archive access at one hundred eighty days.
There is a monitoring fee. Two point five cents per thousand objects per month.
For a bucket with five hundred thousand objects, that is one dollar twenty-five cents per month.
If even twenty percent of your objects are infrequently accessed,
Intelligent-Tiering saves money.
For buckets with more than one hundred thousand objects
and unpredictable access, always use Intelligent-Tiering.
Now calculate your savings after applying lifecycle policies.
Write a Python script that iterates through all objects
in your bucket.
For each object, get its age in days.
Calculate current cost assuming all objects are in Standard.
Calculate projected cost based on your lifecycle policy.
Print current cost, projected cost, monthly savings,
and annual savings.
Run the script. You will likely see sixty to eighty percent savings.
Now let's audit your ECR repositories.
Loop through each repository.
Get the total image count, untagged image count,
total storage in gigabytes, and estimated monthly cost.
Print the results in a table.
Sort by cost descending.
Your top repository is your biggest waste source.
Apply a lifecycle policy to all repositories.
Rule one. Delete untagged images after fourteen days.
Rule two. Keep only the last five tagged images
per feature branch, fix branch, and hotfix branch.
Rule three. Keep only the last twenty images total.
Lifecycle policies are evaluated at push time AND daily by AWS.
They do not run immediately when you apply them.
The first cleanup runs within twenty-four hours.
Come back tomorrow and check your image counts.
You will typically see a sixty to eighty percent reduction.
Now let's add stop and start schedules for RDS development databases.
Development and staging databases run twenty-four seven.
Nobody uses them between 8 PM and 8 AM on weekdays,
or anytime on weekends.
That is one hundred twenty-eight hours per week of idle compute.
Fifty-four percent of the time.
A db.t4g.medium RDS instance costs six point five cents per hour On-Demand.
Running twenty-four seven is forty-seven dollars forty-five cents per month.
With stop and start schedule, eight AM to 8 PM weekdays only,
the cost is seventeen dollars forty-two cents per month.
Sixty-three percent savings.
We will use a Lambda function triggered by EventBridge.
Tag RDS instances with Schedule equals dev-hours to opt in.
Create the Lambda handler.
First, get the action from the event. Start or stop.
Log the action, timestamp, and day of week.
Find all instances tagged with Schedule equals dev-hours.
For each instance, check its current status.
If the action is stop and the instance is available, stop it.
If the action is start and the instance is stopped, start it.
Log all actions to CloudWatch for audit trail.
Deploy the Lambda function.
Package the code into a zip file.
Create an IAM role for Lambda.
Attach a policy allowing rds:DescribeDBInstances,
rds:ListTagsForResource, rds:StartDBInstance, rds:StopDBInstance,
and logs:CreateLogGroup, logs:CreateLogStream, logs:PutLogEvents.
Create the Lambda function with Python 3.11 runtime.
Set timeout to sixty seconds. Memory to one hundred twenty-eight megabytes.
Create EventBridge rules.
Stop at 8 PM weekdays. cron zero zero zero question mark question mark MON-FRI question mark.
Start at 8 AM weekdays. cron zero twelve zero question mark question mark MON-FRI question mark.
Grant EventBridge permission to invoke Lambda.
Add targets to each rule with the action payload.
Now tag your dev databases to opt in.
For each dev database identifier, get the database ARN.
Add a tag with key Schedule and value dev-hours.
Test the scheduler manually.
Invoke the Lambda with a stop action payload.
Check the instance states.
There is a trap you need to understand.
The seven-day RDS auto-restart.
AWS automatically restarts stopped RDS instances after seven days.
Regardless of your tags or configuration.
If a developer is on holiday and the instance restarts on day seven
and runs for a week, you have paid for it.
Mitigate by setting up a CloudWatch alarm that detects the auto-restart
and immediately re-stops the instance.
Create a CloudWatch alarm on the DatabaseConnections metric.
If connections exceed zero for five minutes, trigger the Lambda to stop the instance.
Now let's purchase RDS Reserved Instances for production databases.
First, get recommendations from Cost Explorer.
aws ce get-reservation-purchase-recommendation for RDS.
Look at the instance type, region, engine,
estimated savings amount, and estimated savings percentage.
Compare payment options.
No Upfront, Partial Upfront, and All Upfront.
For each, get the offering ID, fixed price, and usage price.
Calculate true break-even.
Write a Python script that accounts for upfront cost,
hourly rate, and opportunity cost.
Run the script for your instance type.
It will show you the total cost for each payment option
and the savings percentage.
Here are the rules for RI purchasing from real experience.
Only buy RIs for resources that have been running for thirty days or more.
Buying an RI for a service you deployed last week is premature.
You do not know if it will stick.
No Upfront is usually the right call for startups.
All Upfront saves slightly more, about five percent, but locks up cash.
For a startup, cash flow beats marginal savings.
Never buy three-year RIs for anything using rapidly changing instance types.
Graviton instances like r6g and m6g are already being superseded
by r7g and m7g.
A three-year r6g RI purchased today may be on a less-optimal instance type
by year two.
RIs are Regional, not Availability Zone specific.
A Regional RI applies to any Availability Zone in the region.
Always buy Regional.
Now purchase a Reserved Instance for ElastiCache.
Get recommendations from Cost Explorer for ElastiCache.
Find available offerings for your cache node type.
Purchase the reserved cache node.
Now let's enforce everything with Terraform.
Everything you have done manually must be Terraform-encoded
or it will drift back.
This is the discipline that separates a FinOps program
from a FinOps project.
Create a Terraform module for managed S3 buckets.
Enable versioning. Enable server-side encryption with KMS.
Add lifecycle rules for transition and expiration.
Add abort incomplete multipart upload rule.
Add noncurrent version transition and expiration.
Block public access.
Create a Terraform module for managed ECR repositories.
Set image tag mutability to immutable.
Enable image scanning on push.
Enable encryption with KMS.
Add a lifecycle policy to delete untagged images,
limit feature branch images, and keep only the last twenty images total.
Create a Terraform module for managed RDS databases.
Set storage type to gp3, never gp2.
Enable storage encryption.
Set backup retention period.
Set performance insights retention period.
Set deletion protection for production databases.
Add a tag for Schedule. Set it to dev-hours for non-production.
Set it to always-on for production.
Use lifecycle prevent destroy for production databases.
This prevents accidental deletion by a careless terraform destroy.
Add OPA policies for storage.
Deny any S3 bucket without a lifecycle configuration.
Deny any ECR repository without a lifecycle policy.
Deny any RDS instance using gp2 storage.
Warn for any non-production RDS instance without a Schedule tag.
Now update your baseline document.
Add S3 lifecycle coverage. How many buckets have lifecycle policies?
Add ECR lifecycle coverage. How many repositories have lifecycle policies?
Add RDS scheduled instances. List each instance with its status and schedule tag.
Add current storage and database spend.
Let me recap what you've built in Series six.
You added S3 lifecycle policies to all buckets.
Sixty to eighty percent savings on old data storage.
You enabled S3 Intelligent-Tiering for unpredictable access patterns.
Auto-optimized access cost.
You added ECR lifecycle policies to all repositories.
Eighty percent savings on ECR storage.
You built an RDS Lambda stop and start scheduler.
Sixty-three percent savings on development database cost.
You added a CloudWatch alarm for auto-restart detection.
Prevents silent auto-restart cost.
You purchased RDS Reserved Instances for production databases.
Forty percent savings on production database cost.
You purchased ElastiCache Reserved Nodes.
Thirty to forty percent savings on cache cost.
You created Terraform modules with lifecycle enforcement.
Zero drift on all controls.
You added OPA Terraform policies for storage.
CI enforcement of lifecycle rules.
Here's what you need before Series seven.
First, S3 lifecycle applied to all buckets.
Check with get-bucket-lifecycle-configuration.
Second, ECR lifecycle applied to all repositories.
Check with get-lifecycle-policy.
Third, at least one dev RDS instance tagged with Schedule equals dev-hours.
Check with list-tags-for-resource.
Fourth, Lambda scheduler deployed and tested.
Manual invocation returned results.
Fifth, your baseline document updated with storage and database spend.
If you have all five, you're ready for Series seven.
Series two through six covered the technical FinOps layer.
Finding, eliminating, and automating cost controls
at the infrastructure level.
The startup's bill went from forty-seven thousand dollars
to nineteen thousand four hundred four dollars.
But there is a problem.
You did all of this. You. Personally.
Running commands in a terminal, applying policies, tagging resources.
The moment a new engineer joins and creates a new S3 bucket,
a new RDS instance, or a new ECR repository.
They will not know about any of these controls.
They will create unoptimized resources. The waste will return.
Series seven starts the second half of this course.
Platform engineering.
You will learn what an Internal Developer Platform is
and why it is the only sustainable solution to long-term FinOps.
The controls you applied manually in Series two through six
become encoded into golden paths that every new engineer uses automatically.
Without knowing they are optimizing costs.
The startup that went from forty-seven thousand dollars
to nineteen thousand four hundred four dollars
stayed at nineteen thousand four hundred four dollars for eighteen months after.
Even as they grew from forty to eighty engineers.
Even as they added thirty new services.
Because they had a platform.
Not because they had a FinOps engineer watching everything.
That is what you are going to build.
Let's go to Series seven.
```
---
**END OF PHASE 6 — SERIES 6 COMPLETE**
**Total SRT lines:** 250
**Total duration:** Approximately 60-70 minutes (adjust timestamps upward for slower pacing)
**What is covered in this SRT:**
| Section | Lines | Description |
|---------|-------|-------------|
| The Costs That Never Go Down | 12-29 | Why storage and databases are different from compute |
| The Numbers | 29-74 | Startup story: S3, ECR, RDS, ElastiCache savings |
| Environment Setup | 77-80 | Variables, verify storage spend baseline |
| S3 Cost Analysis | 82-89 | Find expensive buckets, storage class distribution |
| S3 Lifecycle Policies | 91-125 | Tiering strategy, IA minimum charge trap, apply policies, bulk apply, Intelligent-Tiering, savings calculation |
| ECR Image Lifecycle | 126-136 | Audit repositories, apply lifecycle policies, 24-hour cleanup window |
| RDS Stop/Start Schedules | 137-169 | Lambda scheduler, EventBridge rules, tag dev databases, 7-day auto-restart trap, CloudWatch alarm |
| RDS Reserved Instance Purchasing | 170-185 | Cost Explorer recommendations, compare payment options, RI calculator, purchasing rules |
| ElastiCache Reserved Nodes | 186-189 | Get recommendations, purchase |
| Terraform Enforcement | 190-209 | S3 module, ECR module, RDS module, OPA storage policies |
| Update Baseline | 210-213 | Measure coverage and spend |
| Recap & Prerequisites | 214-232 | What you built, what's needed for Series 7 |
| Series 7 Preview | 234-250 | Platform engineering, IDP, golden paths |