Welcome back to the course.
In Series one, you built the foundation.
You learned what FinOps is. You learned the three phases.
You learned unit economics. You built a tagging strategy.
You created your baseline document.
In Series two, you found the waste outside the cluster.
You migrated gp2 volumes to gp3.
You released unattached Elastic IPs.
You added VPC Endpoints for S3 and DynamoDB.
You identified thousands of dollars in monthly waste.
In Series three, you deployed Kubecost.
You got visibility inside the cluster.
You saw cost per namespace. You saw cost per team.
You saw efficiency scores.
You applied rightsizing recommendations.
You reduced CPU requests by sixty percent.
You reduced memory requests by forty percent.
But here's the thing about rightsizing.
It's a one-time fix.
You reduce the CPU requests on a deployment.
The deployment restarts.
The pods come up with the new resource requests.
The cluster now has more free capacity.
But the nodes are still there.
The EC2 instances that were running before are still running.
The EC2 instances that were added to handle the larger resource requests
are still there. You're still paying for them.
You reduced the demand, but you didn't reduce the supply.
You need something that continuously optimizes your compute.
Something that watches your cluster's resource usage
in real time and automatically adjusts the underlying EC2 instances.
Something that launches new instances when you need more capacity,
in seconds, not minutes.
Something that removes instances when you don't need them,
without waiting for a long utilization threshold.
Something that chooses the cheapest available instance type
from a list you provide, not just a single predefined type.
Something that supports Spot instances natively,
so you can run fault-tolerant workloads at seventy percent off.
That something is Karpenter.
Series four is where you deploy Karpenter.
Karpenter is Kubernetes-native autoscaling.
It's an open-source project from AWS.
It was announced at re:Invent in 2021.
It reached general availability in 2022.
It's now used by thousands of companies, from startups to enterprises.
And it replaces the traditional Cluster Autoscaler.
Completely. You don't need both. You just need Karpenter.
Let me explain why the Cluster Autoscaler is costing you money.
Most EKS clusters ship with the Cluster Autoscaler.
It was the standard for years.
But it has three fundamental problems that cost you money
every single day.
Problem one. It is slow.
The Cluster Autoscaler adds nodes only after pods fail to schedule.
A pod enters Pending state. The autoscaler notices.
It calculates what instance size fits.
It calls EC2. It waits for the instance to boot.
That process takes four to eight minutes.
During those minutes, your users wait or your jobs queue.
Problem two. It is rigid.
You define one instance type per node group. t3.large. That is it.
If t4g.large ARM instances are twenty percent cheaper right now,
you cannot use them.
If Spot prices dropped for m6i.xlarge, you cannot benefit.
The Cluster Autoscaler has no concept of price optimization.
It just launches whatever you configured months ago.
Problem three. It is slow to remove nodes.
The Cluster Autoscaler waits for a node to be underutilised
for a configurable period, typically ten to twenty minutes.
Before removing it. During that window, you are paying for idle compute.
On a busy cluster with frequent scaling events,
this idle time compounds into hundreds of dollars per month.
Karpenter solves all three.
It was built at AWS specifically because the Cluster Autoscaler
could not meet the cost and performance requirements
of large-scale Kubernetes at AWS.
Speed. Karpenter watches the Kubernetes scheduler directly.
The moment a pod cannot schedule, Karpenter already knows.
In milliseconds.
It launches a node in seconds, not minutes.
Price optimization. You give Karpenter a list of instance families.
It queries EC2 Spot and On-Demand prices in real time.
It picks the cheapest instance type that fits your pods.
Right now, not when you configured the cluster.
Aggressive consolidation. Karpenter does not wait
for underutilisation thresholds.
It continuously evaluates whether pods can be packed more tightly.
When they can, it drains a node, moves the pods,
and terminates the instance.
Your cluster stays right-sized continuously, not periodically.
Spot-native. Karpenter manages the Spot versus On-Demand split
as a first-class feature.
You define capacity types. Karpenter handles the interruption signals,
cordon slash drain sequences, and fallback to On-Demand automatically.
Let me give you the numbers from our startup story.
After Series two and Series three, the startup's bill
was thirty-four thousand eight hundred dollars per month.
Their compute situation before Karpenter.
Fifteen t3.large On-Demand nodes at eight point three two cents per hour.
Cluster Autoscaler managing scale-out.
Nodes sitting at thirty-five to forty-five percent utilisation
most of the time.
Monthly compute cost: four thousand three hundred twenty dollars.
After deploying Karpenter with consolidation and Spot.
Five to eight nodes. Mix of t4g.large Spot and m6i.large On-Demand.
Continuous consolidation removing idle nodes within thirty seconds.
Average cluster utilisation: seventy-two percent.
Monthly compute cost: one thousand eight hundred ninety dollars.
Compute savings: two thousand four hundred thirty dollars per month.
Twenty-nine thousand one hundred sixty dollars per year.
From one afternoon of work.
Combined with Series two and three,
the bill went from forty-seven thousand dollars to twenty thousand dollars.
That is the story you will replicate.
Now let me show you how to deploy it.
Before we deploy Karpenter, you need a few things.
Let me walk through each prerequisite.
First, you need an EKS cluster.
You should already have one from Series three.
If you don't, go back and create one.
The GitHub repository for this course has Terraform configurations
for financial-rag-agent and riskoracle. Use those.
Make sure your cluster is at least version 1.24 or newer.
Karpenter works best on recent Kubernetes versions.
Second, you need Kubecost running.
You should already have this from Series three.
Kubecost gives you the visibility you need to know
if Karpenter is working.
You can see the node count drop in real time.
You can see the cost per namespace drop.
You can see the efficiency scores improve.
Without Kubecost, you're flying blind.
With Kubecost, you can see exactly how much money
Karpenter is saving you.
Third, you need the AWS CLI configured with permissions
to launch EC2 instances.
Karpenter needs to call EC2 APIs.
It needs to launch instances. It needs to terminate instances.
It needs to tag instances. It needs to describe instances.
It needs to create launch templates.
You should already have this from Series one and two.
If you can run aws ec2 describe-instances, you're probably fine.
Fourth, you need IAM roles for Karpenter.
Karpenter runs inside your cluster as a set of pods.
Those pods need permissions to call AWS APIs.
You can't just give them your AWS access keys. That's insecure.
Instead, you create an IAM role.
You attach policies to that role.
Then you associate that role with the Kubernetes service account
that Karpenter uses.
This is called IAM roles for service accounts.
It's the standard way to give Kubernetes pods AWS permissions.
First, you must remove the Cluster Autoscaler.
You cannot run Karpenter and the Cluster Autoscaler simultaneously.
They will fight over nodes.
Check if Cluster Autoscaler is running.
kubectl get deployment cluster-autoscaler dash n kube-system
If it exists, remove it.
kubectl delete deployment cluster-autoscaler dash n kube-system
Delete the cluster role binding, the cluster role,
and the service account.
Verify removal.
kubectl get deployment cluster-autoscaler dash n kube-system
Do not skip this step.
Running both autoscalers simultaneously causes a race condition.
They continuously fight to add and remove the same nodes.
I have seen this cost a client eight thousand dollars
in a single weekend from a node thrashing loop.
Now let's create the IAM role for Karpenter.
First, get your cluster's OIDC provider ID.
OIDC stands for OpenID Connect.
It's how Kubernetes authenticates with AWS.
Each EKS cluster has a unique OIDC provider.
aws eks describe-cluster with name your cluster name
query cluster identity oidc issuer
Extract the ID from the end of the URL.
OIDC_ID equals that ID.
Now create the IAM policy document.
This defines what permissions Karpenter needs.
The policy allows ec2:RunInstances, ec2:CreateFleet,
ec2:TerminateInstances.
It allows ec2:DescribeInstances, ec2:DescribeInstanceTypes,
ec2:DescribeLaunchTemplates.
It allows ec2:DescribeSubnets, ec2:DescribeSecurityGroups.
And iam:PassRole to pass the node IAM role to EC2 instances.
Save this as karpenter-controller-policy.json.
Now create the policy in AWS.
aws iam create-policy with policy name
KarpenterControllerPolicy dash your cluster name
Policy document from the json file.
Get the policy ARN from the output. Write it down.
Now create the trust policy.
The trust policy defines who can assume this role.
We want the Kubernetes service account in the karpenter namespace
to assume it.
The trust policy uses the OIDC provider ID we extracted.
It allows the service account system colon serviceaccount colon karpenter colon karpenter to assume the role.
Save this as karpenter-trust-policy.json.
Now create the IAM role.
aws iam create-role with role name
KarpenterControllerRole dash your cluster name
Assume role policy document from the trust policy json.
Now attach the policy to the role.
aws iam attach-role-policy with role name and policy ARN.
Now create the node IAM role.
This role is assumed by the EC2 instances themselves.
They need permissions to join the cluster,
pull images from ECR, and send logs to CloudWatch.
Create the role with trust policy allowing ec2.amazonaws.com.
Attach the required managed policies.
AmazonEKSWorkerNodePolicy, AmazonEKS_CNI_Policy,
AmazonEC2ContainerRegistryReadOnly, AmazonSSMManagedInstanceCore.
Create an instance profile.
aws iam create-instance-profile with name
KarpenterNodeInstanceProfile dash your cluster name.
Add the role to the instance profile.
Now you have both IAM roles.
One for the Karpenter controller. One for the EC2 nodes.
Karpenter needs an SQS queue to receive Spot interruption notifications
from AWS.
Without this, it cannot proactively drain Spot nodes
before they are reclaimed.
Pods get killed instead of gracefully migrated.
Create the interruption queue.
aws sqs create-queue with queue name your cluster name.
Message retention period three hundred seconds.
Five minutes is plenty. Spot warnings give you two minutes.
Get the queue ARN. Then set the queue policy to allow EventBridge.
Now create EventBridge rules for Spot interruption,
scheduled change, and state change.
For each rule, set the event pattern.
For Spot interruption, source aws dot ec2,
detail-type EC2 Spot Instance Interruption Warning.
For scheduled change, source aws dot health,
detail-type AWS Health Event.
For state change, source aws dot ec2,
detail-type EC2 Instance State-change Notification.
Add a target to each rule pointing to your SQS queue.
Now Karpenter can listen for interruption signals.
When a Spot node is about to be reclaimed, Karpenter knows
with two minutes of warning.
Now you need to tag your subnets and security groups.
Karpenter discovers subnets and security groups by tag.
Without this, it cannot launch nodes.
Get your VPC ID.
aws ec2 describe-vpcs filter non-default VPCs.
Get all private subnet IDs.
For each subnet, add the tag karpenter.sh/discovery equals your cluster name.
Get the node security group.
aws ec2 describe-security-groups with tag aws:eks:cluster-name.
Add the same tag to the security group.
Now Karpenter can find your subnets and security groups.
Now install Karpenter using Helm.
Set Karpenter version. Use v0.37.0. It is stable.
Add the Karpenter Helm repository.
helm repo add karpenter https://charts.karpenter.sh
helm repo update
Install Karpenter from the OCI registry.
helm install karpenter oci://public.ecr.aws/karpenter/karpenter
Version dash dash version, namespace karpenter, create namespace.
Set settings.clusterName to your cluster name.
Set settings.interruptionQueue to your cluster name.
Set serviceAccount annotations with the IAM role ARN.
Set controller resources requests and limits.
One CPU, one gigabyte of memory.
Wait for the installation.
Verify the installation.
kubectl get pods dash n karpenter
kubectl logs dash n karpenter dash l app.kubernetes.io/name=karpenter
Expected log output shows Starting controller,
Connected to cluster, Starting informers.
If you see IAM errors, your IRSA annotation or trust policy is wrong.
The most common mistake is a mismatch between the OIDC ID
in the role trust policy and the actual cluster OIDC ID.
Now create the EC2NodeClass.
The EC2NodeClass tells Karpenter how to configure the EC2 instances
it launches.
AMI, subnets, security groups, instance profile, user data.
Use Amazon Linux 2023.
Better security posture than Amazon Linux 2.
Set the role to the node IAM role we created.
KarpenterNodeRole dash your cluster name.
Discover subnets by tag.
karpenter.sh/discovery equals your cluster name.
Discover security groups by the same tag.
Add tags to all nodes.
Name, Environment, ManagedBy, Team, CostCenter, Owner.
These tags are critical for Cost Explorer attribution.
They also enforce the six tags from Series one.
Block device. Use gp3, never gp2.
One hundred gigabytes. Three thousand IOPS. One hundred twenty-five throughput.
Encrypted true. Delete on termination true.
Always use encrypted true on node volumes.
In financial services environments, unencrypted EBS volumes
on worker nodes can be a SOC2 finding.
Cost is negligible. There is no performance impact for gp3 with encryption.
Apply the EC2NodeClass.
kubectl apply dash f dash dash filename
Now create the NodePools.
NodePools define what nodes Karpenter is allowed to provision.
Create separate NodePools for different workload types.
This is where cost optimization really happens.
First, the application NodePool.
For your API and agent services.
Requirements. Architecture amd64 and arm64.
Include ARM for cost savings.
Instance families. Broad selection gives Karpenter more pricing options.
Graviton instances like m7g and c7g are about twenty percent cheaper
than x86 equivalents.
Instance sizes. Large, xlarge, 2xlarge, 4xlarge.
Exclude nano, micro, small. Not suitable for production pods.
Capacity types. Both on-demand and spot.
Add a taint so only application pods schedule here.
key dedicated, value application, effect NoSchedule.
Hard limits. CPU two hundred cores. Memory eight hundred gigabytes.
Prevent runaway scaling from a misconfigured HPA.
Disruption. Consolidation policy WhenUnderutilized.
Consolidate after thirty seconds. Aggressive but appropriate for production.
Expire after seven hundred twenty hours. Thirty days.
Nodes are replaced monthly with the latest Amazon Linux AMI.
Weight one hundred. Higher weight means this NodePool is preferred.
Now the ingestion NodePool.
For batch workloads like SEC EDGAR ingestion.
Requirements. Compute-optimised instance families.
c5, c6i, c6a, c6g, c7i, c7g.
Spot only. Batch jobs tolerate interruption with checkpointing.
We will cover checkpointing in Series five.
Taint for ingestion workloads.
Consolidation policy WhenEmpty. Only consolidate when completely empty.
In-flight ingestion jobs should not be interrupted mid-batch.
Consolidate after five minutes.
Now the GPU NodePool for ML workloads.
For riskoracle's risk calculation engine.
Requirements. GPU instance families.
g4dn, g5, p3, p4d.
Spot preferred. Training jobs checkpoint every ten minutes.
They can tolerate interruption.
Taint for GPU nodes. nvidia.com/gpu with effect NoSchedule.
Consolidation policy WhenEmpty. Consolidate after two minutes.
Expire after twenty-four hours.
Lower weight. Ten. Prefer cheaper instance types in other pools.
Apply all three NodePools.
Verify. kubectl get nodepool. kubectl get ec2nodeclass.
Now add tolerations to your workloads.
NodePool taints mean pods need matching tolerations to schedule there.
For the financial-rag-agent API, add the application toleration.
key dedicated, value application, effect NoSchedule.
Also add a nodeSelector. role equals application.
For the ingestion workloads, add the ingestion toleration.
And the Spot toleration. karpenter.sh/capacity-type equals spot.
NodeSelector role equals ingestion.
For the GPU ML workloads, add the nvidia.com/gpu toleration.
NodeSelector role equals gpu-ml.
Now test Karpenter in action.
Test scale-out speed.
Deploy a burst of pods that require new nodes.
kubectl create deployment burst-test with image nginx,
replicas 20, namespace default.
Time how long it takes for nodes to appear.
time kubectl wait for condition available deployment slash burst-test.
Watch nodes appear in real time.
kubectl get nodes dash w
You should see new nodes within thirty to forty-five seconds.
Compare this to Cluster Autoscaler's four to eight minutes.
Clean up the test deployment.
kubectl delete deployment burst-test
Now watch consolidation.
Scale down to create underutilised nodes.
kubectl scale deployment financial-rag-agent-api
dash dash replicas 1 dash n financial-rag
Watch Karpenter consolidate within thirty seconds.
Check Karpenter logs for consolidation events.
kubectl logs dash n karpenter dash l app.kubernetes.io/name=karpenter
dash dash follow dash dash tail 30
Pipe to grep dash iE consolidate or disrupt or terminat.
Expected log output.
disrupting node for consolidation reason underutilized.
cordon triggered. node deleted.
Now verify Spot node selection.
kubectl get nodes with custom columns for instance type, capacity type, and architecture.
You should see a mix of on-demand and spot nodes.
Different instance types. Some amd64, some arm64.
Now add PodDisruptionBudgets for production safety.
Karpenter's consolidation must respect your availability requirements.
Without disruption budgets, Karpenter might try to consolidate
two nodes simultaneously, temporarily reducing your replica count to zero.
For the financial-rag API, set maxUnavailable to one.
Never take down more than one pod during consolidation.
For the agent, set minAvailable to two.
Maintain at least two replicas during consolidation.
Apply the PodDisruptionBudgets.
kubectl apply dash f
Verify Karpenter respects your PDBs.
kubectl get pdb dash dash all-namespaces
Now update your baseline document.
echo three equals signs SERIES 4 KARPENTER DEPLOYMENT
with date.
echo dash dash dash NODE COUNT dash dash dash
kubectl get nodes dash dash no-headers pipe wc dash l
echo dash dash dash INSTANCE TYPE DISTRIBUTION dash dash dash
kubectl get nodes dash o json with jq to get instance types
echo dash dash dash SPOT VS ON-DEMAND SPLIT dash dash dash
kubectl get nodes dash o json with jq to get capacity types
echo dash dash dash CONSOLIDATION EVENTS LAST 24 HOURS dash dash dash
kubectl logs with grep dash c consolidation
echo dash dash dash NODEPOOLS dash dash dash
kubectl get nodepool
View your updated baseline.
cat tilde slash finops-baseline.txt
Let me recap what you've built in Series four.
You removed the Cluster Autoscaler.
You eliminated the race condition and node thrashing.
You created IAM roles for Karpenter with least-privilege IRSA.
Secure, scoped EC2 permissions.
You created an SQS queue for Spot interruption handling.
Karpenter can now drain Spot nodes gracefully before they are reclaimed.
You created an EC2NodeClass with gp3 volumes and encryption.
Compliant, cost-optimized nodes.
You created three NodePools.
Application, ingestion, and GPU.
Workload-appropriate instance selection.
You enabled consolidation with thirty second response time.
Continuous node count optimization.
You added PodDisruptionBudgets on critical workloads.
Zero-downtime consolidation.
You updated your baseline with node metrics.
Before and after compute cost data.
Here's what you need before Series five.
First, Karpenter must be running.
kubectl get pods dash n karpenter. All pods Running.
Second, at least one consolidation event visible in logs.
kubectl logs dash n karpenter with grep consolidat.
Third, Spot nodes being selected.
kubectl get nodes dash l karpenter.sh/capacity-type equals spot.
Fourth, PodDisruptionBudgets applied to all stateful workloads.
kubectl get pdb dash dash all-namespaces.
Fifth, your baseline document updated with node distribution.
If you have all five, you're ready for Series five.
In Series five, we go all in on Spot instances.
We engineer for interruptions, not just tolerate them.
You will implement checkpointing for riskoracle ML training jobs.
Save to S3 every ten minutes. Resume from checkpoint after interruption.
You will add SIGTERM signal handlers that trigger a clean save
before instance termination.
You will size Pod Disruption Budgets correctly
for Spot interruption probability.
You will implement multi-region Spot capacity diversification.
When one Availability Zone runs out, fail to another.
You will add the IMDS metadata watcher pattern
for two-minute interruption warning detection.
You will analyze Spot price history to pick stable instance types.
The goal. Run eighty percent of your ML workloads on Spot
at seventy percent off. With zero job failures.
That is not theoretical. We do it on riskoracle.
You will do it too.
Let's go to Series five.
```
---
**END OF PHASE 4 — SERIES 4 COMPLETE**
**Total SRT lines:** 249
**Total duration:** Approximately 50-60 minutes (adjust timestamps upward for slower pacing)
**What is covered in this SRT:**
| Section | Lines | Description |
|---------|-------|-------------|
| Why Cluster Autoscaler Costs Money | 28-43 | Three fundamental problems |
| What Karpenter Does Differently | 43-52 | Speed, price optimization, consolidation, Spot-native |
| Startup Story Numbers | 53-64 | $47k → $20k, compute savings $2,430/month |
| Prerequisites | 66-83 | EKS cluster, Kubecost, AWS CLI, IAM |
| Remove Cluster Autoscaler | 84-91 | Must remove before installing Karpenter |
| IAM Role for Karpenter | 92-117 | Controller policy, trust policy, node role, instance profile |
| SQS Queue for Spot Interruption | 118-129 | EventBridge rules for interruption signals |
| Tag Subnets and Security Groups | 130-136 | Karpenter discovers by tag |
| Install Karpenter via Helm | 137-150 | Helm install, verify logs |
| EC2NodeClass | 151-163 | AMI, subnets, security groups, gp3 with encryption |
| NodePools (3 types) | 164-187 | Application, ingestion, GPU |
| Add Tolerations to Workloads | 189-194 | Match NodePool taints |
| Test Karpenter | 195-209 | Scale-out speed, consolidation, Spot selection |
| PodDisruptionBudgets | 210-215 | Protect critical workloads |
| Update Baseline | 216-223 | Node count, instance types, Spot split |
| Recap & Prerequisites | 224-239 | What you built, what's needed for Series 5 |
| Series 5 Preview | 240-249 | Spot engineering with checkpointing |