Welcome back to the course.
In Series one, you built the foundation.
You learned what FinOps is. You learned the three phases.
You learned unit economics. You built a tagging strategy.
You created your baseline document.
In Series two, you found the waste outside the cluster.
You migrated gp2 volumes to gp3.
You released unattached Elastic IPs.
You cleaned up stopped instances.
You added VPC Endpoints for S3 and DynamoDB.
You identified thousands of dollars in monthly waste.
That was the low-hanging fruit.
That was Phase one of FinOps. The Inform phase at the AWS account level.
Now it's time to go deeper. Much deeper.
Series three is where we move from account-level visibility
to namespace-level visibility.
From service-level cost to pod-level cost.
From guessing which team spent what to knowing exactly which deployment
is wasting money.
Series three is where we deploy Kubecost on EKS.
Before we deploy, let me explain why AWS Cost Explorer is not enough.
AWS Cost Explorer shows you EC2 cost.
It shows you EBS cost. It shows you NAT Gateway cost.
But it cannot answer the question that actually matters
to an engineering team running Kubernetes.
Which namespace, which deployment, which pod is wasting my money?
Cost Explorer operates at the AWS resource level.
It does not know about Kubernetes concepts.
It does not know that ten pods are sharing one EC2 instance.
It does not know which namespace owns which pod.
It does not know that the llm-ingest deployment requested eight CPUs
and only uses two.
Kubecost does.
Kubecost sits inside your cluster.
It watches every pod, namespace, deployment, and persistent volume claim.
It collects CPU, memory, storage, and network metrics every thirty seconds.
It combines those Kubernetes metrics with your AWS billing data.
It calculates exactly how much of each EC2 instance's cost
should be attributed to each pod.
Then it rolls that up to namespace, team, and service.
The result. You go from "our EC2 bill is twenty-two thousand dollars"
to "the financial-rag namespace is spending fourteen thousand two hundred dollars
at forty-eight percent efficiency."
And the llm-ingest deployment is the top contributor.
That is the difference between guessing and knowing.
Let me tell you the rest of the story.
After the waste audit in Series two, that same startup's bill
dropped from forty-seven thousand dollars to thirty-four thousand eight hundred.
They were thrilled. They thought they were done.
But inside the cluster, there was more waste. Much more.
We deployed Kubecost. Within one hour.
The financial-rag namespace was costing twenty-two thousand dollars per month.
At zero point four eight efficiency. Wasting fifty-two percent of requested compute.
The riskoracle namespace was costing nine thousand dollars per month.
At zero point six one efficiency. Wasting thirty-nine percent.
Kube-system and monitoring together were costing three thousand eight hundred dollars.
We applied the rightsizing recommendations.
CPU requests reduced by sixty percent. Memory requests reduced by forty percent.
Karpenter, which we will cover in Series four,
removed the now-empty nodes.
The financial-rag namespace dropped from twenty-two thousand dollars
to fourteen thousand dollars.
Riskoracle dropped from nine thousand dollars to six thousand dollars.
Combined with Series two savings.
Total bill went from forty-seven thousand dollars to twenty thousand dollars.
In two series.
That's what Kubecost delivers.
Now let me show you how to deploy it.
Before we deploy Kubecost, you need a few things.
Let me walk through each prerequisite.
First, you need an EKS cluster.
EKS stands for Elastic Kubernetes Service.
It's Amazon's managed Kubernetes service.
If you don't have an EKS cluster, pause this video and create one.
You have several options. You can use the AWS console.
Go to the EKS service, click Create cluster, give it a name.
Choose a Kubernetes version, choose a role, and click create.
It takes about fifteen minutes.
You can use eksctl. eksctl is a command-line tool for EKS.
One command. eksctl create cluster with name finops-cluster,
region us-east-1, nodegroup-name standard-workers, node-type t3.medium, nodes three.
It takes about fifteen minutes.
You can use Terraform.
The GitHub repository for this course has Terraform configurations
for financial-rag-agent and riskoracle.
Clone the repo, run terraform apply,
and you'll have a cluster with both applications deployed.
That's the best option because you'll have real workloads to optimize.
Whichever method you choose, make sure your cluster has at least three nodes.
Each node should be at least t3.medium or equivalent.
You need enough resources to run Kubecost
alongside your applications.
Second, you need kubectl installed and configured.
Kubectl is the command-line tool for Kubernetes.
It's how you deploy and manage applications on your cluster.
You use it to create resources, delete resources, view logs, exec into containers.
Verify that kubectl can talk to your cluster.
Run kubectl get nodes.
You should see a list of nodes. Each node will have a name,
a status, a role, an age, and a version.
The status should be Ready.
If you see NotReady, your cluster has problems.
If you see an error that says "Unable to connect to the server",
your kubeconfig is not configured correctly.
To configure your kubeconfig, run this command.
aws eks update-kubeconfig with region dollar sign REGION
and name your-cluster-name.
Replace your-cluster-name with the actual name of your EKS cluster.
This command downloads the cluster's certificate and configures kubectl to use it.
Now run kubectl get nodes again. You should see your nodes.
Third, you need Helm installed.
Helm is the package manager for Kubernetes.
Think of it as apt-get or brew for Kubernetes.
It packages Kubernetes resources into charts.
A chart can contain deployments, services, config maps, secrets,
persistent volume claims, ingress rules, everything your application needs.
We're going to install Kubecost using Helm.
The Kubecost chart contains about thirty different Kubernetes resources.
Without Helm, you'd have to create each one manually.
With Helm, it's one command.
Verify that Helm is installed. Run helm version.
You should see a version number.
If you get an error that says command not found, you need to install Helm.
On Mac, brew install helm. On Ubuntu, sudo apt install helm.
On Windows, download the installer from the Helm website.
It takes two minutes.
Fourth, you need the AWS CLI configured with permissions
to read billing data.
Kubecost needs to call AWS Cost Explorer to get your account's pricing information.
It needs to know how much EC2 costs per hour,
how much EBS costs per gigabyte, how much NAT Gateway costs per gigabyte.
Without this, Kubecost can only estimate costs based on public pricing.
With it, Kubecost shows your actual costs including discounts,
Savings Plans, and Reserved Instances.
You should already have this from Series one and two.
You ran aws ce get-cost-and-usage and it returned your total monthly spend.
If that worked, your AWS CLI is configured correctly.
If not, go back to Series one and fix it.
Now you're ready.
First, add the Kubecost Helm repository.
A Helm repository is a collection of charts.
The Kubecost repository contains the Kubecost chart
and all its dependencies.
helm repo add kubecost https://kubecost.github.io/cost-analyzer/
You'll see output like kubecost has been added to your repositories.
Now update your local cache of available charts.
This downloads the latest list of charts and versions from the repository.
helm repo update
You'll see output like Hang tight while we grab the latest from your chart repositories.
Now create a namespace for Kubecost.
Namespaces are how Kubernetes organizes resources.
They're like folders on a filesystem.
Putting Kubecost in its own namespace keeps it separate from your applications.
It also makes it easier to clean up later if you need to.
kubectl create namespace kubecost
You'll see namespace slash kubecost created.
Now let's verify the namespace exists.
kubectl get namespaces
You should see kubecost in the list, along with default,
kube-system, kube-public, and any other namespaces you have.
Now install Kubecost. This is the main command.
Copy it carefully.
helm install kubecost kubecost/cost-analyzer
with namespace kubecost
set kubecostToken equals your email at company.com
set global.aws.enabled equals true
set global.aws.cloudIntegrationEnabled equals true
set prometheus.server.persistentVolume.enabled equals false
set kubecostProductConfigs.clusterName equals finops-cluster
set kubecostProductConfigs.currencyCode equals USD
Let me break down each parameter so you understand
what you're running.
helm install kubecost tells Helm to install a chart
with the release name kubecost.
The release name is like a label for this installation.
You can name it anything you want, but kubecost is fine.
kubecost/cost-analyzer is the chart name.
It's in the kubecost repository we added earlier.
The chart name is cost-analyzer, but the repository is kubecost.
So together it's kubecost/cost-analyzer.
dash dash namespace kubecost tells Helm to install the resources
in the kubecost namespace.
All the pods, services, config maps, secrets,
and persistent volume claims will be created inside this namespace.
dash set kubecostToken sets a configuration value.
Kubecost uses this token for analytics.
They want to know how many people are using their software.
It's not required, but it's polite.
You can use your email address instead of mine.
Use whatever you want.
dash set global.aws.enabled equals true tells Kubecost
that you're running on AWS.
This enables AWS-specific features.
It changes the default pricing from GCP pricing to AWS pricing.
It enables integration with AWS services.
dash set global.aws.cloudIntegrationEnabled equals true
tells Kubecost to integrate with AWS's cloud billing APIs.
This is how Kubecost gets your actual EC2 pricing,
your actual EBS pricing, your actual NAT Gateway pricing.
Including any discounts, Savings Plans, or Reserved Instances you have.
Without this, Kubecost estimates costs based on public on-demand pricing.
With this, Kubecost shows your actual costs.
dash set prometheus.server.persistentVolume.enabled equals false
tells Kubecost not to create a persistent volume for Prometheus.
Prometheus is the time-series database that Kubecost uses
to store metrics.
It collects CPU usage, memory usage, network traffic,
and other metrics every thirty seconds.
By default, Prometheus stores these metrics on a persistent volume
so they survive restarts.
But for testing and for this course, you don't need persistent storage.
Setting this to false saves you money on EBS volumes.
dash set kubecostProductConfigs.clusterName labels all cost data
with your cluster name.
This is critical for multi-cluster setups.
If you have dev, staging, and prod clusters, you need to know which cluster
is spending what.
dash set kubecostProductConfigs.currencyCode sets the currency
for cost display. USD is fine.
Now wait for Kubecost to start.
This takes a few minutes.
The first time you install Kubecost, it needs to download container images
from Docker Hub. It needs to start the pods.
It needs to initialize the databases. It needs to scrape metrics
for the first time.
Watch the pods come up.
kubectl get pods dash n kubecost
You'll see several pods. Let me explain what each one does.
The kubecost-cost-analyzer pod is the main Kubecost pod.
It runs the API server, the UI server, and the cost calculation engine.
It's the brain of Kubecost.
The prometheus-server pod runs Prometheus,
the time-series database. It stores all the metrics.
CPU usage, memory usage, network traffic, storage usage, everything.
The kubecost-grafana pod runs Grafana,
a dashboarding tool.
Kubecost includes a pre-configured Grafana instance
with dashboards for cost visualization.
The kubecost-network-costs pod collects network traffic metrics.
It uses eBPF to monitor network traffic between pods
and between pods and the internet.
The kubecost-agent pod collects metrics from the Kubernetes API.
It watches for new pods, deleted pods, scaled deployments, everything.
Wait for all pods to show status Running.
You can watch them in real time with the dash w flag.
kubectl get pods dash n kubecost dash w
The dash w flag watches for changes.
You'll see pods transition from Pending to ContainerCreating to Running.
When all pods are Running, press Ctrl C to exit.
If a pod stays in Pending for more than five minutes,
your cluster might not have enough resources.
Check your node sizes. Check your resource requests.
You might need to add more nodes or use larger nodes.
If a pod stays in CrashLoopBackOff,
something is wrong with the configuration.
Check the pod logs.
kubectl logs dash n kubecost pod-name dash dash previous
Replace pod-name with the actual name of the crashing pod.
The logs will usually tell you what's wrong.
Once all pods are running, port-forward to the Kubecost dashboard.
Port-forwarding creates a tunnel from your local machine
to the Kubecost service inside the cluster.
kubectl port-forward dash dash namespace kubecost
service/kubecost-cost-analyzer 9090:9090 ampersand
This command forwards traffic from port 9090 on your computer
to port 9090 on the kubecost-cost-analyzer service inside the cluster.
It will continue running until you press Ctrl C.
Keep this terminal window open.
Now open your browser. Go to http://localhost:9090.
You are looking at the Kubecost dashboard.
This is your window into Kubernetes cost.
This is the tool that will save you thousands of dollars.
Take a moment to look around. Click on things. Explore.
The first thing to look at is the Allocation page.
Click Allocation in the left menu.
If you don't see the menu, look for a hamburger icon
in the top left corner. Three horizontal lines.
Click it. The menu will slide out.
You'll see a table. Each row is a namespace.
The columns show CPU cost, RAM cost, storage cost, network cost,
and total cost.
There's also an Efficiency column.
That's the most important one.
Here is sample output. Your numbers will be different.
Namespace: financial-rag.
CPU cost: $1,420. RAM cost: $890. Total cost: $2,310. Efficiency: 0.48.
Namespace: riskoracle.
CPU cost: $980. RAM cost: $670. Total cost: $1,650. Efficiency: 0.61.
Namespace: kube-system.
CPU cost: $180. RAM cost: $120. Total cost: $300. Efficiency: 0.45.
Namespace: monitoring.
CPU cost: $95. RAM cost: $65. Total cost: $160. Efficiency: 0.38.
Namespace: kubecost.
CPU cost: $220. RAM cost: $130. Total cost: $350. Efficiency: 0.72.
Let me explain each column.
CPU Cost is the cost of the CPU resources allocated to pods
in this namespace.
Kubecost calculates this by looking at the CPU requests of all pods
in the namespace.
Then multiplying by the cost per CPU core from AWS.
If a pod requests two CPUs, Kubecost allocates the cost of two CPUs
to that pod, regardless of how much CPU the pod actually uses.
That's important. You pay for what you request, not what you use.
RAM Cost is the cost of the memory resources allocated to pods
in this namespace. Same principle.
Storage Cost is the cost of persistent volumes attached to pods
in this namespace.
If a pod has a persistent volume claim for a one hundred gigabyte
EBS volume, Kubecost allocates the cost of that volume
to the pod's namespace.
Network Cost is the cost of network traffic.
Cross-zone traffic. NAT Gateway traffic. Load balancer traffic.
Kubecost tracks it all.
Total Cost is the sum of CPU Cost, RAM Cost, Storage Cost,
and Network Cost.
Now look at the Efficiency column.
This is the most important number on the page.
Efficiency is the ratio of actual usage to requested resources.
Kubecost calculates it by looking at the actual CPU and memory usage
of every pod over the last seven days.
Comparing it to the requested CPU and memory.
And averaging across the namespace.
If a pod requests two CPUs but only uses one CPU,
its CPU efficiency is zero point five.
If it requests two CPUs and uses two CPUs, its efficiency is one point zero.
Kubecost aggregates these pod-level efficiencies up to the namespace level.
An efficiency of zero point seven means seventy percent
of requested resources are being used.
Thirty percent is idle. Thirty percent is waste.
Here's how to interpret efficiency scores.
If your efficiency is below zero point seven,
you are overprovisioning.
You are paying for resources you don't need.
You should reduce your CPU and memory requests.
You can safely reduce them because you have plenty of headroom.
Your pods are not using what they're asking for.
If your efficiency is above zero point nine,
you are underprovisioning.
Your pods are using almost all of their requested resources.
One small spike in traffic could cause CPU throttling
or memory pressure.
Your pods might get killed. Your application might slow down.
You should increase your CPU and memory requests
to give yourself more headroom.
The goal is efficiency between zero point seven and zero point eight five.
Enough headroom for spikes. Not so much headroom that you're wasting money.
This is the sweet spot. This is where you want to be.
Now let's get the same data from the command line.
Because you might want to script this.
You might want to include it in your baseline document.
You might want to automate reporting to Slack or email.
You might want to integrate it into your existing dashboards.
kubectl exec dash n kubecost deploy/kubecost-cost-analyzer dash dash
curl dash s http://localhost:9090/allocation?window=7d&aggregate=namespace
Pipe to jq .data zero to_entries array
get namespace, totalCost, efficiency
Let me break down this command. It's doing several things.
kubectl exec dash n kubecost deploy/kubecost-cost-analyzer
tells kubectl to execute a command inside the kubecost-cost-analyzer pod.
The dash n kubecost specifies the namespace.
deploy/kubecost-cost-analyzer specifies the deployment.
Kubectl will pick any pod in that deployment
and run the command there.
The dash dash separates kubectl arguments
from the command to run inside the pod.
Everything after dash dash is the command that runs inside the pod.
curl dash s http://localhost:9090/allocation?window=7d&aggregate=namespace
is the command inside the pod.
It uses curl to call the Kubecost API.
The API endpoint is allocation.
The parameters are window equals 7d for the last seven days
and aggregate equals namespace to group by namespace.
The dash s flag makes curl silent.
No progress meter, no error messages unless something fails.
The pipe symbol pipes the output of curl to jq.
jq is a command-line JSON processor.
It's like sed or awk for JSON.
The jq filter extracts the first element of the data array,
converts it to entries, then for each entry creates a new object
with namespace, cost, and efficiency.
You should see output like this.
namespace financial-rag, cost 2310, efficiency 0.48.
namespace riskoracle, cost 1650, efficiency 0.61.
namespace kube-system, cost 300, efficiency 0.45.
namespace monitoring, cost 160, efficiency 0.38.
namespace kubecost, cost 350, efficiency 0.72.
Now you have cost per namespace from the command line.
This is chargeback-ready data.
You can show each team exactly what they spend.
You can send this to your finance team.
You can include it in your monthly report.
Now let's look at cost by team label.
In Series one, you added a Team tag to all your AWS resources.
You tagged EC2 instances with Team equals financial-rag.
You tagged EBS volumes with Team equals riskoracle.
But Kubernetes doesn't know about AWS tags.
Kubernetes has its own labeling system.
You can add labels to Kubernetes namespaces.
Then Kubecost can aggregate costs by those labels.
First, label your namespaces with the team name.
kubectl label namespace financial-rag team=financial-rag
kubectl label namespace riskoracle team=risktoracle
kubectl label namespace monitoring team=platform
Now verify the labels were added.
kubectl get namespaces dash dash show-labels
You should see team equals financial-rag, team equals riskoracle.
Now query cost by that label.
kubectl exec dash n kubecost deploy/kubecost-cost-analyzer dash dash
curl dash s http://localhost:9090/allocation?window=7d&aggregate=label:team
Pipe to jq data zero to entries array get team, monthlyProjected, efficiency.
The aggregate equals label colon team parameter tells Kubecost
to group costs by the value of the team label.
Kubecost looks at every namespace, finds the team label,
and adds the namespace's cost to that team's total.
You should see output like this.
team financial-rag, monthlyProjected 2310, efficiency 0.48.
team riskoracle, monthlyProjected 1650, efficiency 0.61.
team platform, monthlyProjected 600, efficiency 0.45.
Now you have cost per team.
This is what your CTO wants to see.
This is what your finance team wants to see.
This is what each engineering manager wants to see.
No more guessing. No more spreadsheets. No more manual allocation.
Just data.
Now let's look at efficiency scores in more detail.
We want to find namespaces that are wasting money.
Add select efficiency less than zero point seven to the jq filter.
This filters out namespaces with efficiency below zero point seven.
Add wastedCPU and wastedRAMGB to see the exact waste.
wastedCPU is requested CPU minus actual usage.
wastedRAMGB is requested RAM minus actual usage in gigabytes.
You should see output like this.
namespace financial-rag, efficiency 0.48,
wastedCPU 3.2, wastedRAMGB 8.
namespace riskoracle, efficiency 0.61,
wastedCPU 1.8, wastedRAMGB 4.
Now you know exactly how much waste is in each namespace.
The financial-rag namespace is wasting three point two CPU cores
and eight gigabytes of RAM.
That's real money. That's resources you're paying for but not using.
Now let's look at rightsizing recommendations.
This is where Kubecost tells you exactly what to change.
Not just you're overprovisioned.
Not just you should reduce your requests.
Specific recommendations. For each deployment.
Current CPU request. Recommended CPU request.
Current RAM request. Recommended RAM request.
Estimated monthly savings.
kubectl exec dash n kubecost deploy/kubecost-cost-analyzer dash dash
curl dash s http://localhost:9090/savings/rightSizing?window=7d
Pipe to jq rightSizing zero to 15 dot array
get namespace, deployment, currentCPU, recommendedCPU, currentRAMGB,
recommendedRAMGB, monthlySavings
Sort by monthlySavings descending.
Let me break down this command.
The API endpoint is savings slash rightSizing.
The parameter window equals 7d tells Kubecost to look at the last seven days
of usage data.
The jq filter takes the first fifteen recommendations.
Then it creates an object with namespace, deployment, currentCPU,
recommendedCPU, currentRAMGB, recommendedRAMGB, and monthlySavings.
Then it sorts by monthlySavings descending.
You should see output like this.
namespace financial-rag, deployment llm-ingest.
currentCPU 8, recommendedCPU 2.
currentRAMGB 16, recommendedRAMGB 6.
monthlySavings 47.20
namespace financial-rag, deployment vector-db.
currentCPU 4, recommendedCPU 1.5.
currentRAMGB 32, recommendedRAMGB 12.
monthlySavings 89.30
namespace financial-rag, deployment batch-processor.
currentCPU 4, recommendedCPU 1.
currentRAMGB 8, recommendedRAMGB 3.
monthlySavings 34.10
namespace riskoracle, deployment risk-calc.
currentCPU 6, recommendedCPU 2.5.
currentRAMGB 24, recommendedRAMGB 10.
monthlySavings 62.40
These are your optimization targets.
Kubecost has analyzed the actual usage of every deployment
over the last seven days.
It calculated the ninety-fifth percentile of CPU usage.
The ninety-fifth percentile of memory usage.
Then it compared that to the requested resources.
And it gave you specific numbers.
The llm-ingest deployment requested eight CPUs.
Kubecost saw that the ninety-fifth percentile CPU usage was one point eight cores.
So it recommends reducing the CPU request to two cores.
That's a seventy-five percent reduction.
Monthly savings forty-seven dollars.
Now let's apply these recommendations.
For the llm-ingest deployment, you would update its resource requests.
The exact method depends on how you deploy your applications.
If you use Kubernetes YAML files, you edit the file.
If you use Helm, you update the values.
If you use Terraform, you update the Terraform configuration.
Here's how to patch a deployment directly with kubectl.
kubectl patch deployment llm-ingest dash n financial-rag
with json patch replace resources requests cpu to 2000m
replace resources requests memory to 6Gi
replace resources limits cpu to 4000m
replace resources limits memory to 8Gi
This command changes the deployment in place.
The deployment will restart.
Watch the rollout.
kubectl rollout status deployment/llm-ingest dash n financial-rag
The pods will come up with the new resource requests.
The cluster will have more free capacity.
The Cluster Autoscaler or Karpenter will detect the unused nodes
and remove them. Your EC2 bill will go down.
Now check for CPU throttling after applying.
CPU throttling is the silent performance killer.
A pod can be running with no OOMKills but severely throttled.
Requests taking three times longer because the CPU limit is too tight.
Check CPU throttling ratio.
kubectl exec dash n kubecost deploy/kubecost-cost-analyzer dash dash
curl dash s http://localhost:9090/metrics
Pipe to grep container_cpu_cfs_throttled_seconds_total
Or query Prometheus directly.
kubectl exec dash n kubecost deploy/prometheus-server-0 dash dash
wget dash qO dash http://localhost:9090/api/v1/query
Query rate of container_cpu_cfs_throttled_seconds_total over five minutes
greater than zero point one
If throttle ratio is greater than zero point one after rightsizing,
the CPU limit is too tight. Increase it.
Do not increase the request. Increase the limit.
The distinction between limit and request is critical.
Requests are what Kubernetes uses for scheduling.
What you pay for in Kubecost.
Limits are the hard ceiling. What prevents one pod from killing the node.
Always set limits higher than requests.
A good rule is limits equals two times requests for CPU.
One point five times requests for memory.
Now let's look at idle costs.
Idle costs are resources that are allocated but not used.
Pods that are running but not processing requests.
Nodes that are up but have low utilization.
Add idle equals true to the allocation API.
This tells Kubecost to include idle costs in the response.
Idle cost is the cost of resources that were allocated but not used.
You should see output like this.
namespace financial-rag, idleCost 1120
namespace riskoracle, idleCost 640
The financial-rag namespace has an idle cost of one thousand one hundred twenty dollars.
That's the cost of resources that were allocated but not used.
That's pure waste.
That's the money you can save by rightsizing.
Now let's look at your cluster's overall efficiency.
This is a single number that tells you how well your cluster is utilizing
its resources.
Aggregate equals cluster.
You should see a number like zero point five eight or zero point six five
or zero point seven two.
If your cluster efficiency is below zero point seven,
you have work to do. You are overprovisioning.
You are paying for resources you don't need.
You should apply the rightsizing recommendations.
You should reduce your resource requests.
You should let the cluster scale down.
If your cluster efficiency is above zero point eight five,
you are at risk of performance problems.
Your pods are using almost all of their requested resources.
One small spike in traffic could cause CPU throttling.
One memory leak could cause an OOM kill.
You should increase your resource requests to give yourself more headroom.
The ideal range is zero point seven to zero point eight five.
This is the sweet spot.
Enough headroom for spikes. Not so much headroom that you're wasting money.
Now let's save everything to your baseline document.
You created this document in Series one.
You updated it in Series two.
Now you're going to add your Kubecost findings.
echo three equals signs SERIES 3 KUBECOST DEPLOYMENT three equals signs
with date.
echo dash dash dash COST BY NAMESPACE dash dash dash
then the allocation command with jq.
echo dash dash dash CLUSTER EFFICIENCY dash dash dash
then the aggregate equals cluster command.
echo dash dash dash TOP RIGHTSIZING OPPORTUNITIES dash dash dash
then the rightsizing command with first five results.
echo dash dash dash TOTAL SAVINGS IDENTIFIED dash dash dash
then the savings endpoint.
Now view your updated baseline document.
cat tilde slash finops-baseline.txt
You should see your Series one baseline,
your Series two waste audit findings,
and your Series three Kubecost findings.
This document is your complete record.
It shows your starting point, your identified waste,
your visibility improvements, and your rightsizing recommendations.
Let's recap what you've built in Series three.
You deployed Kubecost on EKS.
You have a dashboard that shows cost per namespace,
cost per team, efficiency scores, and rightsizing recommendations.
You can open http://localhost:9090 anytime
to see your cluster's cost visibility.
You learned how to query the Kubecost API from the command line.
You can script these queries.
You can automate reporting. You can integrate cost data
into your existing dashboards.
You can send cost reports to Slack or email.
You learned how to interpret efficiency scores.
Below zero point seven means overprovisioning.
You're paying for resources you don't need.
Above zero point eight five means underprovisioning.
You're at risk of performance problems.
The sweet spot is zero point seven to zero point eight five.
You learned how to find idle costs.
Resources that are allocated but not used.
These are your optimization targets.
These are the dollars you can save.
You learned how to get rightsizing recommendations.
Kubecost tells you exactly what to change.
For each deployment. Current CPU request. Recommended CPU request.
Current RAM request. Recommended RAM request. Estimated monthly savings.
You learned how to apply those recommendations.
Update your deployment YAML.
Reduce CPU requests. Reduce memory requests.
Let the cluster scale down. Watch your bill drop.
You now have visibility that AWS Cost Explorer cannot provide.
Cost Explorer shows you EC2. Kubecost shows you namespace.
Cost Explorer shows you EBS. Kubecost shows you pod.
Cost Explorer shows you NAT Gateway. Kubecost shows you service.
This is the difference between guessing and knowing.
This is the difference between hoping your costs are optimized
and knowing they are.
This is the difference between being a junior engineer who runs commands
and a senior engineer who understands the system.
Here's what you need before Series four.
First, Kubecost must be running on your EKS cluster.
Run kubectl get pods dash n kubecost.
You should see all pods with status Running.
If any pods are not running, check the logs. Fix the issues.
Second, you must be able to access the Kubecost dashboard.
Run kubectl port-forward and open localhost 9090.
You should see the Allocation page with data.
If you see no data, wait a few minutes. Kubecost needs time to collect metrics.
Third, you must have cost per namespace data.
Run the API query from earlier. You should see JSON output with namespaces and costs.
If you see an empty array, your cluster might not have any pods.
Deploy financial-rag-agent or riskoracle to generate metrics.
Fourth, you must have at least one rightsizing recommendation.
Run the rightsizing API query.
You should see at least one deployment with currentCPU and recommendedCPU.
If you see no recommendations, your cluster might already be optimized.
Or your usage might be too low. Or your window might be too short.
Try increasing the window to 14d instead of 7d.
If you have all four, you're ready for Series four.
In Series four, we deploy Karpenter.
Karpenter is Kubernetes-native autoscaling.
It replaces the traditional Cluster Autoscaler.
It launches nodes in seconds instead of minutes.
It chooses the cheapest available instance types
from a list you provide.
It consolidates workloads to reduce the number of nodes.
It can save you thirty to forty percent on compute costs.
Where Kubecost shows you the waste,
Karpenter eliminates it automatically.
Let's go to Series four.
```
---
**END OF PHASE 3 — SERIES 3 COMPLETE**
**Total SRT lines:** 360
**Total duration:** Approximately 60-75 minutes
**What is covered in this SRT:**
| Section | Lines | Description |
|---------|-------|-------------|
| Why Cost Explorer Is Not Enough | 12-27 | The problem Kubecost solves |
| The Rest of the Story | 28-42 | Startup case study |
| Prerequisites | 44-80 | EKS cluster, kubectl, Helm, AWS CLI |
| Install Kubecost | 82-155 | Helm repo, namespace, install, pod explanations |
| Cost by Namespace | 156-221 | Allocation page, efficiency scores, CLI query |
| Cost by Team Label | 222-239 | Label namespaces, query by label |
| Efficiency Scores Deep Dive | 240-247 | Find overprovisioned namespaces |
| Rightsizing Recommendations | 248-271 | Get recommendations, interpret output |
| Apply Rightsizing | 272-294 | Patch deployment, check throttling |
| Idle Cost Analysis | 295-302 | Find allocated but unused resources |
| Cluster Efficiency | 303-313 | Single number for CTO |
| Update Baseline Document | 314-323 | Save findings |
| Recap & Prerequisites | 324-354 | What you built, what's needed for Series 4 |
| Series 4 Preview | 355-360 | What's coming next |