Welcome back to the course.
You have spent nine series building two things in parallel.
The first track. Series two through six found, eliminated,
and automated cost controls at the infrastructure level.
You cut the bill from forty-seven thousand dollars to nineteen thousand
four hundred four dollars.
The second track. Series seven through nine built a platform
that encodes those controls into every new service automatically.
New services are cost-optimized by default.
Developers never think about it.
But there is still a gap.
The controls are applied. The costs are tracked in Kubecost.
The budget annotations are in catalog-info.yaml.
But none of this is visible to the people who create the spend.
The developers and engineering managers using the platform every day.
Developers open the catalog and see deployment status, logs,
CI slash CD history. They do not see cost.
They do not see budget usage. They do not see whether their service
is running at forty-eight percent efficiency, wasting half its compute.
They do not see that they are approaching their team's monthly budget.
They only find out when the bill arrives. And by then it is too late to act.
Series ten changes that.
By the end, every developer who opens the catalog sees.
Their service's current monthly cost and trend versus last month.
Their team's budget progress with a red bar when approaching the limit.
Efficiency score and rightsizing recommendations.
Live cost anomaly alerts routed directly to service owners.
A FinOps homepage dashboard showing the full picture.
FinOps stops being something the platform team thinks about.
It becomes something every developer sees, every day,
as a natural part of their workflow.
Let me explain the architecture.
AWS Cost Explorer API feeds into Kubecost in the cluster.
Kubecost combines cost data with pod metrics like CPU, memory, and network.
The FinOps backend plugin in Backstage queries Kubecost.
It serves cost data to the frontend.
A budget scheduler runs daily at 9 AM.
It checks every service's budget and sends Slack alerts.
An anomaly detection webhook routes AWS cost anomalies to service owners.
A FinOps homepage dashboard shows total spend, team budgets, and top cost drivers.
Monthly chargeback reports go to the finance team.
First, let's create the FinOps backend plugin.
cd finops-idp.
npx at backstage slash cli new dash dash select backend-plugin
dash dash option id equals finops.
Install dependencies.
yarn at cwd plugins slash finops-backend add node-fetch,
at backstage slash catalog-client,
at slack slash web-api, and aws-sdk.
Now create the main plugin router.
Open plugins slash finops-backend slash src slash router.ts.
First endpoint. GET slash cost with namespace parameter.
Call the Kubecost allocation API for the last thirty days.
Call it again for the previous month.
Call the rightsizing API for the last seven days.
Extract current month cost, previous month cost, and forecast.
Forecast is a linear extrapolation. Current cost divided by day of month,
times days in month.
Extract efficiency, CPU cost, memory cost, storage cost,
network cost, and idle cost.
Return the cost data as JSON.
Second endpoint. GET slash rightsizing with optional namespace.
Call the Kubecost rightsizing API.
Return the recommendations sorted by monthly savings.
Include total monthly savings.
Third endpoint. GET slash dashboard.
Get all component entities from the catalog.
Get cluster-wide allocation from Kubecost.
Build per-team cost summary.
For each component, extract the owner and budget from annotations.
Add the cost to the team's total.
Calculate average efficiency.
Build top ten services by cost.
Sort by total cost descending.
Return total spend, team count, team summaries, and top services.
Fourth endpoint. POST slash anomaly-webhook.
Receive an anomaly payload from Kubecost.
Extract the namespace, impact amount, and root cause.
Find the service in the catalog by namespace.
Get the webhook URL from annotations.
Determine severity. Critical if impact over one thousand dollars.
High if over five hundred. Medium if over one hundred. Otherwise low.
Build a Slack message with the details.
Send it to the service's webhook.
Fifth endpoint. GET slash chargeback with format JSON or CSV.
Get allocation data from Kubecost for the requested month.
Get all components from the catalog.
Group costs by team. For each team, sum cost, sum budget,
calculate average efficiency.
If format is CSV, generate a CSV file for the finance team.
If format is JSON, return JSON.
Now create the budget alert scheduler.
Create a file called scheduler.ts in the finops-backend plugin.
The scheduler runs daily at 9 AM.
It fetches all components from the catalog.
For each component with a budget and a webhook.
Get the current cost from Kubecost.
Calculate the percentage of budget used.
Check against thresholds. Seventy-five, ninety, and one hundred percent.
If percentage exceeds a threshold and we haven't sent an alert
for that threshold in the last twenty-four hours, send a Slack alert.
The alert includes current spend, budget, remaining budget,
days left in month, and recommended actions.
Store the alert in memory to prevent duplicates.
In production, use Redis.
Register the scheduler in the plugin.
Use the backend scheduler service to schedule a task.
Frequency is cron zero nine star star star.
Now create the Cost Dashboard frontend component.
Create a file called CostDashboard.tsx in plugins slash finops slash src slash components.
The component fetches cost data from the backend API.
It fetches rightsizing recommendations.
It displays four metric cards. Monthly cost with trend.
Budget progress with colored bar.
Efficiency score with target guidance.
Savings available from rightsizing.
It shows a cost breakdown chart.
CPU, memory, storage, network, and idle costs.
It shows the top five rightsizing recommendations.
Each recommendation shows current CPU and recommended CPU.
Current RAM and recommended RAM. Monthly savings.
If budget is exceeded, it shows a red alert.
If efficiency is low, it shows a yellow warning.
Now create the FinOps homepage dashboard.
Create a file called FinOpsDashboard.tsx.
The dashboard shows total monthly spend across all teams.
Number of teams over or near budget.
Average cluster efficiency.
A team budget table shows each team's spend, budget,
progress bar, efficiency, service count, and status.
A top ten services table shows the most expensive services
with their cost and efficiency.
Add the dashboard to the Backstage homepage.
Open packages slash app slash src slash App.tsx.
Add a new route at slash finops.
Render the FinOpsDashboard component.
Now generate a monthly chargeback report.
curl to the chargeback endpoint with format equals json.
Pipe to python minus m json dot tool to view.
Download a CSV for the finance team.
curl to the chargeback endpoint with format equals csv.
Output to a file with the current date.
Quick summary. curl to the chargeback endpoint.
Use a Python one-liner to print total spend, team count,
and each team's spend.
Now configure Kubecost anomaly detection to send alerts to Backstage.
Configure Kubecost alerts to point at the Backstage webhook.
Set threshold to fifty dollars. Set window to one day.
Test the webhook manually with a curl POST.
Send a sample anomaly payload.
Now update your baseline document.
Add the FinOps plugin status.
Total spend, teams tracked, generated timestamp, teams over or near budget.
Add budget alert coverage.
Number of components with budget annotation.
Number of components with alert webhook.
Add a monthly chargeback snapshot.
Total spend and top five teams by spend.
Let me recap what you've built in Series ten.
You built a FinOps backend plugin.
Single API for all cost data in Backstage.
Cost per service, rightsizing recommendations, dashboard,
chargeback, and anomaly webhook.
You built a budget alert scheduler.
Daily nine AM cycle. Proactive alerts before month-end surprises.
You built a CostDashboard frontend component.
Live cost per service in the catalog.
Budget progress with threshold alerts.
Accountability at the service level.
Rightsizing recommendations in the catalog.
One-click path from cost visibility to action.
You built a FinOps homepage dashboard.
Company-wide cost health in one view.
You built a chargeback report endpoint.
JSON for engineering dashboards. CSV for the finance team.
Finance-ready monthly report.
You configured an anomaly webhook to route AWS cost anomalies
to service owners in Slack.
Here's what you need before Series eleven, the capstone.
First, the FinOps plugin running.
curl to the dashboard endpoint returns data.
Second, the Cost tab visible in the catalog for financial-rag-agent.
Third, a budget alert tested.
Manually trigger by lowering a threshold temporarily.
Fourth, a chargeback CSV downloaded and reviewed.
Fifth, the anomaly webhook tested.
Manual POST to the endpoint with a sample payload.
Sixth, your baseline document updated with final cost and budget coverage.
If you have all six, you're ready for Series eleven.
You have built everything. Every piece is working.
Every component is deployed.
Series eleven is the capstone.
The end-to-end demonstration and the final measurement of everything you accomplished.
You will start a fresh AWS account with a forty-seven thousand dollar per month
equivalent workload. Run through every optimization from Series two through six
in sequence.
Deploy the full IDP from Series seven through ten.
Create a new service through the golden path and trace it to production.
Trigger a budget alert and show the Slack notification.
Generate the final chargeback report.
Update the baseline document with before and after numbers.
Calculate the total annual savings.
The startup that started at forty-seven thousand dollars per month
ends at nineteen thousand four hundred four dollars per month.
A twenty-seven thousand five hundred ninety-six dollar monthly saving.
Three hundred thirty-one thousand one hundred fifty-two dollars per year.
More importantly, the platform ensures it stays there.
New engineers use the golden path. New services are cost-optimized automatically.
Budget alerts catch drift before it compounds.
The FinOps practice is self-sustaining.
That is what production FinOps engineering looks like.
Series eleven proves it.
Let's go to Series eleven.
```
---
**END OF PHASE 10 — SERIES 10 COMPLETE**
**Total SRT lines:** 162
**Total duration:** Approximately 50-60 minutes
**What is covered in this SRT:**
| Section | Lines | Description |
|---------|-------|-------------|
| Closing the Loop | 2-20 | The gap between cost controls and developer visibility |
| Architecture Overview | 22-28 | Data flow from AWS Cost Explorer to developer Slack |
| FinOps Backend Plugin | 29-64 | Five endpoints: cost, rightsizing, dashboard, anomaly webhook, chargeback |
| Budget Alert Scheduler | 65-76 | Daily 9 AM checks, Slack alerts, deduplication |
| Cost Dashboard Frontend | 77-86 | Metric cards, budget progress, efficiency, rightsizing |
| FinOps Homepage Dashboard | 87-96 | Team budget table, top services, company-wide view |
| Chargeback Report | 97-102 | JSON for engineering, CSV for finance |
| Anomaly Webhook | 103-106 | Configure Kubecost, manual test |
| Update Baseline | 107-113 | Plugin status, budget coverage, chargeback snapshot |
| Recap & Prerequisites | 114-143 | What you built, what's needed for Series 11 |
| Series 11 Preview | 145-162 | Capstone: end-to-end demonstration, final savings calculation |