Welcome back to the course.
In Series one, you built the foundation.
You learned what FinOps is. You learned the three phases.
You learned unit economics. You built a tagging strategy.
You ran your first Cost Explorer queries.
You created your baseline document.
That was the warm-up. That was the setup.
That was you learning the rules of the game.
Now it's time to play.
Series two is where we stop talking about waste
and start finding it.
Series two is where we stop being theoretical
and start being practical.
Series two is where you transform from someone
who knows about FinOps into someone who actually does FinOps.
By the end of this series, you will have identified
actual dollar amounts of waste in your AWS account.
Not estimated savings. Not projected savings.
Not hypothetical examples from a slide deck.
Real waste. Real dollars. Real numbers from your account,
your resources, your bill.
Let me tell you a story before we start.
Because stories stick. Stories help you remember why this matters.
I once worked with a startup. Series A.
Forty employees. Growing fast.
They had raised ten million dollars.
They were hiring. They were shipping.
They were doing all the things startups are supposed to do.
But their AWS bill was growing faster than their revenue.
Forty-seven thousand dollars a month. And growing.
Up and to the right. The kind of chart
that makes a CFO break into a cold sweat.
They thought it was normal.
After all, they were processing millions of RAG queries.
They had a large Kubernetes cluster.
They had multiple databases. They had data transfer costs.
They were doing real work. Real work costs real money.
But they had never done an audit.
They had never looked closely at the bill.
They had never asked the question:
is this normal, or is this waste?
I ran the audit. The same audit you are about to run.
Here is what I found.
Forty percent of their EC2 instances were at least twice
as large as they needed to be.
They had selected large instance types at launch, two years ago,
and never revisited the decision.
The workload hadn't grown. The instances hadn't changed.
But they were still paying for the large ones.
Monthly waste from overprovisioned EC2: eight thousand dollars.
They had twelve unattached Elastic IPs.
Twelve. Each one costing three dollars and sixty-five cents a month.
Doing absolutely nothing. Just sitting there in the account.
Reserved, allocated, but not attached to any instance.
Monthly waste: forty-three dollars and eighty cents.
Not huge. But symbolic.
If they were wasting money on something this obvious,
what else were they wasting money on?
All of their EBS volumes were gp2. Every single one.
Hundreds of volumes. None of them had been migrated to gp3.
Gp2 costs ten cents per gigabyte per month.
Gp3 costs eight cents per gigabyte per month.
Same performance. Same IOPS baseline.
Twenty percent cheaper. For zero work. For one command.
Monthly waste: twelve hundred dollars.
NAT Gateway was their fourth largest service.
They were sending all their S3 traffic through NAT Gateway.
S3 traffic through NAT Gateway costs four point five cents per gigabyte.
S3 traffic through VPC Endpoints is completely free.
They were paying for something that could be free.
Monthly waste: twenty-one hundred dollars.
S3 had no lifecycle policies. None.
They had fifteen terabytes of old data
that hadn't been accessed in over a year.
Some of it was three years old. Some of it was five years old.
All of it was in standard storage at two point three cents per gigabyte.
It should have been in Glacier at zero point four cents per gigabyte.
That's eighty percent cheaper.
Monthly waste from missing lifecycle policies: nine hundred dollars.
Total identified waste from the audit:
twelve thousand two hundred forty-three dollars and eighty cents per month.
Twenty-six percent of their bill.
Just from the audit. Just from looking.
Just from running the commands you are about to run.
No optimization yet. No rightsizing yet.
No Karpenter yet. No Spot instances yet. No Savings Plans yet.
Just finding the obvious waste.
The low-hanging fruit.
The stuff that should never have been there in the first place.
After implementing the fixes from Series two,
their bill dropped to thirty-four thousand eight hundred dollars.
They saved twelve thousand two hundred forty-three dollars
in the first month.
That's a hundred forty-six thousand dollars a year.
For a Series A startup with forty employees,
that's a real person. That's a hire.
That's a marketing budget. That's a sales team.
That's the difference between making payroll and not.
And here is the best part.
The fixes took less than a day.
A single day of work. Eight hours. One person.
Running commands. Saving a hundred forty-six thousand dollars a year.
That's a return on investment of forty thousand percent.
That's what Series two delivers.
Now let me show you how to do it.
Before we run any commands, let me remind you
about the environment variables we set in Series one.
You need these for every command in this course.
Every single command uses them.
If they're not set, the commands will fail.
If they're set incorrectly, the commands will give you wrong data.
So let's set them again. Even if you set them in Series one.
Even if you think they're still set. Set them again.
It takes five seconds. It saves twenty minutes of debugging.
Here are the commands.
export ACCOUNT_ID equals aws sts get-caller-identity
with query Account output text.
export REGION equals us-east-1, or your preferred region.
export START equals date dash d 30 days ago plus YYYY-MM-DD.
export END equals date plus YYYY-MM-DD.
Important note for macOS users.
The date command on macOS is different.
Instead of date dash d 30 days ago,
use date dash v dash 30d.
Now verify that they're set correctly.
Run echo for each variable.
echo dollar sign ACCOUNT_ID.
echo dollar sign REGION.
echo dollar sign START.
echo dollar sign END.
You should see your twelve-digit account ID.
You should see us-east-1 or whatever region you chose.
You should see a date that is thirty days ago.
You should see today's date.
If any of these are empty, go back and run the export commands again.
Make sure you copied them exactly.
Make sure there are no typos.
Make sure you didn't forget the dollar sign
or the parentheses or the quotes.
Now verify that Cost Explorer is accessible.
This is the same command from Series one.
It returns your total monthly spend.
aws ce get-cost-and-usage with time period Start END,
granularity MONTHLY, metrics BlendedCost, query amount, output text.
You should see a number. It might be zero if your account is new.
It might be a small number if you're just testing.
It might be a large number if you're in production.
Whatever it is, write it down.
This is your baseline. This is the number
you're going to reduce over the next ten series.
If you get an error that says "Invalid time period",
check your START and END variables.
Run echo for each. They should be in YYYY-MM-DD format.
If they're not, the date command might be different on your operating system.
If you get an error that says "Access denied"
or "Unauthorized operation",
your IAM user doesn't have permission to read Cost Explorer.
You need the AWSBillingReadOnlyAccess policy.
Go back to Series one and add that policy to your user.
If you get an empty response with no number,
your account might have zero spend. That's fine for testing.
But if you're in production and you see zero,
something is wrong.
Your credentials might be pointing to the wrong account.
Run get-caller-identity to see which account you're in.
Now you're ready to find waste.
The first command in any audit is total spend by service.
This is your opening slide.
This is what you show your CTO.
This is the table that makes everything else make sense.
Here is the command.
aws ce get-cost-and-usage with time period Start END,
granularity MONTHLY, metrics BlendedCost,
group-by type DIMENSION key SERVICE,
query results by time zero groups with blended cost amount greater than ten,
output table.
Run it. Paste it into your terminal. Hit enter.
Let me explain what you're running.
Understanding is more important than copying.
Time period uses your START and END variables.
START is thirty days ago. END is today.
You're looking at the last thirty days of spend.
Thirty days is the standard for monthly reporting.
It matches your AWS bill. It matches your finance team's expectations.
Granularity is MONTHLY.
This tells Cost Explorer to give you one number per month.
One row for EC2. One row for EKS.
One row for RDS. One row for S3.
One row for NAT Gateway. Clean and simple.
Metrics use BlendedCost. This is important.
AWS has two cost metrics. Blended cost and unblended cost.
Unblended cost is the list price. The sticker price.
The price before any discounts. It's what AWS publishes on their website.
But almost no one pays that.
Most startups have discounts. Most use Savings Plans.
Most use Reserved Instances. So unblended cost is misleading.
Blended cost is what you actually pay after all discounts.
After Savings Plans. After Reserved Instances.
After volume discounts. It's the real number.
The number that actually hits your bank account.
Always use blended cost.
Group by service is the magic.
This transforms a confusing bill into a clear table.
EC2 gets its own row. EKS gets its own row.
RDS gets its own row. S3 gets its own row.
Every service gets its own row.
The query filters out any service that costs less than ten dollars.
That removes all the tiny charges.
The fifty cents for Route53 health checks.
The two dollars for CloudWatch logs.
You don't need those on your opening slide. They're noise.
Now look at your output.
The top row is almost always EC2.
Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud. That's your virtual machines.
Your compute. Your servers. This is where most of your money goes.
That's normal. That's expected. Compute is expensive.
Compute is what does the work.
Now look at the second, third, and fourth rows.
This is where you find your opportunities.
Let me give you a real-world interpretation guide.
If NAT Gateway is in your top five, that's a red flag.
NAT Gateway is expensive.
It means you're sending a lot of traffic through NAT Gateway.
Some of that traffic might be to S3 or DynamoDB.
And all of that traffic could be free through VPC Endpoints.
If EKS is high and you have multiple clusters,
that's waste. Each EKS cluster costs seventy-three dollars per month.
If you have three clusters, that's two hundred nineteen dollars.
If you have five, that's three hundred sixty-five dollars.
Could you consolidate development and staging into one cluster?
Could you use namespaces to separate environments instead of separate clusters?
If RDS is in your top three, you have databases.
The biggest waste in RDS is development databases running twenty-four seven.
No one uses them at three in the morning.
No one uses them on weekends.
But they're running. They're costing money.
You can add stop and start schedules. That's sixty percent savings.
If S3 is in your top five, S3 is cheap.
Two point three cents per gigabyte.
But cheap times a lot is still expensive.
If you have one hundred terabytes in S3, that's two thousand three hundred dollars a month.
Do you need all of it in standard storage?
Could some of it be in cheaper tiers?
Do you have lifecycle policies to move old data automatically?
Write down your top five services.
These are your optimization targets.
Now save this to your baseline document.
You created this document in Series one. Now add to it.
echo three equals signs SERIES 2 WASTE AUDIT three equals signs
with date.
Then echo three equals signs SPEND BY SERVICE three equals signs.
Then run the same cost command and append the output to your baseline file.
Now let's look at daily cost trends.
This finds anomalies, spikes, drops, and patterns.
Things that don't look right.
Run the same cost command but change granularity to DAILY.
aws ce get-cost-and-usage with time period Start END,
granularity DAILY, metrics BlendedCost,
query results by time zero start and blended cost amount,
output table.
You'll see thirty rows, one for each day.
Each row has a date and a cost.
Now look for patterns.
Do you see a spike on a particular day?
Each spike is a story. What happened that day?
Did you deploy a new service?
Did a batch job run longer than expected?
Did a misconfigured auto-scaler spin up too many instances?
Do you see a drop on weekends?
That's good. That means your workloads follow business hours.
That means you have opportunities to scale down on weekends.
If you see no drop on weekends, your workloads run twenty-four seven.
Ask yourself if they need to.
Do you see a gradual increase over time?
That's natural. Workloads grow.
But is the increase proportional to business growth?
If your cost goes up ten percent per month but revenue goes up five percent,
that's a problem.
Do you see a sudden step up that never goes back down?
Something changed on that day and never changed back.
What was it? A new service? Larger instance sizes?
A feature left on?
Investigate the spikes. Look at the date.
Look at your deployment logs. Look at CloudTrail events.
Ask your team what changed.
You'll often find something obvious.
A test left running. A debug flag left enabled.
A load test that wasn't cleaned up.
Now let's look at cost by region.
This finds resources running in regions you don't use.
Run the cost command again. Group by region instead of service.
Query for all groups. Output as a table.
You'll see a table of regions and costs.
If your primary region is us-east-1, Northern Virginia,
you should see most of your cost there. That's your home.
If you see significant cost in us-west-2, Oregon,
someone created resources on the west coast. Why?
Maybe they were testing latency. Maybe they wanted disaster recovery.
Maybe they misconfigured Terraform.
Maybe a developer spun up resources for a demo
and forgot to tear them down.
If you see cost in eu-west-1, Ireland,
someone created resources in Europe. Why?
Maybe you have European customers. Maybe you need GDPR compliance.
Investigate.
If you see cost in a region you don't recognize,
like Sao Paulo, Bahrain, or Cape Town, definitely investigate.
Those regions are usually not the default.
Someone intentionally chose them.
Now find the actual resources.
Loop through each region.
For each region, describe EC2 instances.
for region in us-west-1 us-west-2 eu-west-1,
do echo checking region, then aws ec2 describe-instances.
If you see any IDs, you have instances in that region.
Then describe volumes in each region.
Then describe RDS instances. Then list S3 buckets.
S3 is global, but you can see which region each bucket is in.
For any bucket you don't recognize, get its location.
Once you find stray resources, you have three options.
Option one: migrate them to your primary region.
This is work, but worth it if the resource is important.
Option two: delete them.
If the resource is not important, just terminate, delete, and remove.
Option three: tag them and add them to your regular reporting.
If the resource is supposed to be in that region, tag it with the region name.
Then include it in your regular cost reporting.
But don't ignore it. Tag it. Track it. Own it.
Now save cost by region to your baseline document.
Echo a header, run the command, and append the output.
Now let's talk about cost anomaly detection.
This saves you from surprise bills.
You enable it once. It runs forever.
It watches your spend. It learns your patterns.
And it alerts you when something unexpected happens.
Before you see it on the bill.
First, create an anomaly monitor.
Use create-anomaly-monitor.
Give it a name like finops-monitor.
Set the type to DIMENSIONAL. Set the dimension to SERVICE.
This monitor watches for anomalies by service.
It looks at EC2 spend, EKS spend, RDS spend, S3 spend, and NAT Gateway spend.
If any service deviates from its historical pattern,
the monitor detects it.
If EC2 spend doubles in a day, you'll know.
If NAT Gateway spend triples in a week, you'll know.
If a new service appears, you'll know.
Now get the monitor ARN.
You need this to create a subscription.
Use get-anomaly-monitors and query for the ARN.
MONITOR_ARN equals that output.
Now create an anomaly subscription.
Use create-anomaly-subscription.
Give it a name like finops-alerts.
Provide the monitor ARN in a list.
Add a subscriber with your email address.
Set the threshold to fifty dollars. Set frequency to DAILY.
The threshold is the minimum anomaly impact to trigger an alert.
Fifty means any anomaly that changes your spend by fifty dollars or more
triggers an alert.
You can set this lower for small anomalies
or higher to avoid noise.
Frequency DAILY means you get a summary once per day.
You can also use IMMEDIATE for real-time alerts.
Now check for existing anomalies from the last seven days.
Use get-anomalies with date interval from seven days ago to today.
Query for the service and total impact.
Run this command. Are there any anomalies?
If yes, investigate. What caused the spike?
Was it expected? A deployment? A load test? A misconfiguration?
Should you adjust your monitoring to ignore that kind of spike
in the future?
Now let's talk about the easiest win in the entire audit.
Gp2 to gp3 migration.
Twenty percent savings. Zero downtime. One command.
Same baseline performance.
Let me explain the difference.
Gp2 is the older generation of general purpose SSD volumes.
It costs ten cents per gigabyte per month.
It provides a baseline of three IOPS per gigabyte.
A one hundred gigabyte volume gets three hundred IOPS baseline.
It can burst to three thousand IOPS, but bursting is limited.
Gp3 is the newer generation.
It costs eight cents per gigabyte per month. Twenty percent cheaper.
It provides a baseline of three thousand IOPS regardless of size.
Even a one gigabyte volume gets three thousand IOPS.
It also provides one hundred twenty-five megabytes per second
of throughput baseline. Gp2 doesn't have a throughput baseline.
Gp3 is cheaper, faster, and more consistent.
There is no reason to use gp2 anymore.
Every gp2 volume should be migrated.
Here's how to find all your gp2 volumes.
aws ec2 describe-volumes with filter volume-type gp2.
Query volume ID, size, state, and name tag. Output as a table.
How many volumes do you see?
Each one is a candidate for migration.
Now calculate potential savings.
A one hundred gigabyte gp2 volume costs ten dollars per month.
Gp3 costs eight dollars. Savings of two dollars per month.
A one terabyte volume saves twenty dollars per month.
Ten terabytes saves two hundred dollars per month.
Now migrate a single volume to gp3.
Use modify-volume. Provide the volume ID.
Set volume type to gp3. Set IOPS to three thousand.
Set throughput to one hundred twenty-five.
Replace the volume ID with your actual ID.
Three thousand IOPS is the baseline. You can go higher if needed,
but higher costs more.
One hundred twenty-five throughput is the baseline.
Now monitor the migration progress.
Use describe-volumes-modifications.
Query for volume ID, modification state, target volume type, and progress.
The modification state can be modifying, optimizing, or completed.
Modifying means the change is in progress.
The volume is usable during this time.
Performance might be reduced, but it works.
Optimizing means the modification is complete
but performance is still improving. This can take hours.
Completed means the modification is fully complete.
The volume is now gp3. Performance is at the target level.
The whole process takes between one and forty-eight hours.
You don't need to wait. The volume is usable during migration.
Now migrate all gp2 volumes at once.
Find every gp2 volume ID.
Loop through each ID. For each volume, run the modify-volume command.
One command. Zero downtime. Twenty percent savings.
Now let's find unattached Elastic IPs.
These are pure waste. Each one costs three dollars and sixty-five cents per month.
Doing nothing. Just sitting there.
What is an Elastic IP? It's a static public IP address
you can allocate to your AWS account.
You can attach it to an EC2 instance, a NAT Gateway, or a load balancer.
When attached, it's useful. When not attached, it's waste.
AWS charges for unattached Elastic IPs
because they're scarce resources.
There are a limited number of public IP addresses.
If you're hoarding them, AWS wants you to either use them or release them.
Here's how to find unattached Elastic IPs.
Describe addresses. Query for addresses with no association ID.
Show allocation ID, public IP, and domain. Output as a table.
The query filters for addresses that have no AssociationId.
AssociationId is set when the EIP is attached to something.
If there's no AssociationId, the EIP is unattached.
How many rows do you see?
Each row is an unattached EIP.
Each one costs three dollars and sixty-five cents a month.
For five EIPs, that's eighteen dollars a month.
For ten, thirty-six dollars. For twenty, seventy-three dollars.
Now release them.
Find every unattached EIP allocation ID.
Loop through each ID. For each ID, run release-address.
The address goes back to the AWS pool. You stop paying for it.
Now let's find stopped instances.
Stopped instances don't charge for compute.
But their EBS volumes still do.
A stopped instance with a one hundred gigabyte gp3 volume costs eight dollars per month.
Even though it's doing nothing. Even though it's not running.
Why would you stop an instance instead of terminating it?
Maybe you want to preserve the data.
Maybe you want to keep the configuration.
Maybe you're not sure if you'll need it again.
But if an instance has been stopped for more than seven days,
you probably don't need it.
If it's been stopped for more than thirty days,
you definitely don't need it.
If it's been stopped for more than ninety days,
you should have terminated it already.
Here's how to find stopped instances.
Describe instances. Filter for state name stopped.
Query for instance ID, type, and name tag. Output as a table.
How many stopped instances do you see?
Each one is a candidate for termination.
For each stopped instance, ask these questions.
Why is it stopped? Was it intentional? By a script?
Because it failed?
When was it stopped? Check the state transition reason field.
If it was stopped more than thirty days ago, terminate it.
Who stopped it? Check CloudTrail.
Who ran the stop instances API call? Can you ask them why?
Does anyone need it? Send an email to the team.
Give them a deadline. If no one responds, terminate it.
If the instance has important data, snapshot the volumes first.
Use create-snapshot with a description that includes the date.
Then terminate the instance with terminate-instances.
Now let's find unattached EBS volumes.
These are volumes not attached to any instance.
Just sitting there. Costing money. Doing nothing.
Why would you have an unattached volume?
Maybe you detached it from an instance and forgot to delete it.
Maybe you created a volume from a snapshot but never attached it.
Maybe a script created a volume and failed to attach it.
Here's how to find unattached volumes.
Describe volumes. Filter for status available.
Query for volume ID, size, type, and creation time.
Output as a table.
Status available means the volume is not attached to any instance.
It's available to be attached, but it's not.
How many unattached volumes do you see?
Each one costs money.
A one hundred gigabyte gp3 volume costs eight dollars a month.
A one terabyte volume costs eighty dollars.
Ten volumes cost eight hundred dollars.
Ask the same questions. Why is it unattached?
When was it created? Who created it?
Does anyone need it? Can you delete it?
If you're not sure, snapshot it first.
Here's a bulk snapshot and delete script.
Find every unattached volume ID.
Loop through each ID. Create a snapshot with a description that includes the date.
The delete command is commented out for safety.
Run the script first to create snapshots.
Review them. Make sure you don't need them.
Then uncomment the delete command and run again.
Now let's find old snapshots.
Snapshots older than ninety days with no deletion policy.
Each snapshot costs money.
Old snapshots that are no longer needed are waste.
Why would you have old snapshots?
Maybe you created them for backup and forgot to set a retention policy.
Maybe you created them before a migration and never cleaned up.
Maybe a script created them and never deleted them.
Here's how to find old snapshots.
Describe snapshots for your account ID.
Query for snapshots created more than ninety days ago.
Show snapshot ID, date, and size. Output as a table.
How many old snapshots do you see?
Each one is a candidate for deletion.
For each old snapshot, ask these questions.
Why was it created? When? Does anyone need it? Can you delete it?
Check the snapshot description.
Many snapshots are created automatically by backup tools.
Those tools usually have deletion policies.
If a snapshot has no deletion policy, it's probably orphaned.
Now let's talk about NAT Gateway.
This is the silent killer.
NAT Gateway is expensive.
And most of the traffic going through it doesn't need to.
First, see how much you're spending on NAT Gateway.
Run the cost command. Filter for usage type group EC2 colon NAT Gateway.
Query for the amount.
How much are you spending?
For a moderately busy cluster, it's often hundreds of dollars a month.
For a busy cluster, it can be thousands.
Now let's fix it.
The problem is that most startups send all their traffic
through NAT Gateway.
Including traffic to S3 and DynamoDB.
S3 and DynamoDB traffic through NAT Gateway costs four point five cents per gigabyte.
But through VPC Endpoints, it's completely free.
VPC Endpoints are free.
No hourly charge. No data transfer charge. Completely free.
Why doesn't everyone use them?
Because most people don't know they exist.
Or they think they're complicated or expensive.
They're not. They're free and easy.
Here's how to create a VPC Endpoint for S3.
First, get your VPC ID.
Describe VPCs. Filter for non-default VPCs. Query for the first VPC ID.
Second, get your route table IDs.
Describe route tables. Filter for your VPC ID. Query for route table IDs.
Third, create the VPC Endpoint for S3.
Use create-vpc-endpoint.
Provide your VPC ID. Provide the service name for S3 in your region.
Provide the route table IDs. Set the type to gateway.
That's it. Now all S3 traffic from your VPC
goes through the free endpoint instead of the expensive NAT Gateway.
Now do the same for DynamoDB.
Use the same command with the DynamoDB service name.
Now S3 and DynamoDB traffic is free.
Your NAT Gateway bill will drop immediately.
For other services like ECR, Secrets Manager, and CloudWatch,
you need interface endpoints.
Interface endpoints cost one cent per hour per Availability Zone.
That's seven dollars and twenty cents per month per zone.
For three zones, that's twenty-one dollars and sixty cents per month.
If you're spending more than that on NAT Gateway traffic
to those services, the interface endpoint saves you money.
The break-even point is about three hundred gigabytes per month.
Now let's find idle load balancers.
Load balancers with no healthy targets.
They're running. They're costing money.
But they're not serving traffic.
First, list all load balancers.
Describe load balancers. Query for ARN, name, type, and state.
For each load balancer, check its target groups.
Describe target groups. Query for target group ARN and load balancer ARN.
Then for each target group, describe target health.
Count how many targets are healthy.
If a load balancer has zero healthy targets, it's idle.
Delete it. Or fix the target group. But don't leave it running.
Now let's put it all together.
Here's a complete waste audit summary script.
Echo a header. Then get the count of gp2 volumes.
Estimate monthly savings assuming one hundred gigabytes average.
Get the count of unattached EIPs.
Estimate savings at three dollars sixty-five cents each.
Get the count of stopped instances.
Estimate savings assuming one hundred gigabyte EBS each.
Get the count of unattached volumes.
Estimate savings assuming one hundred gigabytes each.
Get the NAT Gateway cost.
Estimate savings after VPC endpoints at fifty to one hundred percent.
Run this script. Write down the numbers.
These are your identified savings.
This is what you've found just by running the commands
in Series two.
Now save everything to your baseline document.
Echo each finding with its count or cost.
Let's recap what you've built in Series two.
You ran your first real cost discovery commands.
Total spend by service. Daily cost trends. Cost by region.
You identified your top five cost drivers.
You know where to focus your optimization efforts.
You enabled cost anomaly detection.
You created a monitor that watches for unexpected spend.
You created a subscription that alerts you when anomalies are detected.
You'll never be surprised by a bill again.
You found every gp2 volume in your account.
You migrated them to gp3. Twenty percent savings. Zero downtime. One command.
You found every unattached Elastic IP.
You released them. No more three dollar sixty-five cent paperweights.
You found stopped instances still paying for EBS volumes.
You snapshotted and terminated them.
You found unattached EBS volumes.
You snapshotted and deleted them.
You found old snapshots.
You reviewed and deleted the ones you didn't need.
You analyzed your NAT Gateway cost.
You created VPC Endpoints for S3 and DynamoDB.
Free traffic instead of expensive traffic.
You found idle load balancers.
You deleted the ones with no healthy targets.
By the end of Series two, you have identified
actual dollar amounts of waste in your AWS account.
Not estimated. Not projected. Not theoretical.
Actual waste from your account, your resources, your bill.
And you have a plan to eliminate every dollar.
Here's what you need before Series three.
First, your baseline document must be updated
with the waste audit findings.
Run cat on your baseline file to verify.
You should see the waste audit findings at the bottom.
Second, you should have migrated at least one gp2 volume to gp3.
Run describe-volumes-modifications to check the status.
The modification state should be completed or optimizing.
Third, you should have released at least one unattached EIP.
Run describe-addresses to verify. You should see fewer addresses than before.
Fourth, you should have created VPC Endpoints for S3 and DynamoDB.
Run describe-vpc-endpoints to verify.
You should see endpoints for S3 and DynamoDB with state available.
If you have all four, you're ready for Series three.
In Series three, we deploy Kubecost on EKS.
We get cost visibility at the namespace level.
We see exactly which team is spending what.
We see efficiency scores. We see idle CPU and memory costs.
We stop guessing. We start knowing.
Let's go to Series three.
---
**END OF PHASE 2 — SERIES 2 COMPLETE**
**Total SRT lines:** 364
**Total duration:** Approximately 60-75 minutes
**What is covered in this SRT:**
| Audit Step | Lines | Description |
|------------|-------|-------------|
| Environment Setup | 57-88 | Variables, verification, troubleshooting |
| Total Spend by Service | 89-137 | Opening slide, interpretation guide, save to baseline |
| Daily Cost Trends | 138-157 | Spikes, drops, patterns, anomaly investigation |
| Cost by Region | 158-180 | Find stray resources, loop through regions |
| Cost Anomaly Detection | 181-202 | Create monitor, subscription, check anomalies |
| gp2 to gp3 Migration | 203-235 | Find, calculate savings, migrate single, migrate all |
| Unattached Elastic IPs | 236-250 | Find, calculate waste, release |
| Stopped Instances | 251-268 | Find, decision framework, snapshot, terminate |
| Unattached EBS Volumes | 269-284 | Find, snapshot, delete |
| Old EBS Snapshots | 285-294 | Find, review, delete |
| NAT Gateway + VPC Endpoints | 295-320 | Find cost, create endpoints for S3 and DynamoDB |
| Idle Load Balancers | 321-326 | Find, check health, delete |
| Waste Summary Script | 327-335 | Complete audit summary |
| Recap & Prerequisites | 336-360 | What you built, what's needed for Series 3 |
| Series 3 Preview | 361-364 | What's coming next |